<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[A discourse for parents honour and authoritie Written respectiuely to reclaime a young man that was a counterfeit Iesuite.]</title>
            <title>De patrio jure. English</title>
            <author>Ayrault, Pierre, 1536-1601.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1614</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 243 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 91 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00123</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1012</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118975</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854182</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854182</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19591</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00123)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19591)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 650:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[A discourse for parents honour and authoritie Written respectiuely to reclaime a young man that was a counterfeit Iesuite.]</title>
                  <title>De patrio jure. English</title>
                  <author>Ayrault, Pierre, 1536-1601.</author>
                  <author>Budden, John, 1566-1620.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 170 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E. Griffin for W. Harper and T. Harper,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1614]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of: De patrio jure.</note>
                  <note>Title and imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A discourse for parents honour, and authority.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; lacks title page.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Emmanuel College (University of Cambridge). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Parent and child --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19591:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19591:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>¶ To the moſt reuerend Father in God, TOBIE by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine prouidence Archbiſhop <hi>of</hi> YORKE, <hi>Primate and</hi> Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolitane, of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y Moſt reuerend good Lord, The late experience of ſome defections and reuolts in children of lewde behauior, which haue contemptuouſly prophaned all obedience to parents, together with ſome deſire of mine owne, to retaine the wauering diſpoſitions of others, which may be in like ieopardie to be abuſed here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, haue put me into a buſineſſe would God ſo helpfull for them, as neceſſarie for the time, I meane this Engliſh tranſlation, of a moſt exceſtent Latin Originall. It treateth for the honorable maintenance of parents au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, and was compiled ſome fiue and
<pb facs="tcp:19591:2"/>twenty yeeres ſince by the famous French Ciuilian <hi>Petrus Aerodius,</hi> in purpoſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime his ſonne <hi>Renatus,</hi> who at that time, being vnder age, and without his fathers leaue had betaken himſelfe to the Ieſuites, company. Doubtleſſe, the good parents griefe for an iniurie of ſuch hainous qualitie, (if he may be heard ſpeaking out of the tender bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wells of his affection,) is euer within mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure though it be excesſiue, iuſt, though paſt hope of recouery. A ſonne, nay the eldeſt ſon, the firſt fruits of his ſtrength, ſo faire a bud, to be ſtript from his naturall barke perforce, and inoculated in a ſtocke of aſtrange kind, would abate the imputation of being cenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red pasſionate without a cauſe: euery man, to my thinking, vpon the ſuppoſall of ſuch a perſon, being apt to acknowledge ſo much in himſelfe, and that in the Poets phraſe, Huic vniforſan poteram ſuccumbere culpae, The dignity of the diſcourſe, needs no enlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by a preface, for (if too much increduli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ouerweene not my iudgement) the moſt cenſorious Criticke, if he find patience to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe it in the natiue edition, will in meer iuſtice
<pb facs="tcp:19591:2"/>commend moſt, or allow all. The ſtile is cloſe wrought, and full of ſtuffe, the choice of his words apt and frugall, the ſentences deepe and ponderous, the ſhafts of his arguments, drawne by a ſtrong arme vp to the head, the nouelty of examples delightfull, the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties venerable, yet infinitly various, his dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling faire and fatherlike, contending, rather for truth than conqueſt. Now might I take ſo much preſumption vpon me, as to hope of ſome degree of your Graces good acceptance, (to whom eſpeciallie, for diſcourſe or title it is moſt properly belonging) I would farther alleadge for my ſelfe, that I haue often ſeene my worthy predeceſſor M. <hi>Doctor Gentilis,</hi> his Maieſties profeſſor for the Ciuill lawes, reading me ſome Lectures, and teaching me how to offend in this kinde, whom I euer found of this opinion, that his excellent Lucubrations neuer proſpered bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than when they receiued luſtre from your Graces iudicious confirmation: to whom, as he was very much obliged, ſo was he not ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring rather by preuenting occaſion than by taking it, thankfully to report the ſame. And
<pb facs="tcp:19591:3"/>laſtly becauſe the age wherein we liue, is ſo much viſited with an Epidemiall diſtemper of diſobedience, the cure would be ſought for at their hands, who by reaſon of their eminent place of practice, beſt know (out of their great learning) to apply ſoueraigne anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotes againſt ſuch malignant qualities: and if that will not worke, then me thinks <hi>Lucius Brutus</hi> his ſeuerity well allaied would not come out of ſeaſon, that derobed himſelfe of all reſpects of a father, that he might the better act the part of a Conſull, <hi>exuit patrem vt Conſulem ageret.</hi> For ſuch auſteritie in parents many times proues pitty, and is powerfull, to make obedience where it finds none. A reformation of ſo generall impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance that euery man may be ſaid to haue a part in it, though he can challenge no proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, becauſe <hi>quod commune eſt meum eſt,</hi> and (without peraduenture) an vndutifull ſonne ſo reclaimed to his naturall obedience is that <hi>commune bonum.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Graces in all humble ſeruice to be commanded, IOHN BVDDEN.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:19591:3"/>
            <head>¶ The Author to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing for three whole yeeres together, made continuall enquirie after my eldeſt ſonne, and that to ſmall purpoſe, (for hee is among the Ieſuits) I am now deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined to preſent that to publique view, which otherwiſe I ſhould haue ſeque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred to priuate vſe. I treat with him as with an offender, that contemptuouſlie refuſeth to make his appearance, and as a man ſhould doe wth a runaway, that is, by writ of outlarie, and proclamation of rebellion. Therefore I beſeech thee
<pb facs="tcp:19591:4"/>good Reader, if this expoſtulation and complaint of mine appeare vnto thee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together cauſeleſſe, and if it happilie ſo fall out, that thou meet with this poor youth, thus eſloigned and ſeduced from me, be ameanes, that he may ſometimes peruſe this ſmall treatiſe: then if he find himſelfe reſolued, to bee at his owne reines, and diſpoſing, I paſſe not, father or not father, whether he ſo take me or ſo refuſe me. From <hi>Angiers</hi> 1589 in <hi>October.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19591:4"/>
            <head>A DISCOVRSE for Parents honour, and <hi>Authority ouer their</hi> Children.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat is the reaſon that the famous Doctor <hi>Gregory Nazianzene</hi> in his oration Apologeticall which hee made to the people ſaith, that there is a great deale more in the authority apertaining to parents which is giuen the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from almighty God, than in that which hath bin eſtabliſhed by men, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in their written lawes, or long continued cuſtoms? Is it ſo that this one commandement <hi>Honour thy Father and thy Mother</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunds more with children, than that hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deous thunderclap of <hi>diſinheriting</hi> them, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented by the Grecians, or then the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:19591:5"/>of life and death, which though it be deteſtable in nature, yet was it our owne French law, and in vſe likewiſe with many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther nations beſide; or then thoſe three ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne alienations, whereby children were freede from their parents ſubiection, and ſo many counterſales, which made them bond againe: deuiſes (as it is well knowne) of the Romane policy? Should the ſonne beene found diſobedient to his Father, by theſe lawes, the father did right himſelfe, and was both accuſer, witneſſe and iudge. Moreouer the execution of puniſhments, whereunto he might ſentence them, were of ſuch nature, as the very repreſentation of them to their me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories (they were ſo bloudy &amp; cruell) might preſently deterre from attempting or enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the leaſt breach of their bounden duety: but on Gods part, a bare commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment onely is ſufficient: be the childe duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, theres a reward for him; be he obſtinate, theres no puniſhment inflicted. And yet wee ſay, that lawes preuaile more when they bee penall, then when they ſimply doe but will and require, and that authority is more awful, which is properly our owne, and exerciſed in our owne name and right, then that forſooth which is indented with couenants, and taken vpon curteſie from an other.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:19591:5"/>
            <p> Now ſir, how wrought that ſame ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne fatherly authority, I meane that which iſſued from the prouiſion of man, and not from the ſacred conſtitution of God? why it wrought thus much, that this priuate diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, did ſometimes farre exceede the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, inſomuch, that wherein the Magiſtrates immediate authority ſeemed feeble and in a manner maymed, there the domeſtique diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline (being appealed vnto as to an higher iuriſdiction) gaue preſent help and aſſiſtance; that is to ſay, parents were able to doe more with their children, then law or legion, or Dictator himſelfe. <hi>Cn. Martius Coriola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> marched forth with a dangerous army, againſt his country, breathing forth nothing but ruine and vaſtation, whomade him to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arme himſelf, forſake his enſignes, &amp; leaue the commaund of the field but <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eturia</hi> only? He that neither yeelded to Senators ſent vnto him, nor Magiſtrates, nor prieſts, yeelded to his mother. He that neither the Maieſty of the Empire, nor any touch of religion could cauſe once to retire, did ſoone relent at the name of his mother.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cn. Seruilius, L. Sergius, M. Papirius,</hi> being Tribunes together, and in like authority, which was alſo Conſular, were vehement competitors, which of them ſhould be gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19591:6"/>in the war againſt the <hi>Lucani:</hi> euery one was for himſelfe: and thereupon deſpiſed the charge of the City as an office altogether thankleſſe and baſe: the Senators beheld the contention with aſtoniſhment, Dictator was there none, that by ſtrong hand might order theſe factious Tribunes, ſaith <hi>Q. Seruilius,</hi> nay ſith there is no reſpect hereby carried to your owne ranke and quality, nor duty to the eſtate of this common wealth, my fathlery au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority ſhal ſoone diſpatch this controuerſie. I tell you, my ſonne without drawing of any lots for the matter, ſhal bide at home, and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne the City. And what did the Father of <hi>C. Flaminius</hi> tribune of the common people, which enacted the law about the partage of ſome french grounds, by the poll, the Senate was againſt it, his colleagues mainly oppoſed him, which he ſet light by, an army was mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred againſt him (in caſe he ſhould perſiſt in that opinion (but that danted him nothing, his father, euen as he was in the place to haue proclaimed his new made Law, ſeizes vpon him: how was it now with my yong maſter? downe comes he from his chaire of eſtate, and this braue gallant that before ſet at nought all the maieſty, authority and prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiue of his country, is now ſubdued at a poore priuate mans check, and as <hi>M. Valerius</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:19591:6"/>ſtorieth it in his fift booke, was not ſo much as once blamed for it, by the leaſt muttering of the ſeſſions ſo diſappointed and broken vp. How then is it poſſible, but that in the point of parents authority, there ſhould be more force in mans law than in the bare and ſimple precept as it was deliuered from God by <hi>Moſes,</hi> eſpecially if that be true which <hi>Halicarnaſſus</hi> reporteth that contempt, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety, murdering of parents, were therefore ordinary monſters among the Greekes, but exceeding ſcarce and ſeldome to be found in Rome, becauſe the authority which thoſe ancient Law makers <hi>Charondas Pittacus</hi> and <hi>Solon,</hi> aſſigned to parents, was a mild and fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble regiment contrariwiſe that which <hi>Romu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> gaue, was abſolute, full, and without limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, whence it came to paſſe that in all the large territory of the Romane Empire, hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly will you meete with one <hi>Malleolus</hi> that is, ſuch a deſperate ruffian as butchered his own mother?</p>
            <p>What then may we ſay of this diuine com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement eſtabliſhed (as we ſee) neither by threat of abdication, nor loſſe of life? here is only commanded that which honeſty and good conſcience perſwades vnto. Nor let any man thinke that it is a good anſwer to the obiection to ſay that <hi>Moſes</hi> Law, aſwell as
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:19591:7"/>any other law, did not only ſharply cenſure parricide, but euen euery diſhoneſt and idle ſpeech vttered by a ſonne, for we intreat not, what authority a publique magiſtrate hath, neither of a iudiciall proceeding held in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtories, and common Aſſiſes, we talke of that which may be exerciſed at our home dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, in our owne priuate houſholds, which fathers, not officers, by vertue of their office, challenge ouer their children, that is to ſay without appeale to any higher be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch, without aſſiſtance of any other Iudges office? For ſo it is, he that puniſheth by the helpe of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, doth in deed not puniſh but complaine. But yet ouer and aboue al that which we haue already obiected againſt <hi>S. Gregory,</hi> it falls ſo ſhort that parents by this heauenly oracle haue any more dominion ouer their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, than either by theſe, or other humane lawes, that in truth they cannot be ſaid, to haue receiued thence any one iot of power or authority. For let a ſonne be negligent in performing of that one command, <hi>honour thy father,</hi> what may the father doe in ſuch a caſe? It is true, it allures him with reward, that is, with a proſperous and a long life, but it puts ouer no puniſhment into the fathers hands, no none at all. As though in ſo doing, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what would be found, which nature of her ſelf
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19591:7"/>could not well abide. Did <hi>Moſes</hi> then miſtake, and when he deliuered Gods lawes was he ſomewhat more careleſſe in this point which concernes Fathers? A ſinne it is ſo to ſay; for this authority of parents, which wee ſeeke after, was for precedency of time farre more ancient than the commandement it ſelfe, which is demo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtratiuely, proued by this very inſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that God almighty, would neuer haue commanded <hi>Abraham</hi> to haue ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced his ſonne <hi>Iſaacke,</hi> if hee had had no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of life and death ouer him. Would God haue enioyned it, would the father haue executed it, would neighbours and ſtrangers haue endured it, which in no caſe at no time, by no law a father might bee able to iuſtifie? beſides they that liued long before <hi>Moſes,</hi> would neuer haue buſied themſelus ſo much in matching of their children in wedlock: for that was a matter reſting in their choyce, not in the choice of the parties contracting mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, which ſinne of theirs was cauſe of the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſal deluge) nor wold the children bin ſo eager in purſuit of their parents bleſſing: and what ſhall we ſay more? ſurely the bare en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditement brought in by the father to the Magiſtrate, would neuer haue ſerued for a ſufficient euidence againſt an vndutiful child, if euen in thoſe dayes, the power of a father
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19591:8"/>and his domeſtique diſcipline had not beene very tranſcendent. What ſhall wee ſay then? Did God by his latter law repeale the former and confine this duety to an inhibition of wordes alone? If the caſe were ſo, what then might wee ſay for <hi>Nazianzene?</hi> Without doubt ſomething might bee ſpoken for him, and very much, were it not, that the very ſelfe ſame Chriſtian Religion, which in a manner we receiued from him, did in ſome ſort now croſſe the good Chriſtian Biſhops aſſertion. For this authority of parents (if there be any ſuch thing extant) is ſo far reuolted from that which was ordained and eſtabliſhed by God, by nature, by the Law of nations, and Law poſitiue, and that forſooth vpon no othet occaſion (but that wee (I cannot tell how) ſeuer this filiall duetie from religion) that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Chriſtians now a dayes to be a Father, is nothing elſe but ſo to bee tearmed, the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is gone though the name continue. Can Chriſtian religion then, and Gods heauenlie commandement, wich Saint <hi>Gregory</hi> ſo highly commendeth, maintaine the home diſcipline, if Chriſtians bee the men which eſpecially ouerthrow it? But before we paſſe any further in the diſcourſe, let vs ſatisfie this great Diuine, and then conſider, whether it be true, that now a daies there is any authority
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19591:8"/>left vs ouer our children or no, and if it bee any, and yet but of verie ſmall eſteeme, whether notwithſtanding it bee ſuch, or ſo much, as ſhould be expoſed to all contempt and wrong. Certaine it is, that the outragious cruelty which the ancient Lawmakers deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to improue the power of parents withall, was but a caſt of policy, that ſo in regard ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, either out of pure conſtraint, or of a ready mind, children might conforme themſelues to better behauiour, and at no hand bee with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawne from that reuerent obeyſance, which naturall affection (and no law nor ordinance of man) taught them, as they were ſucking of their mothers breaſts. They in their wiſedom knew right well, that youth was ſo prone to riot and luſt, ſo arrogant and laſciuious in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour, ſo hard to bee tamed and menaged, that they concluded it to bee a caſe of meere neceſſity by way of enacting ſuch terrible pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, to renue and repaire that, which was ſo far corrupted and depraued from na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures primitiue inſtitution; that as in old time they kept debters to their word by tearing their lims in ſunder, &amp; drawing bloud from them, &amp; the like, ſo the very ſhew and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation of ſuch horrible tortures and martyrdomes which parents might inflict vpon their children, might leſſon them obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:19591:9"/>and beare them downe, if they ſhould euer attempt or vndertake any thing that paſt not firſt by their allowance and leaue, by whom they liued, &amp; had their education: but yet thereby no checke was giuen to naturall affection, for it was to be intended that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though parents might be ſo tender of their childrens good as to enter into ſuch ſeuere termes of conſultation for them, yet the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers neuer dreamed it would once ſo hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, which they permitted: that is, that a ſon might be ſold by the father for a bond-ſlaue, diſinherited, and then kild. Or if perchance it might ſo fall out, that it ſhould be vpon ſuch as had worthily deſerued it, and with ſuch circumſtantiall conſiderations, that iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice her ſelfe, ſhould ſne haue giuen iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment could neither haue ſaid better, or done more vprightly. But God almighty handles matters otherwiſe, that which he commands is plainly ſet down, not with fetches and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uices. For hee needs no compaſſing or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facing to perſwade that to be iuſt and good which he once requires, he is ſo eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally good of himſelfe, and hath ſuch a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiue of iuſtice and equity co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſubſtantiall to him as his bare command neceſſarily en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forceth our preciſe obedience. Religion keeps men more in aw, than feare: for were the ſon
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:19591:9"/>looſe or diſhoneſt, of conuerſation, and for that cauſe oftentimes turnd out of doores, nay laſtly refuſed of the parents for their child, becauſe no gentle meanes preuailed ought with him? Why if once he were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted to chriſtianity preſently (ſaith <hi>Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timius</hi>) he became to liue in good order, and good counſell regaind him to duty and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. Doubtleſſe though God vnto theſe lawes of men and nature inſerted alſo his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly beheſt, yet did he nothing thereby pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudice thoſe former lawes; he commanded obedience, but neuer abrogated any part of their authority. Nay long time after Chriſts paſſion, the commiſſion of life and death which parents might exerciſe vpon their children, was ſtill currant amongſt Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and though the more ancient of them reproued ſome things amongſt the Pagans, as the murdering of yong infants, the bloudy fencing of ſword players, yet againſt that ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible authority of parents they ſpake not a word. And howſoeuer God in bare termes pronounced this Commandement, <hi>honour thy father and thy mother,</hi> yet notwithſtanding for two reaſons eſpeciallie it farre exceeds the lawes of men. The one is, becauſe what he commands is conſtant and perpetuall, but our lawes bee mutable and repealeable: if
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19591:10"/>anything pleaſe vs to day, to morrow we are out of loue with it: a patterne whereof wee may ſee in that verie lawe which <hi>Romulus</hi> ordained. For at firſt without all exception or bar, it was free for a father to put his child to death. Afterwards it might not bee done but vpon the aſſiſtance and aduice of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, then the cauſe muſt bee heard iudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allie: laſtlie the magiſtrate might decide it, but no priuate iuriſdiction, nay in concluſion that rigorous lawe, vtterlie vaniſhed and became voide: the other is, becauſe if the iniunction of a Conſull bee greater, than the Pretors and the Pretors greater than an order of the Edilis, it will neceſſarilie follow, in good proportion, that the lawe of God is to bee preferred before any ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of man whatſoeuer. And why ſo? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe men in their wiſedomes may erre, and therupon be of meane reputation by reaſon of ſuch eſcapes &amp; ouer ſights, as ſaith the ſame <hi>Tertullian.</hi> In God there is no ſuch matter; ſo then <hi>S. Gregory</hi> who vnderſtood this well enough, and was of opinion that this precept of our Lord God ſhould be left at large, and neuer concluded by any limitation, (when he had forſaken the world, againſt the will and expreſſe commandement of his father, and had betaken himſelfe to a monaſtery,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19591:10"/>and had refuſed a Biſhopricke which before was his fathers, yet at length he began to be toucht with a ſence of inward regreeting: and can I (ſaith he) be vndutifull and diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient vnto ſo good a father, and be blameles; can I endure to be accuſed for a ſtubborne and contemptuous ſonne, to be guilty of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olating and diſtaining my natural obedience vnto my father? and thereupon leauing the ſolitary life, he gets him home, accepts the ſea and Biſhopricke which had been before his fathers: and all this doe I (ſaith he) more for God almighties commandement ſake, than for any feare of mortall men: therefore now good father, I pray giue me your bleſſing. And in this ſence (you ſee) may <hi>S. Gregory</hi> be well vnderſtood. For euen <hi>S. Chryſoſtome</hi> in his eleuenth booke againſt ſuch as diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend the monaſticall life, writes in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: Thy ſon loues and obſerues, and honors thee, not becauſe the law of nature enioynes him ſo to doe, but much more for that in ſo doing hee may teſtifie his duetie to the commandements of almighty God, for whoſe loue he hath perfitly deſpiſed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquiſht all the world. But if notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all this, it be true, that now a dayes there be no trace left of this fatherly power which we ſo much hunt after, and if this home bred
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:19591:11"/>authority be ſcarce remaining in ſhadow or ſhew among vs, how may <hi>S. Gregory</hi> be then defended? the power of life and death long ſince hath bin diſcontinued by an immemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall cuſtome to the contrary (as before we mentioned) you cannot pawne or ſell your ſonne, much adoe you will haue to diſinherit him. If he get any thing it is for himſelfe, his father hath no part nor property in it, hee will ſerue his father with proceſſe, he will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite him at the common Aſſize without as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king him any leaue. And in a word ſuch is the religion now adaies, ſuch is the Churches tradition (as men ſay) that let the ſonne en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet into any kind of life, bee married, bee a monke, or ſo forth, all this may he doe in ſpight of his fathers teeth, and abſolutely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his will. How then (good father <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zianzene</hi>) or wherein ſtands that ſanction ſo much inforced by God and nature, <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor thy father.</hi> What didſt thou ſee in that au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority royall, and preheminence of parents when thou vpon a timorous ſcrupuloſitie of conſcience durſt not once ſo much as to treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe againſt it. If in the caſes before mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned our children may diſobey their parents, and yet not be punſhed by them, put mee ſome caſes out of the old law, why they ſhold not now enioy the like libertie? or what be
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19591:11"/>the principall points of this domeſtique mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchie, which the chriſtian religion, doth yet retaine and defend for lawfull? can it bee poſſible, that heathen parents haue puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed euen to the pit of hell a ſhameleſſe and vngratious ſonne (ſo far were they in loue with the childrens obedience) it is a matter ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of that father which (as <hi>Pauſanius</hi> rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth it in his tenth booke) <hi>Polignotus</hi> drew in a picture of hell taking paines to bee his owne ſonnes hangman for a ſpeciall prancke of vndutifulneſſe, that he had plaid him in his life time: And haue chriſtians on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary inuented caſes, to authoriſe vnnaturall impietie and breach of duty againſt parents? can it be poſſible (as ſaith <hi>Theophilus</hi> in his third booke to <hi>Eutol.</hi>) that <hi>Platoes</hi> law for the communitie of wiues, was principallie vpon that point diſliked, becauſe the danger might be, that the ſonne might ſomtime honor him that was not his father, and vpon ignorance at another time might alſo doe him no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence, who was his father indeed, (a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence neuertheleſſe ſo due by the rules of the lawe of nations, and in ſuch order mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhalled by them, that (as <hi>Pomponius</hi> teſtifieth) it is to be ranged in the ſecond place, firſt God, after him our parents, and then our country) and ſhould we vnder colour of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:19591:12"/>in that one point principallie offend. Firſt and foremoſt, therefore we will ſpeake thus much in generall (as men do vſe to ſell wares in groſſe that the poſition and aſſertion is very ſottiſh and impious, becauſe the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of parents, is weakned and rebated in ſome points, and circled within an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that, <hi>Ergo</hi> there is no ſuch matter at all remaining, becauſe the preheminence of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents is abrogated, (to ſpeake in the Romane dialect) <hi>ergo</hi> it muſt follow there is no duty no naturall reuerence at all left vnto them. Then deſcending to particular dueties, wee will take a view, whether euery one of them bee ſo important, as that of pure ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie parents ought to bee obeied in ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall or no? Which will be ſoone found if we take ſome farther view, and make a quire, what that was which the ancients did ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly require of their children when they paſt ouer ſuch a large iuriſdiction and power vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the parents; the caſe is cleere, that they did it not therefore, that parents ſhould bee as magiſtrates to their children, and ſo admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter iuſtice at home to euery one that their children had offended, againe as the Praetor did in the Court of the common pleas, nor that there ſhould be one authority publique, another priuate and domeſtique. For if the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:19591:12"/>crime were publicke, and committed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the verge of the fathers houſe, the officer was to order it. Nor is it a good concluſion, the child hath offended, therefore he muſt haue no other iudge but his father. Indeed it is true that there were ſuch fathers in times paſt at <hi>Rome,</hi> and likewiſe amongſt other na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions (whereof we haue written in the ſixt book of our reports, the ſeuenth Chapter) that by vertue of ſuch fatherly authoritie, wold take cogniſance of ſuch crimes as their children had offended in abroad; as <hi>Caſſius, Manlius Torquatus, C. Flaminius</hi> and ſome others beſides,) ſo then this was no occaſion, that gaue ſuch a prerogatiue to the power of parents, but that rather which <hi>Halicarnaſſeus</hi> in the life of <hi>Romulus</hi> alleadgeth, that when children did perceiue, how they were awed at home and that their ſubiection vnder their priuate parents, was much more ſtrict than vnder the publique Magiſtrate, (for they are commanded firſt to yeeld obedience to their parents, after that to their country) that the Prince himſelfe might ſcarce doe any thing without iudiciall proceeding. But the father might do euery thing at his own will &amp; pleaſure (for ſo ſpeaks <hi>Aristotle</hi> in his poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques) they might learne to be more duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to doe nothing without line and leuell,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:19591:13"/>that is, without expreſſe commandement and iniunction from their parents, might neither will, nor nil ought, ſaue that which proceeded firſt from their parents pleaſure and by his allowance. In a word, that as the bit, ſpur, and ſwitch, makes the horſe obedient to his rider, ſo the feare of ſo great chaſtiſements might enforce the ſonnes conformity to his father, as to a demie God on earth, and ſole founder of his being And ſurely, had our forefathers meant no other thing hereby then to put a ſnaffle into youthes mouth, to reſtraine them from ſuch vices as nature is prone vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, why then they would haue determined this their authoritie, at ſome certaine time or age of the ſonne, vpon ſome certaine office or honour, that might haue befallen, or ſome condition and eſtate of life whereunto they might poſſiblie be aduanced. But the ſonne, were he neuer ſo old, bare he neuer ſo great office, yea had it been the high Prieſthood, was euer notwithſtanding vnder his fathers checke. And what thinke you was the iſſue thereof? marry ſir, whatſoeuer the father had once determined concerning his children, to what kind of life ſoeuer he had bound them, yea and though it had been to the cart and plough, as <hi>L. Manlius</hi> did vſe his ſonne, why by reaſon of ſo eminent a power, againſt
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:19591:13"/>which there was no helpe, no remedie to be had, he muſt of neceſſity reſt content. Hence it was that all the ſonnes negotiations had ſuch dependance on the fathers will, as you ſee counterpaines haue, that muſt accord with their originalls, or riuers haue, that muſt be fed from their fountaines head. And though (put caſe) the ſonne ſwaruing ſome deale from this courſe of duty, as being ſtubborne and paſt all ſhame, found his penalty there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon executed, ſometime with more rigour, ſometimes with more clemency, though the father by the ordinances of ſome countries might ſentence his ſonne to death, by others complaine of him to the magiſtrate, and only giue in euidence againſt him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay though by long preſcription theſe domeſtique cenſures haue been altogether diſuſed. For to ſmall purpoſe is their inſtance, and (God knowes it is a poore one) that alleadge why but yong children be ſtill yet vnder their parents cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection: it will be no good inference to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude that therefore it is not now any longer iuſt and reaſonable becauſe law had once de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined it to be ſo; it will be no good infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to conclude, that the law and edict of all nations, which decrees an abſolute obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to parents, is now clearely vaniſhed and out of vſe. Lawes be lawes ſtill, though
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:19591:14"/>they be not penall, though there be no loſſe of life nor forfeiture of goods enſuing: as for example, adultery though there be ſmal adoe made about it, now adaies, yet in its owne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, it is alwaies foule and diſhoneſt. If either by negligence or coniuencie it be not ſharply puniſhed, the law notwithſtanding is ſtil chaſt and honorable which forbids it. And ſo the law for childrens obedience, is euer right &amp; conuenient, though many times no penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie enſue This is euident ſpecially out of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. it is true, he would not that a father ſhould put his child to death with his owne hands, but rather ſeeke for it by petition from the magiſtrate, and ſo haue it executed, and that alſo without any other enqueſt, or euidence, than at the fathers ſuit: from whence it is more then probably collected, that in the common wealth of the Iewes the father had a ſoueraigne authority, in caſes of life and death, for although by this order of <hi>Moſes,</hi> it were ſomewhat ſtaid from ſpeedy executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yet the matter is plaine, that it is eaſier for me to bee a petitioner that another man ſhould be executed and die, than that I ſhould be his executioner with mine owne hands. But howſoeuer, I would faine know and learn, why and for what offence a father might en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite his ſonne, by this Hebrew Law-makers
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:19591:14"/>decree, that vpon ſuch conuiction he might be preſently ſtoned to death. Was it becauſe he was a murtherer a Church-robber, a traitor, a theef, a fornicator, or an vſual offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor againſt the peace of the King, his crown and dignity? Let vs heare his owne words de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered to this purpoſe:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If any man haue a ſonne that is ſtubborne and diſobedient, which will not harken to the voice of his father, nor the voice of his mother, and they haue chaſtiſed him and he would not obey them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then ſhall his father and his mother take him, and bring him out vnto the Elders of his Citie, and vnto the gate of the place where hee dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And ſhall ſay vnto the Elders of his City, this our ſonne is ſtubborne and diſobedient, and he will not obey our admonition, he is a robber, and a drunkard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then all the men of the Citie ſhall ſtone him with ſtones vnto death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I pray what manner of offences be there herein mentioned? be they not treſpaſſes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt parents, priuate miſdemeanours and domeſticall, hatcht within doores, not acted in publique view? certainly as by order of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary diſcipline contempt in a ſouldier is a crime very capitall, becauſe there is nothing ſo far endangers the ſtate of an army, as one
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:19591:15"/>mutinouſly diſpoſed, ſo by the ſame cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondencie of reaſon, it is fit and requiſite that all perſons belonging to my charge, as my ſeruants, my children, my wife, my cattell, all ſhould be at my becke, all ſhould be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der my conduct as the chiefe generall, all ſhould be actuated by my motion, as hauing ſurrendred the intereſt of their liberty into my plenary diſpoſition and authority. <hi>Aeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anus</hi> tells vs a ſtory of one <hi>Rhaco Mardus,</hi> who hauing brought his ſonne <hi>Cartomes</hi> like a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner with his armes faſt pinacled into the preſence of King <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> to receiue iudgement of death, vpon ſuggeſtion that he was a graceleſſe deſperate caſtaway, and grew to be very earneſt to that point, why (ſaith the King of <hi>Perſia</hi>) canſt thou endure to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold thy ſonnes life taken from him? his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer was, I haue in my garden a lettice rudely ouergrowne with leaues, and though they be lims of the bodie, yet doe I now and then crop off and prune ſome of the bitter ſtalkes, and ſuch as may be ſpared: What doth my lettice thinke you die for griefe vpon the matter, or doth it mourne, becauſe there is a limbe or two lopt off? nay, it flouriſheth the better and ſuch a maim makes him eat a great deale the ſweeter. In like manner may it pleaſe (you O King) to deeme of me, for albeit I
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:19591:15"/>ſhall ſee and behold the death of this wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched varlot that hurts and anoies my houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, corrupts, by his ſtubborne and lewde example his poore yong brethren, I will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe be ſtill of the opinion to ſpeed the better by it, yea and rather thriue by ſuch a maim than any waies be endamaged by it, and this is ſutable to that of <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> and <hi>Halicar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſeus.</hi> But that I may the better proue this point, how is it that this queſtion, namelie whether a ſonne, in ſome caſe may lawfullie diſobey his father, firſt ſtepping aſide out of priuate mens houſes, entred into the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique ſchooles of the vniuerſitie, to bee diſputed and queſtioned there, and after to be decided finallie at the ſeat of iudgement, but that it was neuer in mans memorie heard of before, nay the contrarie was euer held for certaine and true, that ſuch a queſtion would neuer haue been propounded? when <hi>Danaus</hi> much againſt his will, had matcht his fiftie daughters to <hi>Egiſthus</hi> his grandchildren, and had charged the yong virgins that on the mariage day euerie one ſhould murther hir husband with ſuch a ſword, as to that end he had giuen them, (the iuſt like tale may you read in <hi>Chalco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dilas,</hi> of a Phyſition of <hi>Florence</hi> that commanded his daughter to poiſon <hi>Lantiſlaus</hi> King of <hi>Naples</hi> the firſt night
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:19591:16"/>they ſhould lie together) euerie one did as their father had enioined them excepting on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Hypermneſtra</hi> which ſaued her husband <hi>Lynceus</hi> his life. But what followed hereupon? theſe murderous paricides were ſo far from being brought, to anſwer the law and plead not guiltie for the matter, or that their obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience herein was deemed culpable, that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe <hi>Hypermneſtra,</hi> for that ſhe had not performed hir fathers beheſt, was thereupon publiquelie arraigned, and much adoe to be freed at the common Aſſiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, ſo that in point of obedience vnto parents no exception wold be taken, to haue denied them or to haue doubled with them had vtterlie been vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. The truth is, freed ſhe was, but the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict was brought in vpon euen voices, with ſuch demurring, and ſo much hazard of life, (the record is famouſly knowne by her owne letter in <hi>Ouid</hi>) that as though ſhe had eſcaped ſome dangerous ſhipwracke, ſhe built a Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple vnto <hi>Venus</hi> and <hi>Diana,</hi> and hung vp a ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in memoriall of her deliuerie. How then ſhould that domeſtique dutie be blemiſht or broken, when children though they had offended in obeying, their obedience notwith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtanding, was vnto them their chiefeſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation, their refuſall a crime vtterlie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pardonable. That great Oracle of the Law
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:19591:16"/>
               <hi>Vlpian</hi> holds this opinion, that he may not properlie be ſaid, to haue any will of his owne that liues vnder commaund of a father or maſter, and well worthie is he of pardon (as he thinkes) in this caſe, that pretends neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie obedience for his excuſe.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>L.</hi> 11. <hi>F. de his qui notantur infamia.</hi>
               </note> And queſtion leſſe <hi>Tiberius</hi> was of the ſame mind, that a ſonne might by no meanes refuſe the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of his father. But howſoeuer, it hath been alwaies held (ſaith <hi>Gellius</hi>) be the thing honeſt which is commanded, or be it indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, the obedience thereunto ought to bee abſolute. Be it diſhoneſt and againſt good manners, yet the care muſt be neuertheleſſe ſuch ſo not to obey, as that it bee done with a modeſt and lowly behauiour, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a vaine of tart reprehenſion, or refuſall, or the leaſt ſhew of diſlike. Reſpite the doing of it for a time or put it off handſomelie, rather than refuſe to doe it, let there appeare a maidenlie baſhfulneſſe in a conſtant deniall, and let the ſonne diſcouer ſome zeale that he would fain obey his father, when he obeieth him not. As <hi>Ageſilaus</hi> did, who when his father charged him that he ſhould giue a ſentence againſt law, marry father ſaith he I well remember, that long ſince you willed me to be euer for the law, I will therefore at this time not doe that which you command me now, but that
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:19591:17"/>which was your pleaſure I ſhould haue done long agoe. And as <hi>Acrotatus</hi> did, of whom when his parents required ſome thing vniuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie hee denied it honeſtlie in this manner: I know you would haue me to doe that which is honeſt and iuſt, for ſo you bred me vp (I thanke you) I will therefore doe that which you once willed me to do, but that which you now command, I may not. He that ſhould openlie gaineſay and arrogantlie oppoſe himſelfe againſt his father, ſhould proue no better than a malepert wicked vngratious impe. Euen in a good cauſe, a ſonnes ſpeech towards his parents ſhould be humble and reuerent, (as <hi>Saluianus</hi> ſaith) for how elſe ſhould that be true, which our forefathers were wont prouerbiallie to ſpeake, a man may wrong his dutie, by the caſt of his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, if by any law in the world a ſonnes diſobedience were maintainable. Should the perſon of an Embaſſador be ſacred, and inuiolable, among enemies, and muſt you ſpare to vſe the leaſt word of diſgrace againſt him? and would you haue the maſter of a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie entertaine, and harbour within his owne walls, vnder the roofe of his owne houſe, one authorized to be his comptroller, his check<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate, nay his profeſt mortall enemie? but why beſtow we ſo much time, and proofe
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:19591:17"/>about this poſition? forſooth to this end, to make good the deuiſe and plot of this dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtique authoritie, that in caſe children ſhould obiect or pretend ought againſt it, all paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of contradicting or queſtioning might hereby be preuented: for it is an obligation wherein wee are bound to nature, and the condition is that we be euerſubiect to our parents It is holie and acceptable, not only before God, but euen amongſt men, that chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ſhould be obedient vnto their parents in ſingleneſſe of heart and without all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, as ſaith <hi>Theophilus</hi> to <hi>Eutolicus.</hi> And whereas almighty God added nothing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the bare and ſimple commandement to threaten the offendor, he did it vpon this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that he thought it ſufficient for him briefly to comprize that, which otherwiſe was naturall among all men and notoriouſly knowne in their conſcience well enough to be a true, vnchangeable, &amp; perpetuall notion. To the intent therefore, that we may ſhew that this authoritie of parents ſtreams foorth from natures ſpring tell me, is there any rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to be giuen, that a woman ſhould be more in ſubiection to a man than a child is to his parents? why; but a woman in reſpect of the ſole infirmitie of her ſex is ſubiect to a man, and there is no other reaſon but the ſonne
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:19591:18"/>owes him double ſeruice, the one in reſpect of diſparitie of yeers, between them, the other in reſpect of his fathers goodnes towards him. But grant there be no fee of duetie to bee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged: for the firſt, which is ods of age, and when once they come to ſtrength and full yeares, in Gods name cancell that obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation; (and yet <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> will tell you, that ſuch prerogatiues of aduantage can neuer be determined) I would faine know of what ſort you take this laſt to bee. I meane a parents bounty, and whether that may expire by any age or time: tis a doctrine of naturall reaſon, that wee are bound to requite them which haue beene good vnto vs: for in this point none can be of a contrarie opinion to <hi>Vlpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> (and as it is fairely deliuered by <hi>Philo,</hi>) the vnthankefull man ſinnes againſt huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, if according to the meanes of his abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, he require not kindlie a benefite receiued; nay, not to returne one good turne for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in the ſenſe of Saint <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> is little better than wilfull murther. Well then, but there is no greater obligation, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that which is due from children to their parents, after God they be our Gods; that wee are, that wee liue, and moue, tis the bounteous gift of our deare parents, and ſuch a gift as may admit no manner of recompence, for it can neuer bee
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:19591:18"/>poſſible, that the ſonne ſhould beget his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: now concerning the mothers tender care and diligence, what thinke you of the ſweet food wherewith ſhee nurſes her poore infant? what thinke you of thoſe pretty loue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie iniuries which the innocent Babe manie times doth to his mother? as ſoone as hee is thirſtie, the mothers dugge is ready to giue him drinke; and before they breede teeth, they meete that with their lippes, which needes no chewing; as he ſpeakes, that is the ſuppoſed author of Saint <hi>Ieromes</hi> epiſtle, <hi>De honor and is parentibus, for the honouring of parents;</hi> and he addes moreouer, that for this cauſe parents ought to bee dearely e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed of their children, becauſe they can neuer bee repaired by any other; for when once the law of all fleſh hath taken them out of this world, a man ſhall neuer bee able to finde another father or mother; then what a diueliſh ingratitude were it (as that other <hi>Plato</hi> ſaith right well;) If we for great matters cannot finde in our hearts to beſtow ſmall trifles? for manie benefites a few poore retri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butions? whatſoeuer to the vttermoſt of our power wee ſhould render to them of what value were it; what ſcale would it beare being compared with this light which wee ſee, this educatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which we haue, this Country which
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:19591:19"/>we enioy, this natiue Country wherein wee liue, thoſe large poſſeſſions from Fathers and Grandfathers, lineally diſcended vpon vs, which muſt maintaine vs &amp; ours: for al theſe we are tenants in fee, and holde them from our parents donation. (Let <hi>Seneca</hi> ſpeake his pleaſure to the contrarie, he ſpeakes but like a diſputer;) but what ſaith the great Doctor <hi>Origen,</hi> who when hee ſpeakes well, no man ſpeakes better: hee in his eleuenth Homily vpon <hi>Leuiticus,</hi> writes in this wiſe: The name of a father is a great miſterie, the name of a mother is a concealed reuerence, God is thy ſpirituall father, and heauenly Ieruſalem is thy mother. Firſt, God thy father that crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thy ſoule, and therehence it is ſaid, I haue begotten ſonnes and exalted them; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, thy bodilie father, is thy father, by whoſe meanes thou waſt borne and begotten in the fleſh, and cameſt into this world, that bare thee in his loines. Now then, becauſe the name of a father is ſo ſacred and venerable, therefore whoſoeuer ſhall curſe his father, ſhall die the death. In like ſort muſt wee ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine of our mothers alſo, by whoſe labour &amp; care we were borne, and bred vp, wherefore as the Apoſtle ſaith, thou oughteſt to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciprocally thankefull to thy parents, for if thou diſhonour thy carnall father, his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:19591:19"/>reflecteth vpon thy ſpirituall father, and if thou iniurie thy mother, that iniury redoundeth to the heauenly Ieruſalem, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore at no hand muſt wee be at variance, or conteſtation with our parents, no not ſo much as in word. He is thy father, ſhe is thy mother, let them in Gods name doe and ſaie as they pleaſe, they know well enough what is fitting to be done. As for vs be we neuer ſo obſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quious and dutifull to them, yet ſhall we come ſhort, of that full meaſure of thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, which we owe them, for our birth, for our bearing, for the fruition of this glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ſweet light which we behold, for our food, and laſtly for the courſe of inſtitution (perhaps as it may ſo fall out) in ſome of thoſe learned and liberall ſciences, nay oftentimes they be the cauſe, that wee come to the knowledge of God, that we frequent his Church and heare the word of his heauenly law. Now if this inſtinct which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from God and nature, and this kind retaliation of benefits be found euen in ſence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and bruit beaſts, then ſhould man, whom the graces haue foſtered, to whom curtelie and good manners is hereditarie, be worſe than a lion, a Storke, a parde? for of the piety of Storkes and Swallowes, <hi>S. Ambroſe</hi> ſpeakes excellentlie in his fift booke of the <hi>Exam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ron</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:19591:20"/>the ſixteenth and ſeuenteenth Chapters, and if ſo be (as <hi>Epictetus</hi> will haue it) that nature is not ouer curious, of what qualitie or condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thy father be, be he good or bad, baſe or honorable, he is ſtill thy father, the obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation which thou entereſt into by being his ſonne can neuer become voide Can then any doubt be made, whether his will and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement be in all caſes to be fulfilled? the verie perſon of parents and patrons ſhould be alwaies religiouſly honored, and obſerued of the ſonne and the freed man, as <hi>Vlpian</hi> the father of the Law hath adiudged it. But put caſe that the ſonne ſhould obiect that, which <hi>Diogenes</hi> ſometimes did obiect to <hi>Zeno.</hi> That children were nothing beholding to their parents for their begetting, becauſe that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded rather from a paſſion of pleaſure and ſence than from any ſound loue or good affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. He that imploies himſelfe about the begetting of children leſt of all intends that which he goes about, he heeds not procrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but the ſatisfying of his owne appetite and voluptuous deſire. Indeed this were well ſpoken for a Cynicke, and well ſaid to turne away the imputation from bruite beaſts and put it vpon men; yet euen verie beaſts when by courſe of nature and ſeaſon of the yeere, they couple together for breed, do it more to
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:19591:20"/>reare their yong than for any rage of ſenſuall appetite, (as <hi>Athenagoras</hi> thinks) twere Well, if there were no ods between their copulation and our mariages, if matrimonie proceeded whollie from the law of nature, taught in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall to all liuing creatures, not from the law of nations peculiar onlie to men of reaſon: or that now it were no longer held for a matter of high miſterie amongſt vs chriſtians, but of ſhame and diſhonor: not a league of loue to liue together in the eſtate of holy wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locke, but ſome partnerſhip, or conſpiracie rather to the ſatisfying of brutiſh luſt, and carnalitie. But ſuch mens iudgements concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning mariage, comes either from ignorance, as not knowing what it meanes, or from ſome tedious diſcontent, which they find in liuing ſingle. But <hi>Socrates</hi> in <hi>Zenophon</hi> hath giuen <hi>Diogenes</hi> his anſwer in this point to the full. For (ſaith he) why ſhould men marrie, if chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren were begotten to ſatisfie ſenſuality: can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not the fire of luſt be quenched except ye firſt muſt needs marrie? but now, in that we are content to vndertake the yoke of mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, (which I muſt needs ſay lies heauy vpon ſome of vs) we do it to multiplie the world by propagation of children. For were it other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, we would neuer be ſo curious about the matter, I warrant you, to enquire of what age
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:19591:21"/>ſhe was whom we meant to marrie, of what houſe ſhe came, what good conditions ſhe had, we would neuer bee ſo carefull, for the education of our children borne vnder that mariage, giue them ſuch meanes for their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, take ſo much deliberation for their matching afterwards, if luſt and pleaſure had been our onelie ends and reſpects. Far more diuine was that conceit of <hi>Philo</hi> in a dialogue of his concerning mariage, who expreſſeth himſelfe thus, Parents when they beget chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, be deputie officers, and vicegerents vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der God, both ſerue and be ſubordinate for procreation, the one frames the body, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther workes the ſoule: and therefore <hi>Ignatius</hi> writing to the <hi>Philadelphians</hi> tearmeth parents fellow labourers with God, in which ſenſe man is the liuelie image, and counterfeit of God, as <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus</hi> reporteth in his eleuenth booke of Inſtitutions. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore neglect one, neglect both: condemne the vnderworkman, and ſet at nought the maſter workman himſelfe. Nay ſaith <hi>Philo,</hi> they be not workmen, they be euen Gods amongſt vs, and when they beget their children, they repreſent one God, that is from all eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie not begotten. The difference is, God is the creator vniuerſall, man the indiuiduall, God of all creatures, man of his children on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly:
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:19591:21"/>whereupon it followeth, in his opinion ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarilie, that he muſt needs be implous, againſt the inuiſible, and incomprehenſible God, that is careleſſe in performing all good offices, and duties to theſe inferior Gods our parents, that liue amongſt vs, be euer in our eie, and in our familiar acquaintance. The ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſame witneſſeth <hi>S. Iohn</hi> in his firſt epiſtle and fourth Chapter, <hi>If any man ſay, I loue God, and hate his brother, hee is a lier, for how can hee that loueth not his brother, whom he hath ſeene, loue God whom hee hath not ſeene?</hi> for loue God and the ſparkes of loue will be kindled towards your neighbour: loue your neighbour and then your loue to God ward will be in a burning fire, as <hi>Gregory</hi> the great ſpeaketh in the ſeuenth of his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralls, the tenth Chapter Nay beſides all this, <hi>Moſes</hi> that gaue lawes to the Iewes, in deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his holy ordinances, marſhalleth the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour due vnto God in the firſt table, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peating afterwards in <hi>Leuiticus</hi> the verie ſame precepts, he begins with the honor due vnto parents, requiring vs to yeeld them ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor and obedience: afterwards in a ſecond place he commands the ſame for God, as who ſhould ſay, they be both Gods alike and the definitions are but one in ſence and ſignification, he that honors his father and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:19591:22"/>mother, honours God, and he that honours God, by an infallible conſequence, honoreth his parents alſo. Moſt certaine it is, that when <hi>Zenocrates</hi> the Philoſopher, wrote; that the Athenians kept moſt religiouſly in their Temple of <hi>Eleuſis,</hi> three fundamentall precepts, whereunto their vſe was to reduce all ſuch lawes as euer <hi>Treptolemus</hi> had made for them: the firſt begins with parents, (as <hi>S. Ierome</hi> teſtifieth writing againſt <hi>Iouinian</hi>) ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing honour thy parents, worſhip thy God, abſtain from fleſh meat. And that moſt diuine <hi>Plato,</hi> who may truly be ſtiled another <hi>Moſes,</hi> after that he had written many things concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning God, why ſaith he, theſe be no lawes, but the preambles and prefaces to ſuch lawes, as we intend to make for the honor of parents. Marke, how he that ſayes the father muſt be worſhipped deduceth his premiſſes from God himſelfe. What an holy ſpeech was this in compariſon of that of <hi>Telencer,</hi> who though he knew the nature of this dutie well enough, being on a time demanded why the yong men of <hi>Lacedemon</hi> roſe vp, and gaue place to their ancients, made this anſwer, that being trained vp ſo in ciuilitie towards ſtrangers, they might be more apt to honour their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents alſo? <hi>Tertullian</hi> in his booke of praier, is verily of the opinion that the name of a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:19591:22"/>is a name of reuerence and authority, and he which ſhould attempt to take away dutie from children, or gouernment from parents, or vpon partialitie leane more to the one than the other, he in ſo doing, ſhould take away both, and rob parents of that prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence which the Lawes of God, nature, and men haue euer inueſted them with. So then if we muſt ſtill continue this dutie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards our parents, euer be heedful to obſerue and keep it, why may wee not conclude the ſame for parents auhoritie ouer vs, in this manner. Children muſt alwaies honor their parents, <hi>ergo</hi> parents muſt euer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand their children. Theſe ſweete louing affections were both iointlie worſhipt in one oratorie by the old Romans, and in my fancie ſhould not now bee ſequeſtred from being mutuallie dependant one to the other. For my better proofe herein, I would pray leaue a little to examine an argument of <hi>Tertullians,</hi> and to conſider the neceſſity of his illation wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he will demonſtrate Chriſt to be God, yet not God the father, but God the ſonne. I am not come ſaith Chriſt to do mine owne will, but the fathers that ſent me, this did he euer fulfill euen to his death. Hereupon he infers the concluſion <hi>ergo</hi> he was not the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther but the ſonne. Now ſir, how could this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument follow if the ſonnes will ſhould be
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:19591:23"/>diſtinct or any other, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the fathers wil? what maieſtie or honor were there added vnto God, in calling him a father (wee haue no name elſe whereby to know or expreſſe him) if there were no proper or naturall ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation for the name to this purpoſe? if there were no more difference betwixt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents &amp; children, but a nominall diſtinction, and the diuerſitie to reſt onlie in name, but no title of authoritie or iuriſdiction? but now a daies where can you find anie other diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence for fathers at this time to emancipate or enfranchize their children, is held not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie If my ſonne could ſpeake as ſoone as he were borne, I thinke this would be his lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, Sir I acknowledge you thus far foorth for my father, as to giue me maintenance and bring me vp. I came a free man into the world and if I liue but one welue or fourteene yeers to an end, I hope to ſue out my liuerie for my wardſhip. If I can but keepe my hands from doing violence to your perſon, I am ſure though in other matters I proue reſpectiue or vndutifull, no man will much complaine of me. The power and authoritie of you parents is cleane reuerſed, and abrogated. Now ſhould you threaten him with ſome curſe or reuenge that would follow vpon this contempt, this anſwer would be, tis a long while ere that comes Sir, and I ſhall looſe nothing by the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:19591:23"/>forbearance. But if ſo be this thorow per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion did ſinke into mens hearts, that he that offended his father offended God, that to be excluded from the fathers preſence, were aboue all other puniſhments the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, in briefe, if the ſonne could be made to to vnderſtand how dreadfull the bitter curſe of a father were (whereof we may chance to ſpeake ſomewhat more at large hereafter,) why theſe might be ſufficient props to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend and keepe vp, this excellent fabrique of rule and authoritie which in theſe daies is ſo much ruinated and decaied. But now (ſuch is our corruption) all this will not ſerue the turne, that ancient ſeueritie of the Romanes would better preuaile with them, that is, they ſhould neuer be brought to anieiudiciall trial for the matter, but be condemned and neuer heard ſpeake, which is a courſe of proceeding that <hi>Halicarneſſeus</hi> and <hi>Quintilian</hi> oftentimes mention. And why? becauſe a common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth is nothing elſe but a bodie incorporate of ſo many priuate families, and ſo founded &amp; begun by parents, that as (me thinks the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance were not much vnfit) to terme a family the nurſe, the wombe, and the roote of a common wealth: contrariwiſe a common wealth, a ſwarme, or colonie deduced from a priuate familie. He therefore that will go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:19591:24"/>a common wealth in good faſhion, and baniſh al looſe &amp; diſſolute behauiour thence and all crimes and exorbitant offences, let him looke firſt to good order at home. If he can make them lowlie, ſober, and dutifull within doores, they will come into the world, ſo nurtered, ſo taught, ſo affected, well may they change their homes, they will be ſure neuer to leaue their old manners. Contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, let him looke careleſlie to it, let him but once ſuffer the reines to be at libertie, preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſhall you ſee treaſons, murders, rapes, adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries, guſh out in large ſwelling ſtreames, and ſurround the countrrie. And this is the cauſe (if I be not miſtaken) why in ancient time they appropriated to priuate families peculiar gods, taking it for good policie, to countenance the infirmitie of domeſticall iuriſdiction, with the authoritie of diuine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, that both theſe two like mighty cable ankors, might hold them in all tempeſt faſt to their obedience. That euen as the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der infant, ledde and guided by the little finger, is able afterwards of himſelfe to walke without a guide; ſo comming to mans eſtate, the meanes of this priuate education, might awe and order him in the Common wealth, to carrie a due reſpect to the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, but not to dread his perſon, as hauing
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:19591:24"/>the ſword borne before him to grace his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice withall, not to terrifie well-doers. But ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily in mine opinion there can bee nothing more abſurd or incongruous, than once to thinke that Religion is any way aſſiſtant to this good order; for (if it be true, which before I toucht) certes Chriſtian Religion as it is vſed, doth more ſuppreſſe and pul down, than either eſtabliſh or ſet vp this authority of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents: and there is nothing ſo much with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawes our children from duetie and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence as thoſe two precepts of the firſt and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Table, which now a daies men make meere contradictories, Honour God, and honour thy parents. Its a maruellous mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that whereas euer heretofore theſe two commandements, held good correſponden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy with each other, and might both be fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led together, they ſhould now bee tearmed oppoſite, and ſo repugnant one to the other, that hee which fulfilles the one, muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity breake the other. But whence come theſe ſtrange &amp; newfound problemes? Marry Sir I will tell you, euen from the diſputes of our ancient Philoſophers that wra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gled about this queſtion, whether at all times, and in all matters, we ought to obey our Fathers com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements? for as there haue been ſome that handled this queſtion iuſt as <hi>Bias</hi> did
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:19591:25"/>the queſtion of ſacriledge; there is no body, ſaith <hi>Bias,</hi> that is ſacrilegious, for if ſome God or other be reſiant in euery place of the world, then doth a thiefe conuey nothing out of one hallowed place, which hee carrieth not into ſome other hallowed place; ſo haue ſome of our Philoſophers vſed the like ſubtlety in treating the matter of this power of parents. There is no neceſſity (ſay they) why you ſhold obey your parents: for either they command that which is iuſt, and we muſt doe it, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they commaund it, but becauſe it is iuſt; or els they commaund that which is vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and vve may not doe it, not becauſe they commaund it, but becauſe it is vnlavvfull. Whereupon the concluſion follovves, <hi>ergo</hi> there is no obedience due to them at all; yea but <hi>Gellius</hi> replies, the Dilemme is not perfect, for that ſome things are of a nevv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and indifferent nature, vvherein vve muſt obey them abſolutelie, and ſome things are in their ovvn nature good, and honeſt which vve are the more bound to do, becauſe they commaund them. Some diſtinguiſh other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe; in ſome caſes wee muſt obey, in others wee may not. For, what if my father ſhould commaund mee to plot treaſon againſt my Country, to murther my mother, to kill my Prince, or facts of the like deteſtable and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:19591:25"/>impious nature. Right ſo, whileſt the Schoole Diuines began to argue, whether one might ſerue God and man, or whether God were to bee ſerued before father (as though there were any queſtion to be made of it, but God muſt, without all exception bee obeide, when the matter commaunded tends to impietie) they fell fowle vppon the ſame tenents, with the Philoſophers, which were verie vncertaine, idle, and blaſphemous. In good ſouth, I hate not the perſon of any man that makes difference betwixt honeſt and vnho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, lawfull and vnlawfull, nor yet them nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which make ſome things neuter and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different. The opinion in ſome ſort is to bee excuſed: but without doubt, the ſafer way had been, neuer to haue ſtirred in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that is, if they had not reuolted from thoſe mens iudgements, which helde the queſtion affirmatiuelie, and without diſtinction, that parents in all things were to be obeide. For ſay it be true, which by a cauilling diſtinction they haue put vpon vs, yet to my thinking they haue no ſound footing to ſtand vpon for it: and to ſpeake my opinion, the determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of ſuch queſtions is exceeding dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous. How much more cautelous and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpect then was <hi>Philo,</hi> writing vpon the decalogue, when treating of the two firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:19591:26"/>of the two Tables, he ſaith (as his manner is to doe all things) moſt diuine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie: they that leauing all other affaires of the world, beſtow themſelues wholly vpon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation, or they that abandoning all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion, apply themſelues to action wholie to obſerue their parents diſpoſition, conforming themſelues reſpectiuelie to liue in the world, as though they would bee taken apart, either for Gods ſeruants in the one, or mens friends and followers in the other: I tell you theſe mens vertues are but perfect by the halfes: nay, he that offends againſt either partie of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fends againſt both. Doubtleſſe ſome ſuch matters there be which will neuer bee drawne to anie manner of mediocritie or indifferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, but preſentlie they doe ſome harme or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: for doe but ſhake them a little, &amp; they ſtagger preſentlie; bring them to the touch, you will finde they cannot endure the triall. Theſe diminitiue queſtions be like fine cates, for as the more dainetie and delicate they be, do ſooner putrifie and corrupt in the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, ſo theſe if they be too much minſed and refined, they mar the generall tenant which is defended of all men. Whether the Biſhop of Rome be aboue or vnder a generall Councell, whether the Emperor be aboue the people, whether democracie be better then
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:19591:26"/>monarchie, whether in religion contrarietie of ſects may be tollerated, at firſt ſight, they be ſet forth with a maruellous faire ſhow, but if you marke them well, there is poiſon ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in, when you come to the reckoning. For vpon theſe and ſuch other like diſputes, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie day enſue, ſchiſmes, ſeditions, ciuill wars, &amp; this queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> now in handling, is much after the ſame ſort. For he that once made but a doubt whether the dutie and reſpect which we owe to our parents were to binde vs for terme of life, and not rather of <hi>Turuus</hi> his opinion maintained againſt <hi>Tarquinius</hi>) that there was no ſuch ſummary proceeding, as when father and ſon were parties, where the iſſue was ſoone tried, if he be vndutifull, fare him wel, and al ill luck go with him. Make but the leaſt breach into the fort of naturall dutie, ye ſhall preſentlie ſee how he falls to railing, and reuiling, to ſtabbing, nay to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering of it. And ſo hauing begun with his father, he is like enough to finiſh it with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection againſt his Prince. This then was euer a maine determination, amongſt the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient philoſophers, that obedience in all things was preciſely to be yeelded vnto, when our pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts required it. Or put caſe, any incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenience ſhould happen thereupon, better were it to admit the propoſition, in termes of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:19591:27"/>largeſt extent, than out of any priuate or par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular caſe to argue againſt a common and receiued opinion, and to determine it accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinglie, either in ſchooles, conſiſtories, or pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits. And this doth <hi>Cicero</hi> wifely obſerue in his booke of offices, yee ſhall not find anre ſuch queſtion in all his booke: he was euer reſolute and confident vpon the point, that children muſt not be their pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts maſter, nor ſubiects their Princes, nor ſchollers their teachers, nor ſeruants their Lords: not, but that ſometimes they far ſurpaſſe them for wit and pregnant diſcourſe, but that it cannot be auoided but that iniuries and contempts will be offered, when ſuch compariſon and oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of perſons is once endured. Let autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie be once diſgraced, and farewell autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. When in a great ſeſſion of the <hi>Centum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiri</hi> holden at <hi>Rome, Accia Variola,</hi> went about to diſproue the will of her father, which ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times had borne the office of a Pretor there, for that he had bequeathed vnreaſonable le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacies to her ſtepmother, there came to the hearing of the cauſe ſo many fathers together with their children, vpon a feare and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation of which ſide the fathers or the daug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, the ſentence ſhould paſſe, that the Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges (as <hi>Plinie</hi> reports) like wiſe men left the matter as they found it. For no other occaſion
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:19591:27"/>than this, leaſt peraduenture if iudgement had been giuen for the daughter, other chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren by her example might in time preſume to conteſt with their parents. But to come neerer to the matter, in theſe like queſtions, I would faine learne whom we ſhould follow, prophane Philoſophers, or the bleſſed Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> who in his Epiſtle to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſſians, aduiceth thus, <hi>Children obey your parents in all things, for this is pleaſing with God,</hi> where when he expreſly ſetteth downe <hi>in all things,</hi> hath he not vtterly excluded, thoſe two parts of the diſtinction, <hi>In ſome things you muſt obey; in ſome things you may chuſe whether you will obey or no?</hi> and the concluſion withall, <hi>we be not bound to obey?</hi> nay but why did God the father of all parents, forbid <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> to eate of the fruit of the tree in the midſt of the garden, but that he would trie whether <hi>Adam</hi> would obey him in all things or no, as ſaith <hi>Theophilus</hi> to <hi>Eutol?</hi> nor is the obiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on worth the ſtanding vpon: why but what if the father ſhould command any treaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble practiſe or attempt againſt the eſtate? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe here is a caſe put which neuer happens at the hundreds end, or ſo ſeldome, that it would be paſt ouer in ſilence, and neuer more lookt after. Nay contrarie wiſe, (as I ſhould thinke) the preſumption is ſtrong and holds
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:19591:28"/>for the father, what manner a man ſoeuer he be; good or bad that he will neuer command his ſonne, that which he in his conſcience knowes to be fowle and diſhoneſt. Yea let the mother be neuer ſo laſciuiouſlie giuen, yet will ſhe traine vp her daughter in chaſte and vertuous demeanour. Moreouer, he that argues this act of a fathers command makes that a reaſon for his allegation, which is mainly againſt all reaſon, that is, he ſuppoſes old men doting fooles, and yong men graue counſellors: he makes the ſonne iudge whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the fathers actions be lawfull or againſt law, good in their owne nature, or by his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction and ſurmiſe. And all this can neuer agree to diſcretion, and honeſty. For ſo he ſowes matter of queſtion and debate, where indeed the only vertue ſhould be (the vertue ſo highly eſteemed of the noble Lacedemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians) to yeeld obedience and that readilie. But becauſe error is growne potent, and hath giuen ſuch a deepe wound as the ſcarre will hardlie be couered ouer, let vs a little by the way conſider what were thoſe neuter and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different things which <hi>Gellius</hi> ſpeaketh of? to my remembrance they be theſe, as if (ſaith he) thy father bid thee to be a ſouldier, to till his land, to be an officer, to be an aduocate, to marrie a wife, to goe vpon his errand, come
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:19591:28"/>when thou art ſent for, and ſuch like, which in themſelues be neither good nor bad, but as the intent is and manner of doing them, ſo may they merit blame or commendation. For if the father ſhould charge me to marry a wife that were infamous, paſt all ſhame, or diſparagious for any enormious crime, if he would haue me plead <hi>Catiline</hi> or <hi>Bibulus,</hi> or <hi>Clodius</hi> his cauſe, then were his comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment herein not indifferent becauſe here is a troupe of diſhoneſty one vpon the necke of another. So that if his pleaſure were to enioin me ſuch actions, the queſtion were at an end, how far forth I ſhould obey him: were it not that the thing which <hi>Gellius</hi> plainly pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth for indifferent, as to marrie a wife, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into this or that kind of life, now adaies are taught to be of ſuch nature, that conſent &amp; authoritie of father is nothing thought of or reſpected in them: my ſonne may marrie, may be a Church man, may be a monke, not onlie without my leaue, but ſpight of my teeth though I doe expreſly forbid him, and that which all Vniuerſities, all Conſiſtories, all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, of learned men, without any inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption or impediment haue euer permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in fauour of naturall dutie, that doe theſe men, vnder pretence of faith and religion, vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terlie reuerſe and diſanull. But our enſewing
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:19591:29"/>diſcourſe ſhall ſpeciallie in this place be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined within the compaſſe of religious vowes, wherin I muſt haue leaue to tell thee, that either thou art in falt that without any priuity or conſent of mine betookeſt thy ſelfe thus to the Ieſuits order; or I am to be blamed that notwithſtanding holy Church affoords thee ſuch a libertie, grieue and take on for the ſame. For as concerning the argument of mariage &amp; the freedom thereof, whether pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents haue any voice in their childrens be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowing, our countriman <hi>Paquerius</hi> hath writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſo learnedlie thereof in his Epiſtles, as who ſhould but offer to adde one line, to that which he hath written of that ſubiect, might rather preiudice his owne iudgement, than a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny way the picture drawne by the pencill of ſo curious a workman. I muſt needs confeſſe that the determination of the Biſhops aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in the Councell of Trent makes much for my contryman his purpoſe, that although clandeſtine contracts, made without the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents aduiſe and leaue) ſtand for good mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age till the Church diſalow them, yet neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe for many weighty and important conſiderations, the Church thought it beſt altogether to interdict and diſauow them. It ſeems ſhe would haue a reſeruation in her ſelfe to determine the controuerſie, and not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:19591:29"/>it ouer to the arbitrement of parents, whether ſuch mariages were good and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to lawe, or contrarily void and of none effect. I muſt likewiſe grant that ſundry con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions enacted heretofore by many of our chriſtian Princes in their Diets and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, are pregnant for his purpoſe, namely that ſuch matches are no better than a rape and no mariage at all, or if it be, they take or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to vndoe the mariage knot with the point of an imperiall ſword. Yet for all that which <hi>Paquerius</hi> hath written about the queſtion, I would pray leaue to adde two no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table precedents, not with that ſelfe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt or arrogancie, as though I meant to confirme or confute ought about the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tract of maiarge, which either the Church or our moſt illuſtrious Princes haue beene pleaſed hitherto in their excellent wiſedomes to determine, but that our children might hereby know and be well inſtructed, that all that is according to lawe, is not therefore by and by according to honeſtie, leaſt perhaps that contempt and neglect which now they meaſure vnto vs, be afterwards by a iuſt ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of reuenge written in heauen, meaſured by their children vnto them alſo. The one example is of <hi>Rebecca,</hi> and the woman of <hi>Timnath,</hi> both which although God had
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:19591:30"/>appointed the one for <hi>Sampſon,</hi> and the other for <hi>Iſaacke,</hi> yet it pleaſed him notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that theſe marriages ſhould firſt be made by the aduiſe and liking of their parents, that <hi>Rebecca</hi> ſhould be demanded of <hi>Bathuel,</hi> of the mother, and of the Vnckle, yet ſo, as <hi>Abraham</hi> the father muſt giue charge about the meſſage, and not the ſonne <hi>Iſaacke, thou ſhalt be diſcharged from my oath, ſaith Abraham to his</hi> ſeruant, <hi>if thou goe vnto my country and to my kinsfolke, and they ſhal not giue her vnto thee.</hi> The Angell of the Lord made way to theſe mariages, but their parents contracted them; The other example is of <hi>Tertullian</hi> in a treatiſe written to his wife: Oh how ſhall I be able (ſaith he) worthily to deſcribe and ſet foorth the bleſſed eſtate of that couple, whom the Church hath ioined together, praier and thanksgiuing haue confirmed, angels in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen proclaimed, and the father in earth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued, for euen here in the world children may not marrie without their parents con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and approbation, either in reſpect of due ſolemnitie or force of law. Doubtleſſe his meaning hereby was, that mariage among Chriſtians had better ſucceſſe and proſperity when firſt it was approued by almighty God, as hauing in this world the conſent of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:19591:30"/>and in that other the conſent of our father which is in heauen. The ſame opinion was maintained by <hi>Soterus</hi> liuing vnder the raign of the Emperor <hi>Commodus,</hi> as alſo auer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by <hi>Euariſtus</hi> and S. <hi>Ambroſe.</hi> Proceed we then in Gods name and let vs now diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of religious vowes, not queſtioning their validitie, nor the perfection of the reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious or lay life, which of them both is better nor any ſuch matters. But whether children be at their owne libertie and pleaſure to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue and make ſolemne profeſſion of a vow, if the father be not acquainted firſt with it, or elſe if he diſclaime it; as alſo whether without him a ſonne may enter into the Eccleſiaſtical vocation, and the father muſt not preſent him before he be admitted to holy orders. Hereof I ſay we will preſume to entreat ſo far foorth as a meane Ciuilian may haue good leaue, either to know or take in hand, ſuch ſecret miſteries of your profeſſion. And if the whole faculty of Diuines, or thoſe ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of yours, haue any thing elſe in ſtore, to giue me ſatisfaction in my queſtion, let me vnderſtand of it as ſoone as may be poſſible, that ſo for mine owne part I may ſet downe, and reſt contented by their reſolution. But for you ſir, I would haue you to lurke no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in corners, but make your perſonall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:19591:31"/>to the ſummons, and be not afraid boldly to chant that high ſentence of <hi>S. Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome,</hi> againſt them, which in a depraued ſence they haue perhaps trumpt in thy way: <hi>Cruelty in ſuch a caſe is your only piety.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt then let it be conſidered how paynim people obſerued their vows. For though they were far wide of the true worſhip of God, yet in their religion, they left out nothing which might any waie make, either for the honor, maintenance, or enlargement of it, nay it were hard to ſay, whether therein they ſurpaſſed not vs Chriſtians. True it is, that theſe pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nims were not very ſcrupulous to offer either themſelues or their goods to Idolls, nor was it very materiall with them why and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they made ſuch raſh vowes. Neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, this was euer a diſputable queſtion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, whether the vow were of any va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidity, without the fathers conſent and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie. Moſt certaine it is that in the matter of ſacrificing the children the parents were to offer them to the ſacrifice, the caſe is cleare out of <hi>Tertullian</hi> in his <hi>Apologeticus,</hi> whereas ſaith he, <hi>Saturne</hi> neuer vſed to ſpare either his owne children or other mens, but indifferent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deuoured both; thereupon ſuch as were pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents offered their ſonnes and daughters to be his ſacrifices, and willingly expoſed them
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:19591:31"/>to him, nay they would fawne and flatter the poore innocents, to the intent, that they ſhold not howl &amp; crie, when they were to be ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced which you may likewiſe read in <hi>Plutarch</hi> in his booke which he entitles <hi>Of Superſtition,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the end: but ſay, there were no parents liuing to giue vp their childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to this diueliſh abomination? what was to be done in ſuch a caſe? Its well inough knowne, that the Prieſt had no ſuch power or authoritie, to take whom he pleaſde for the ſacrifice. This was a ſpeciall prerogatiue reſerued for the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate (and more then this came to) hee choſe out the virgin by lot, which was appointed to be ſacrificed, that ſo the Gods might ſeem to be at their own choice for the oblation, and not at the Prieſts deuotion, and on whomſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the lot fell, ſhee was to be offered, as you may reade in <hi>Homer</hi> of <hi>Iphigenia Agamem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons</hi> daughter, in <hi>Panſanias,</hi> of <hi>Lyciſcus</hi> and <hi>Ariſtodemus</hi> their daughters, in <hi>Plutarch</hi> of <hi>Smincheus his daughter,</hi> whom the Dolphins ſafely ſet a ſhore, with her ſweet heart <hi>Eualus.</hi> Hence come thoſe themes vſuall &amp; frequent in declamations. A virgin ſacrificed to the peſtilence. A ſonne that is diſinherited, to bee offered for ſacrifice. A ſiſter liuing infamou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly to be ſacrificed. Which ſort of Rhetoricall exerciſe, partly you may read in <hi>Quintilian,</hi>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:19591:32"/>(an Author by me firſt reſtored to his inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gritie) partlie in <hi>Calphurnius,</hi> for whome the learned <hi>Pitheus</hi> did as much; but in all theſe and the like, it would be noted, that ſhould the ſonne or daughter voluntarily offer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, their parents are euer oppoſed as meet and able perſons in law to except againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For no man would haue admitted ſuch a bar (I promiſe you) I thinke ſcarce among boyes in the Schoole, if children might haue beene permitted to ſacrifice themſelues. And hence it commeth (as you may reade it in <hi>Philoſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi>) that <hi>Meneceus Creons</hi> ſonne, vpon an anſwere of <hi>Tireſias</hi> the Prophet, ſacrificed him ſelfe without his fathers priuitie, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe meant to hinder him from ſuch a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. But moſt memorable is that which is written by <hi>Plutarch</hi> in his booke of <hi>Superstiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> that if a man had not any children of his owne, the faſhion was to buy them of ſome poore people: but in that caſe, it might not ſerue the turne to haue him preſent, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting, that made ſale of his childe, it was beſides requiſite that the naturall mother, ſhould come forth, eyther to teſtifie her wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſſe, that her ſonne ſhould die in that manner, or to forbid the ſacrifice. <hi>Virgil</hi> in the eleuenth of his <hi>Aencidos</hi> glanceth at ſuch like ſacrifices, when he brings in <hi>Metabus,</hi> dren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:19591:32"/>of his daughter <hi>Camilla</hi> in the riuer <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſenus,</hi> and thus beſpeaking:
<q>
                  <l>Faire Queen of the ſpringing woods, chaſt Lady Diana,</l>
                  <l>Here to thy ſeruice I do vow Camilla my daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</l>
               </q> Vpon which place, <hi>Seruius</hi> his note is good. Twas well ſaid, <hi>the father himſelfe vowed her:</hi> for that none but fathers had their children vnder ſuch bonds of <hi>obedience.</hi> And <hi>Plutarch</hi> in his booke of <hi>Iſis and Oſiris,</hi> talkes to <hi>Clea</hi> the Nunne, in a Phraſe of the like ſtraine: <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſince thou waſt a childe, thy parents dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thee to the ſeruice of the Goddeſſe Oſiris.</hi> And thus much in briefe for the Grecians.</p>
            <p>Now to come to our Anceſtors, among the <hi>Gawles</hi> (as it is yet with vs) there were three eſtates and orders among them: the <hi>Druidet</hi> were the men of moſt principall marke and eſteeme, and were ſo highly reputed of, and had ſuch large priuiledges, by reaſon of their ſacred Miniſteries, and their interpretations of doubtfull queſtions in religion, that well was hee that could bee of their company, to be enrowled and profeſt in their rule. What? but might children ſo doe without their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parents liking? No forſooth, as you may well vnderſtand by <hi>Caeſar</hi> his owne relation, ſome (ſaith he) be allured with great rewards, ſome
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:19591:33"/>out of a voluntarie diſpoſition enfrock them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues into the Religion; ſome their parents ſend thither, and ſome their kinsfolke. Such were Voluntaries, as were at their owne diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing, ſuch as were ſent thither, liued vnder awe and charge of parents or guardian. The Romanes haue a title in their booke of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſts, <hi>De Pollicitationibus, of Promiſes,</hi> in them there is ſpecial mention made of ſuch promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, as either we make ſolemnely to God, or to our Countrie: but if a ſonne liuing in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection to his Father, ſhould make any ſuch promiſe, it were nothing worth, and this, <hi>Vl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pian</hi> out of his learning deliuers vnto vs for law. Men that be Maſters of families after they come to bee of full age, are bound by their vowe and ſolemne promiſe: but as for a ſon during his minormity, or a bondſlaue whilſt he is a villain, neither of them can bind themſelues by their vowe without the fathers or Lords authority. Indeed he that is a maſter of a family after the death of the aunceſtor, muſt neceſſarilie be of full age, to make his vowe good, but let the ſonne be neuer ſo old, and make a vow, be it not ratified firſt by the fathers approbation, it is vtterlie voide and of no effect in lawe: and the caſe is the ſame, though he haue a ſtocke of monie or anie patrimonie of his owne, to imploy and occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:19591:33"/>for his preferment: the vow notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding al this is of no force or obligatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in law. And what may the reaſon hereof be? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he that is not his owne man, can neither come in bond himſelfe, nor ſtatute out anie thing that he hath. Moreouer he that hath right and intereſt to any thing, cannot looſe it but by ſome fact of his owne. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a ſonne liuing in ſubiection vnder his father, howbeit he might be termed to doe a godlie and religious act by vowing and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing that which is none of his owne, yet were the act (though to neuer ſo religious vſe) no better than plaine theft and pillage: firſt in vowing his patrimonie, and ſubſtance, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the father hath a propertie in it, then in vowing his perſon which is a matter in deed of greater conſequence, becauſe he is no free man to this intent, abſolutelie to diſpoſe of himſelfe: and the parents by ſuch a conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration ſhould wrongfully be depriued of the heire of the houſe, the hope of their linage, and the propagation both of their name and familie, and laſtlie of all ſuch goods and chat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels, which being purchaſed by the child, were after him, to reuert vnto the fathers poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſo that for iuſtifying of the ſonnes vowe, the conſent and allowance of the father was eſſentiallie neceſſarie. Very fauourable is that
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:19591:34"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:19591:34"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:19591:35"/>interpretation which makes for religion, (we doubt not) yet withall not to be rackt to ſo high a ſtraine, as thereby to neglect all due and laudable ſolemnities, for that were the next way rather to prophane religion, than to aduance it. Our father and our country haue each one as much authoritie as the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (let that be gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted) yet (as <hi>Liuy</hi> ſtorieth it) when <hi>P. Cornelius Scipio</hi> was Pretor in <hi>Spaine,</hi> and had vpon the great ieopardie of a battell, promiſed ſolemne plaies and ſhewes, after the victorie was obtained, made afterwards ſuit to the Senate for ſome alotment of monie out of the treaſurie to that vſe, their anſwer was, that his vowe bound not the Senate of <hi>Rome</hi> and therefore he ſhould make plaies and ſhewes in Gods name, at his owne charge, and vpon his owne purſe, or with ſuch ſpoiles and booties as he had taken in the war. Now may a ſonne doe that with his fathers goods, and that without asking him any leaue, which the greateſt officer in <hi>Rome</hi> could not doe without the Senates warrant? if you tell me, that theveſtall virgins might beſtow them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues againſt their fathers will, becauſe they were ſaid <hi>to bee taken, not to bee choſen,</hi> and that therefore the high Prieſt, did not receiue them as preſented by their parents, but <hi>tooke</hi> them away perforce; ſuch kind of reaſoning,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:19591:35"/>from the nature of the word, will ſtand them in ſmall ſtead: for this ſolemnitie or phraſe of ſpeech which the Biſhop vſed, <hi>I take thee Amy,</hi> is ſo far from implying, that there was any vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willingneſſe or violence in the action, that it makes moſt eſpecially for that purpoſe which we maintaine. Surely there was no <hi>taking</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome <hi>giuing,</hi> and in this ſence the high prieſt, <hi>tooke her</hi> that was dedicated to <hi>Veſta,</hi> but by your leaue ſhe was firſt giuen and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented by her father. Whence <hi>Metabus</hi> in <hi>Virgil</hi> infers, <hi>Take here thy ſeruant Goddeſſe chaſt.</hi> but <hi>Gellius</hi> cleares the point in his firſt booke: therefore it ſeemes to be ſaid, that the maiden is <hi>taken</hi> becauſe (ſaith he) the high Prieſt <hi>taking</hi> her by the hand, lead her away as a captiue from her father vnder whoſe obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience ſhe liued: and ſome few words before that, hauing recited the ancient ſolemnitie of the Papian law, which enacted <hi>choice and lot</hi> as fitteſt meanes to be vſed in the admiſſion of any perſon vnto religion. At this time, ſaith he, if any man of credit or worſhip, come to the high Prieſt, and offer his daughter to be a Nunne, the profeſſion is as lawful, as if all the ceremonies had been performed, which the Papian law requires. And it was a matter of ſuch neceſſity, that the daughter ſhould be offered by the parents, that if ſhe were an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phan
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:19591:36"/>fatherleſſe and motherleſſe, ſhe was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted vneligible for that religion. The ſame may be ſaid, if either ſhe her ſelfe were eman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipated, and ſet at libertie by her father, and in the life time of the father, became ſubiect to the power of her grandfather, ſhe was to be refuſed and put by, as a perſon vneligible: and why ſo, might not her grandfather pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent her? might not her guardian? might not her ouerſeer? if ſhe were at her owne diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing, might ſhe not vowe and offer vp her ſelfe? <hi>Labeo Antiſtius</hi> wil tel you ſhe might not, becauſe a girle vnder ſix, or aboue ten could not be receiued into the order. Why but might not any other preſent her? no, there was none ſo fit, and without all exception for the purpoſe, <hi>as her owne father.</hi> If any elſe had done it, there muſt haue beene ſome ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary hearing and debating of the matter, but had the father done it, it was thought need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and vnneceſſary. For as when a naturall father, will adopt his naturall and baſe borne child, to be his lawfull ſonne, the adoption wil hold vpon anie termes, ſo it is in point of conſecration; let but the father tender his child to religion, and there is nothing elſe expected For what if the daughter, vpon ſom diſlike or other would leaue <hi>Veſtaes</hi> cloiſter, and lay it to her grandfather or gardians
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:19591:36"/>charge, that they had no ſuch authoritie or commiſſion, to make her change her eſtate and manner of liuing, that this power belongs only to him that hath power of her life and death, that is, her father, as <hi>Seneca</hi> tels me? For the grandfather had nothing to doe with it: ſurelie he that makes a poore yong girle enter into an order of religion, that liued before in the world at large, doth in manner execute her aliue, and make her a baniſht woman in her owne country: and therefore not without good cauſe, the <hi>father</hi> alone was put in truſt with this high authority. For as for the chiefe Prieſts authoritie &amp; vſurped right, were it not firſt giuen &amp; take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the fathers leaue and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, it was iudged to all intents and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes clearelie voide in lawe. Now ſhould it be vrged, why but this which you ſpeake of, was of vſe onelie in veſt all Nunnes, and that principallie by reaſon of their minoritie, when they were profeſſed Nunnes, this ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection is eaſily anſwered and the contrarie opinion clearely euicted by <hi>Gellius</hi> his owne words which be theſe, <hi>Manie be of opinion that onlie virgins ſhould bee taken after this faſhion, to orders of religion, nay but euen</hi> Iupiters <hi>Priests, the Biſhoppes, the ſoothſaiers, were to bee taken and admitted in the ſelfe ſame faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> And certaine it is, that male children in
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:19591:37"/>their parents life time, were ſo taken. Doe we not read in <hi>Dion,</hi> that when the great contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie was about <hi>Cornelius Spinter</hi> his admiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on into the Chapter of the high Prieſts, though <hi>Fauſtus</hi> were both his kinſman and an high Prieſt, likewiſe in the Colledge, that the naturall and adoptiue fathers did both ioine in this, to make good their preſentation for their ſonne and not the ſonne for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe? queſtionleſſe it is, that children could not exempt themſelues from filiall obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, had not the father firſt allowed them the libertie, which needed neuer to haue been granted them, if they might haue made vows at their owne pleaſure, and without their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers conſent. But that I may come by little and little to times of chriſtianitie, (for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance theſe heatheniſh examples, can doe little good with you) I pray you, as you think, what lawe or cuſtome had the Iewes for their precedent in this caſe? firſt, it is not ſaid anie where in expreſſe tearmes to the ſonne, Leaue father and mother, but with this prouiſoe, that he ſhould cleaue to his wife. If any thing be otherwiſe ſpoken it is by way of aduice, and may not paſſe vpon truſt without ſtricter ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination, as it ſhall elſe where be declared more at large. In deed in caſe of mariage there is an abſolute commandement penned, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:19591:37"/>all limitation, to renounce all naturall affection and dutie, but in other caſes it is done with ſo many cautels and deliberati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that in my iudgement it were better ſtill to keepe on the high rode way, than to iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney by coaſting. But whatſoeuer it be, that <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> in that place ſpeakes of the relinquiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our parents, doth the argument thereupon conclude, that the knot of wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locke, is of more force and power then the bond of filiall dutie? nay verily, for this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds and ſprings from nature, and (which is more) from our owne indiuiduall and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall ſubſiſtence: that other, from a deſire to propagate a mutuall ſocietie and conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation amongſt men. And whereas, a man and his vvife be accounted as it were for one per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, this is in the intent and imagination of the law, and therefore we ſee them eaſily to be parted againe, as <hi>Anaſtaſius</hi> ſpeaketh in the tenth booke of his commentaries vpon the <hi>Hexameron.</hi> But the ſonne is altogether bone of our bone, and fleſh of our fleſh, he is one and the ſelfe ſame perſon with his father, a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of the ſelfe ſame ſubſtance, and (as I may ſo ſay) a verie piece carued out of his body and ſoule: whence it followes, that come what can come, a ſonne muſt euer be a ſonne: Diſinhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit him, turne him into the wide world to ſhift
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:19591:38"/>for himſelfe, ſell him, leaue him to his owne libertie, ſuffer him to be adopted into another family, ſtill nature holds her owne, bloud and kindred will neuer be altered Before the Emperor <hi>Conſtantines</hi> daies, had the father vnnaturally forſaken and caſt off his daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, yet might ſhe not marry an husband with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his conſent But a man might be rid of his wife (God he knows) many wais: by the ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of a Iudge in Court, by madneſſe (ſuch a law the Emperor <hi>Leo</hi> made) by a ſeparation from bed and boord, by bondage and laſtly by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorce: but in children the caſe is admirable: that, though the principall obligation be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed, (as ſay I am diuorced from my wife) yet the acceſſorie holds, that is, children which be wedlockes pledges, though their mother be not my wife, yet are they my children: they be morgaged by nature, and ſo muſt they euer continue. But if the caſe ſtand ſo, then why doth a ſonne forſake father and mother to cleaue vnto his wife? why doth he forſake the greater commandement, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take him to the leſſe? becauſe in this caſe, the parents vnderhand be willing hereunto, as in a deſire to haue the world peopled, by propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of children, ſo to maintaine a lineall ſucceſſion in poſterity, and the inheritance
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:19591:38"/>euer to deſcend vpon the grandchild after the death of the ſonne and heire. And yet to keepe houſe with a wife, in anie conſtruction, is this, to leaue or abandon ones father? nay herein conſiſts their principall dutie and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. And if they marrie, and keepe houſe together and ſo deduct as it were new Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, all is done with leaue, and reference to their parents. And for my part, I would faine know, how it can in anie ſence be conſtrued that for a man to marrie a wife is to forſake and relinquiſh his father and mother, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as children though they be maried neuer ſo often, are not thereby exempted from obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and though they be eftſoones man and wife, yet be they ſtil in ſubiection to their father? and mariage changes not the lawes of nature, and ciuilitie? But be it as it may be, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God calling to his remembrance the law which firſt he eſtabliſhed in paradiſe, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded alſo this heauenlie diuine commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to <hi>Adams</hi> ſentence, that whether chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren marrie or not marrie his oracle ſhould continue without all exception and inſtance to the contrarie, <hi>honour thy father and thy mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:</hi> yea and that in more preciſe and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate manner of ſpeech than if he ſhould haue ſaid obey father or mother, for obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is contained in honour, and he that is
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:19591:39"/>not bound to obey, muſt neuertheleſſe be bound to honor. For examples ſake, if by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremitie and rigour of law, you may marry or profeſſe your ſelfe a monke, againſt my will, and that ſuch a vow and mariage, is in a ſort iuſtifiable and good, yet ſhould you notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding euen by force of that commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment come and aske me firſt leaue, and craue mine aduiſe in the matter, which though it be no obedience in your part yet it is mine ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor. Laſtlie you ſhould haue ſhewed me, what mooued you to this or that courſe of life, whether your owne naturall propenſion, and deliberate inclination, or ſome ſtrange circumuention &amp; forraine perſwaſion? But let that dutie and cuſtome be omitted, and let the act neuertheleſſe, be accounted as lawfull as is anie, yet where is the honor which God hath preſcribed? where is that reuerence and dutie, which humanitie bindeth you vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to? if it be done onelie but for ſolemnitie, why then you muſt know that ſolemnity giues the eſſence to the act. Let vs proceed. It is ſtoried by <hi>Marius Victor</hi> that famous orator of <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeiles</hi> in his third title of his Commentarie vpon <hi>Geneſis,</hi> that God commaunded not <hi>Abraham</hi> (albeit from his youth vp he wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped the true God with all his ſoule, and
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:19591:39"/>abhorred gentiliſme) to leaue his country, and that wicked land and polluted houſe, before that he ſaw, that after his fathers death, hee might without offence keepe that comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, which he had giuen him. What ſhall we ſay the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? that the Ieſuits haue greater com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand ouer thee, then God had ouer <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham:</hi> he was 75. yeere old, and his parents were dead, before God commanded him that he ſhould leaue his country, and goe vp vnto the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> &amp; doſt thou which art yet but 16. yeers old, my ſelfe and thy mother yet liuing, forſake me &amp; thy countrie, becauſe the Ieſuits bid thee? if thou doſt it for the keeping of anothers vow, yet that dutie which both by the law of God and nature, thou oweſt me is greater. But <hi>Marius</hi> of <hi>Marſeiles</hi> (for your learning) liued in the time of <hi>Theodoſius</hi> and <hi>Valence</hi> the Emperors, and the Ieſuits were not heard of: there were no ſuch creatures, till the raign of <hi>Francis</hi> the firſt our King. Moreouer why did God command the ſame <hi>Abraham,</hi> to ſacrifice vnto him his owne ſonne, and to be the Prieſt himſelf, but becauſe he thought the counſell of the fathers was expedient to be vſed in euerie cauſe, that concerned their children? if it had been all one vnto God, who had offered vp <hi>Iſacke</hi> vnto him, and if
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:19591:40"/>the ſacrifice ſhould haue been as gratefull and acceptable vnto him being offered by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man as by the hands of his owne father, why ſurelie he would haue commanded this office to ſome other, rather than to his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Abraham.</hi> For religion is not the holier or the more ſanctified becauſe it is ioined with parricide. what then? God would haue <hi>Iſaacke</hi> offered vp vnto him. But becauſe this oblation was to proceed from his father, he commanded him to doe it, who by reaſon of his fatherlie authoritie, could not offend in ſlaying him. <hi>A father is not guilty of parricide, ſaith Aelius Martianus</hi> the great counſellor at the Ciuill law. If thou wilt ſay that in <hi>Iſack</hi> &amp; <hi>Samuel</hi> the cauſe, why it was neceſſarie that their parents ſhould offer them to the Lord, was by reaſon of their minoritie, in regard they were yong &amp; vnder age: why the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Iephthe</hi> for certaine was ſacrificed by her father (as was <hi>Praxithea by Erictheus, and Calpurnia, by her father Marius) after the Cim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brian war,</hi> when ſhe was fit for mariage. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer what might be obiected againſt <hi>Eliſeus?</hi> he being called to the office of a Prophet (which was a regular and ſtrict kind of life, as appeared both by their vnction mantell and abſtinence) albeit he was an elder in yeers and called thereunto by the Prophet <hi>Elias,</hi>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:19591:40"/>and that by a ſpeciall command from God, made this anſwer, <hi>I pray thee let me goe kiſſe my father and my mother, and then I will follow, thee.</hi> The kiſſe was the fathers benediction, &amp; the leaue was that which he deſired ſo much of the Prophet, to take before his departure? what ſaid <hi>Elias? Goe and return, for what was my dutie, I haue done vnto thee.</hi> As if he ſhould haue ſaid, <hi>that which remaineth to be done, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth to thy parents.</hi> For although God ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſlie commanded me, that I ſhould annoint thee to be a Prophet, in my roome, after me, yet how could this be done, if theſe ſecond Gods our parents, ſhould haue gaine ſaid it? therefore afterwards when the Prophet had caſt his mantell on him, forthwith <hi>Elizeus</hi> left his plough, and followed <hi>Elias.</hi> But he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted not from his father, before he had firſt taken his leaue of him. Certaine it is, that in the time of the old law perſonall vowes were ranſomed by monie, and the vowes of the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarites</hi> endured but for a time. But in the thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth Chapter of <hi>Numbers,</hi> it is ſo manifeſtlie ſet downe what ought to be obſerued concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the daughter, that it were ſhame for a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to vouch anie thing to the contrarie. <hi>If a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> (ſaith <hi>Moſes) vowe a vowe, and bind her ſelfe with an oath, being in her fathers houſe, her vowe ſhall ſtand, except ſhe hath done it, againſt
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:19591:41"/>her fathers conſent.</hi> But leaſt her youth might be pretended for an excuſe, the ſame is written of a wife alſo, whether ſhe as yet remaine in her fathers houſe, or whether ſhe be brought vnto her husbands, her vowe ſhould not ſtand, if her husband conſented not vnto it. <hi>Moſes</hi> excepted none beſides a woman diuor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, or a widdow; whence was this? becauſe Gods power was leſſened, by reaſon the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers or husbands conſent, concurred with his? ſurelie no. But becauſe thoſe very powers which they haue, are from God, and by eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing theirs, he confirmeth his owne. But thoſe exceptions of widdowhood or matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie vere not neceſſarie in a ſonne; For as ſoone as he was out of his fathers command there was no doubt, if he were at mans ſtate, but he might lawfullie bind himſelfe with any of thoſe vowes, which were admitted in the old law. For except it were with the vowe of <hi>faſting or abſtinence</hi> from meates, they ſcarce bound themſelues with anie other. But a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man (as at <hi>Rome</hi>) was in perpetuall wardſhip ſometimes of her father, ſometimes of her husband, and ſometimes alſo of her brother, if her father died before ſhe was married. Wherefore if the woman voweda vowe, there the lawgiuer you may ſee) was more cautelous and difficult. But of the ſonne ſo long as he
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:19591:41"/>remained in his fathers houſe, who euer dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in that caſe, but that he was of the ſame condition with his ſiſter? vowed he the gift of anie peece of monie? why it was anothers monie? vowed he his owne perſon? vvhy he had no right to it? that was ſubiect vnto ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. How then could he, vvhich vvas not at his owne diſpoſall, bind himſelfe and vvrong his father, vvho had all dominion and rule o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer him. It wil not be wel, to ſay that there was more dutie expected from vvomen than from men. For tell me, vvhy did thoſe ancient law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers ſo much varie in the queſtion, vvhether the ſonnes of a furious and phranticke man might contract mariage, and yet did all agree that the daughter might. Why did they make ſuch doubt of the ſonne? vvas it not becauſe he vvas the pillar and proppe of the familie? in him was the hope of their poſteritie? from him vvas expected the continuance of their ſtocke, and on him depended the line of their petigree? therefore it is requiſite that greater care be had, that he be not diſparaged in his match, of vvhom more reuerence, more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, and more obedience is required. If hee enter into nevv alliance, if he make his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a grandfather, and beget an heire for him, ought not all this to be done with more aduice, and circumſpection than ordinarie.
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:19591:42"/>And was it not alſo, becauſe age in a ſonne did not ſo importune and call for mariage, but in a daughter it did euen enforce and haſten it before her time? A ſonne, albeit he ſtaied till his father were perfectlie recouered, and well in his wits, there was no inconuenience befell, for thereby his iudgement was ripened, and he prooued the worthier man after, (and I may tell you) good behauiour is as neceſſarie at home as abroad, if old <hi>Cato</hi> may be belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. But a daughter may be the worſe, if ſhe ſtay beyond her time. And that did <hi>Phalaris</hi> once tell <hi>Claeneta</hi> that for the ſame reaſon, ſhe ſhould not defer the mariage of her daughter that was twentie yeers old in anie caſe, becauſe her father <hi>Philodamus</hi> was abſent in a forraine countrie. For he was trauelled farther, than that her daughter might conuenientlie ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect his returne home. But concerning a ſon percaſe he would haue altered his opnion. It followeth therefore that what <hi>Moſes</hi> did forbid in a daughter, he would haue much more forbidden in a ſonne likewiſe.</p>
            <p>But you thinke it long perchance ere I come to the times of chriſtianitie, you do wel. For that is the point of the card whereunto all our courſes ſhould be intended and dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted. Chriſtian religion (you will ſay) other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe determines of childrens dutie. Let vs
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:19591:42"/>ſee then whether Chriſt came to deſtroy it, or to perfect it, corrupt &amp; mar all good man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, by abrogating God his fathers precepts to teach children contempt and ſtubborne behauiour, or rather whether it were not laid as an imputation vpon him, to the end it might bee beleeued, that hee did deface all reſpect of amity and alleagiance, to rent in ſunder all dutifull affection, and make heart-burning and diſcord betweene the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and his children, as ſaith Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> writing vpon Saint <hi>Luke?</hi> We will therefore beginne with Chriſt himſelfe, and afterward come vnto the Church, where if your more refined Diuines haue anything for me, that is in truth more learned and witty, let it haue the victory: for albeit we are all Chriſtians, yet all of vs are not interpreters of the faith: therefore all ſuch Diſputes of greater myſterie, wee leaue to deepe Diuines; and will content our ſelues with ſuch as are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uious and triuiall. Chriſt was twelue yeers olde (<hi>Luke</hi> 2.24.) when hee went vp to <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> with <hi>Mary</hi> and <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> but forſooke them at their departure, therefore they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned backe to <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> to ſeeke him, and it came to paſſe, that three dayes after they found him in the Temple ſitting among the Doctors; to whom <hi>Mary</hi> ſaid; <hi>Sonne why haſt
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:19591:43"/>thou thus dealt with vs? thy Father and I haue ſought thee with heauy hearts.</hi> Hee anſwered ſomewhat obſcurely; but yet (if I am not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued) no leſſe fitlie for the mitigation of their ſorrow, (than thou ſuppoſeſt that thou haſt done for the appeaſing of mine anger) viz. <hi>That it is better to obey God than men.</hi> Yet he returned and went downe with his parents, and came to <hi>Nazareth,</hi> and was ſubiect vnto them, ſaith <hi>Luke</hi> in his Goſpell, did he euer afterwards forſake them? no not vntill the time of his paſſion. But I pray thee, let vs heare farther, what <hi>Bernard</hi> the Abbot ſaith. Although <hi>Mary</hi> and <hi>Ioſeph</hi> vnderſtood Chriſts words (for it is likely they did) becauſe he thus beſpake them, <hi>Knew you not that I muſt goe about my Fathers buſineſſe?</hi> yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding they would not bee quiet, ſaith hee in his 19. Sermon on <hi>Solomon,</hi> but would haue him obedient vnto them: therefore all the reſt of his time, he euer afterwardes fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed them. Now, from whom may we draw a better patterne of obedience and duety to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards parents for children, than from Chriſt. Learne (ſaith S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> vpon theſe words) what thou oweſt to thy parents, when thou readeſt that a ſonne was neuer contrary to his father, either in fulfilling his will, performing his duty, or obſeruing his opportunity. Thou
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:19591:43"/>oweſt to thy mother the hazarding of her chaſtity, the loſſe of her Virginity, her perill in thy birth, her tedious ſorrowes, her conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual troubles (who, wretched as ſhe is) is then in greateſt danger, when ſhe hath the fruition of her deſires, and brought forth the ſonne of her deſire: for albeit ſhe is free from the ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row in his birth; yet is ſhee not free from the feare of his death. What need I ſpeak of thoſe Fathers, which are ſo prouident for their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens good? or of the riches which they haue ſo multiplied and laied vp for them? or of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo warie husbands for their childrens thrift? might not this goodneſſe of theirs at the leaſt, challenge ſome tribute of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence? The ſame Author in his firſt booke <hi>de Virginibus,</hi> ſaith, how ſweete a pledge is that which hath its beginning in perill, and its en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in perill, which firſt is a griefe vnto pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents before it can bee a pleaſure vnto them? The Maſter diſdained not (ſaith <hi>Bernard</hi>) to follow his Diſciples, nor God to follow men, nor the word and wiſdome it ſelfe to follow a Carpenter and his wife: and yet <hi>Ioſeph</hi> was not properly his father. Ieſus fulfilled the will both of his heauenly and earthly father, teaching vs thereby that nothing hinders, but that they may bee both obeyed at once, and that it is not neceſſarie, that one ſhould be
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:19591:44"/>neglected for the other. <hi>Iuſtin Martyr</hi> out of this place in his 136. queſtion, handles ſome other queſtions alſo very wiſely, (as he vſeth to doe all.) If it bee forbidden by Gods holy Scripture, to contemne our parents, (ſaith he) and if he who dooth that which is forbidden, is to bee tearmed a ſinner; how commeth it to paſſe that our Lord Ieſus Chriſt in many places deſpiſed his parents, and yet neuertheleſſe is ſaide to bee without ſinne? For at the marriage of <hi>Cana</hi> hee chec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked his mother, ſaying: <hi>Woman what haue I to doe with thee?</hi> And when his mother would faine haue ſeene him, he called thoſe his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and his brethren, <hi>that did the will of God:</hi> Furthermore, when it was ſaid vnto him, <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed is the wombe that bare thee, and the pappes that gaue thee ſucke:</hi> hee replyed, <hi>yea bleſſed are they that obey the will of God.</hi> All which words are thought to bee ſpoken of him in ſome contempt of his mother; becauſe wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as ſhee was properly called bleſſed; others in oppoſition of her by him, were tearmed bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed alſo. But now ſince this moſt holy Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin was choſen for the conception and birth of our Sauiour Chriſt, how came it to paſſs, that ſhee was accounted vnworthie to be called bleſſed? Here <hi>Iuſtin Martyr</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth this anſwere. Theſe words <hi>(what haue I
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:19591:44"/>to doe with thee?)</hi> were not ſpoken by way of obiurgation, but as if he ſhould haue ſaide in other tearmes; I am not ſuch a one as haue vndertaken the care of wine, which is ſpent in marriages; yet notwithſtanding if your deſire bee that there bee no want of wine, bid the ſeruants doe whatſoeuer I ſhall ſay vnto you, and you ſhall eaſily perceiue there ſhall bee no want of Wine; which as he ſpake, ſo it fell out. Therefore it is not likely that he did checke his mother in wordes, that did ſo much honour her in deedes. As for other places Chriſt ſpake not ſo, as if hee would depriue her of that honour, which was due vnto a mother; but he taught her how ſhe was entituled to true bleſſedneſſe. For if hee that heareth the word of God, and keepeth it bee Chriſts brother, ſiſter and mother; and Chriſts mother hath done both theſe, then it is cleare, that <hi>Mary</hi> in this reſpect ought rather to be called bleſſed. And becauſe God choſe not an ordinary woman to be the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Chriſt, but ſuch a one that was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> other the moſt excellent in perfection and vertues, therefore Chriſt would that his mother ſhould bee moſt commended for that vertue, which gaue her preheminence aboue all women, that a Virgine ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come his mother. Moreouer <hi>Luke</hi> the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliſt
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:19591:45"/>teſtifieth, that Chriſt neuer did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing in contempt or diſgrace of his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, when he ſaith, <hi>Hee went downe with Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph and Mary to Ieruſalem, and was obedient to them, euen to his death:</hi> And ſo alſo ſaith S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> interpreting theſe wordes in his booke, <hi>De Sancta Virginit.</hi> Now Chriſt after that hee began to preach to the people, and withall perceiued that the Scribes and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſies did erre moſt groſly in this commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whereof we treat, and retorted the ſame againſt their parents, vnder this colour, that forſooth they might performe any thing elſe in ſtead of their bounden duety, ſo they did that which they thought to be as iuſt and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſaid, <hi>Why doe you tranſgreſſe the law of God by your tradition? for God hath ſaid, Honour thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and mother, and hee that curſeth father or mother let him die the death: but yee ſay, Whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer ſhall ſay vnto his father or mother, by the gift that is offered by mee thou mayeſt haue profite, though hee honour not his Father and Mother, he ſhall bee ſafe. O yee hypocrites, yee worſhip God in vain, preferring mans precepts before Gods.</hi> Why ſpake Chriſt this ſo ſeuerely? was it becauſe the Phariſies ſo greatly abuſed thoſe offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, and that ſacred treaſure which they cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Corban?</hi> or was it becauſe thoſe oblations, which were deſtinated vnto the Temple, were
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:19591:45"/>by them miſapplyed to themſelues, and to their owne luſts, and not vnto God? ſurelie no, for then hee would haue noted onely their luxurie and abuſe. But hee checked the prieſts becauſe they made compariſon of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, and preferred their owne (which were otherwiſe good) before Gods. And becauſe they tooke occaſion by their gift, howſoeuer holy to contemne their domeſticke rites and lawes of piety, and that bond of naturall du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty which is more ancient tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any whatſoeuer. And yet there is ſomwhat more in it, then ſo: For the firſt commandement, that you ſtand ſo much vpon, and the fifth you ſo lightly regard, are both Gods commandements, they both iſſue from the ſame Author, and the ſame Law-maker. It is neceſſary therfore that either the one hinder the other, or that the latter be abrogated by the former (which is againſt all law that euer I could reade) or elſe that both of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be kept, as well the firſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining vnto God, as the fifth pertaining vnto parents. But the truth is, that ſome pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts are immutable, and they are (ſayeth <hi>Hildebert</hi> in his laſt Epiſtle) ſuch as the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall decree of God hath eſtabliſhed. Of which ſort (ſaith the Archbiſhop of <hi>Towres</hi>) are theſe, <hi>Thou ſhalt loue the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and all thy ſoule,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:19591:46"/>and thy neighbour as thy ſelfe. And honour thy Father and thy mother, and ſuch like:</hi> Other precepts are mutable, which the eternall Law of God hath not decreede, but the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and policy of ſome later wittes haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented for ſome conuenience and vſe, &amp; not ſo principally tending to ſaluation. And of this ſort it is to be a Ieſuite; Certaine I am, that the law, whereby thou ſtandeſt bounde vnto mee, is perpetuall, and vnchangeable. But what if here we be bolde to ſay, that God himſelfe is leſſe ſollicitous for his owne ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, than for our parents honor? And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of thoſe two commandements, the latter in a ſort is to be preferred before the former. And ſhall yet theſe Phariſies pleaſe thee more than Chriſt? It was not without a miſterie, that God gaue thoſe commandements con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his owne honour ſimply, without impoſition of puniſhment, if any brake them, or propoſall of rewarde if any kept them: but when he gaue this commandement con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning our duty towards our parents, he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded this clauſe, <hi>that thy dayes may be long vpon earth.</hi> For albeit hereby it bee clearely eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that nature cannot ſuffer, that he ſhould liue long vpon the earth, that reſpectes not theſe of whom he hath receiued life, nor en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure that it ſhould goe well with him any
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:19591:46"/>where, that will hide himſelfe for no other end, but that he may not ſhew himſelfe grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnto them that with ſo great care and trouble after they had giuen him life, haue nouriſhed and ſuſtained him; yet that which wee ſo principally intend, appeares from thence. For he ſayth that he is full of iealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, if a man worſhippe ſtrange and falſe gods; but if he worſhippe his parents, God is ſo farre from enuying it, that by all meanes poſſible, he wils and comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds it, &amp; that with ſuch a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, which of mankind is moſt deſired. Why preſſeth he all theſe things ſo earneſtly? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe when parents, theſe ſecond gods are ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured, whom hee ſo much acceptes, and ſo well accounteth of, whatſoeuer is done vnto them, he taketh it done vnto himſelfe: but if any duety bee left vndone vnto them, let vs worſhip him in the beſt manner wee can deuiſe, yet doth it not excuſe vs. And perhappes this may be the reaſon, that God (if I may ſo ſpeake) is not ſo hard to pleaſe in that honour and worſhip which wee owe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, as euery man is curious in the duetie, which is to bee done vnto him. God is reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renced as ſufficiently as he would be, if euerie one according to his ſexe, age, and quality do honour him as he is able. For it is not the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall dignity that makes a Chriſtian,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:19591:47"/>ſayth <hi>Ierome.</hi> One man in the Church is an eye, another the tongue, another the hand, and another the foote or the eare. In whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer vocation a man be, if therein hee ſerue God as he is able, hee pleaſeth God excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding well. For God exacteth not the ſame o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of all. But in man it is farre other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, except his ſonne be obedient and duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full at his beeke, and at his ſeruice, when hee ſhall thinke fitte, he is by no meanes conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Neither is it much materiall, of what condition both of them are, for whoſoeuer is a father, is a father in the ſame proportion, and whoſoeuer is a ſonne, is a ſonne in the ſame degree. Therefore that we may honour our parents without exception, and beyonde that voluntarie obedience, which wee ought to ſhew them, the Lord ſaith, this I will, this I commaund and for this duety I prolong thy yeares, that thou mayeſt performe it alwayes. What then? if Chriſt did iuſtly and deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uedly reprehend thoſe Iewiſh Prieſtes, doeſt thou thinke (eſpecially ſeeing both of vs pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe one Religion) that thou being my ſonne ſhouldeſt addict thy ſelfe to ſome certaine Colledge, Rule or Societie, (which ſay it bee lawfull and holy, yet is it but the inuention of men) and thereupon contemne and deſpiſe mee thy father (a ſinne which God and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:19591:47"/>hath forbidden thee?) Excepting that worſhippe, which wee owe vnto our God, (ſuch as is adoration and inuocation.) What is there in religion it ſelfe, more religious and more diuine, than to honour and reuerence our parents? Sacrifice is a holy worke, yet Chriſt (as you may ſee) leſſe eſteemeth it than the duety and obedience of children. It is a holy and religious work for a man to deuote himſelfe vnto the Church, Miniſtery and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of the brethren. Neuertheleſſe S: <hi>Paul</hi> commaunds in his firſt Epiſtle to <hi>Timothy</hi> 5. Chapter, and 4. verſe: <hi>If widdowes haue children or nephewes, let them learne firſt to ſhew godlineſſe to their owne houſe, and to recompence their parents, for that is honest and acceptable be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God.</hi> Certainely, if wee ought to chooſe any to that Miniſtery, hee or ſhee ought to be choſen, who are well reported of for their good works, and they are of this kinde, if <hi>ſhse hath nouriſhed her children, &amp;c.</hi> Would <hi>Paul</hi> haue preſcribed this ſo earneſtly, except hee himſelfe being the author had well percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued that there were ſome priuate and dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall duties, which of neceſſity were to bee preferred before all other though ſacred and publique? the truth is, that theſe latter pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from thoſe former. For when the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is of morall and naturall inſtitution,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:19591:48"/>Chriſtians differ in nothing from Pagans. He that liues contrary to Nature, keepes not Gods commandements, as <hi>Nilus</hi> ſaith in his inſtitution to certaine Monks. And as <hi>Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagoras</hi> in his Apologie for Chriſtians ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerues, that God mooues not man to thoſe things which are againſt Nature. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpake nothing, but that which <hi>Socrates</hi> had ſpoke before him in <hi>Zenophon,</hi> &amp; which the Athenia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s had long before thoght vpon and prouided for in their lawes. If any one be diſobedient to his parents (ſayth he in his 2. booke <hi>de fact. &amp; dict. Socrat.</hi>) let him be vncapable of all Magiſtracy. For how can he offer pure Sacrifice or ſit well at rhe ſterne of the common-wealth, if hee be a bad liuer at home, and if he be vnkind, vnnatural and iniurious to the people of his own houſe? As for the lawes of the Athenians, you ſhall finde them in <hi>Aeſchines</hi> againſt <hi>Timarchus,</hi> &amp; in <hi>Plutarch</hi> in the life of <hi>Aeſchines:</hi> but what ſaith Saint <hi>Paul?</hi> hee as if hee were in ſome emulation with <hi>Socrates</hi> ſayth; <hi>If there be any of you that prouideth not for his owne, namely for them of his owne houſhold, hee denieth the faith, and is worſe than an Infidell.</hi> Now ſee what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecture may be gathered of thee to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. Certainely (ſay they) he cannot chuſe but of neceſſitie bee moſt obedient to the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:19591:48"/>Prouinciall, Presbyters, who ſo reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely contemnes his Father, and ſo co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragiouſly renounceth him for a ſtranger and a Publican. See (my good ſonne) how far thou art diuerted from the way of the Lorde, &amp; how exceedingly thou art eſtranged from his commandements, although thou arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantly thinkeſt, that thou doeſt know and vnderſtand them better, than all thy fathers and thy forefathers did, yea better than Chriſt himſelfe. Without doubt a father and a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are not to be compared with God, yet are they to be beloued with God, ſaith <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> againſt the Gnoſtickes. And in his book <hi>of Chaſtitie</hi> he ſaith, <hi>you may know by the placing of euery commandement, the manner: by the order, the ſtate, and by the end the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward: therefore hee which honoureth not his father and mother, is worſe then an adulterer, worſe than a murtherer, and worſe than a theefe.</hi> But I had rather co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pare vertues with vertues, than vices vvith vices. vvhat is ſo good a work in the Church as to giue lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies to charitable vſes. And yet ſaith <hi>S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine, whoſoeuer will diſinherit his ſonne, and make the Church his heire, let him ſeeke one that will accept it, truly he ſhall not find that Auſtin will be his heire, and by Gods grace he ſhall find no man will be.</hi> And in his 119. Epiſtle vnto <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicias;</hi>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:19591:49"/>doth he not reprehend her, becauſe ſhe vowed continencie not acquainting her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band firſt with it? and when he had afterward conſented vnto her vowe, doth he not blame her becauſe ſhe tooke vpon her the habite of a Nunne, againſt his will? and did he not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue her becauſe ſhe gaue her goods to two poore Monkes, when ſhe had a ſonne liuing on whom ſhe might haue beſtowed them? which I ſpeake not (ſaith he) as though I thought that if any of vs ſhould be ill ſpoken of and ſcandalized for our good works, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we ſhould deſiſt from doing them, but becauſe in euerie ſocietie the reſpect we beare to our kindred ought to be one, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect we ſhew to ſtrangers, another, the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a chriſtian is one, and the condition of an infidel another, the duty of parents to their children one, and the dutie of children to their parents another. Write therefore vnto him a letter of ſatiſfaction and aske him par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don (ſaith he to <hi>Eridicea</hi>) becauſe thou haſt ſinned againſt him, and diſpoſed of thy goods after thy pleaſure, without his aduiſe, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to his will: not that it repenteth thee, that thou didſt beſtow thy goods on the poor but becauſe thou wert vnwilling that he ſhold haue any ſhare or part in ſo charitable a worke. Is not the fact memorable, which is
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:19591:49"/>recorded of <hi>Aurelius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Carthage,</hi> who reſtored a deed of gift he had receiued of a father that then had no children, vnto him againe, when afterwards hee had children? For it is not likelie nor to be preſumed in any caſe that he had rather haue another man to be his heire, than his owne ſonne; See here a far better iudgement of filiall duety, than that which thoſe vpſtart Phariſies put vpon thee, viz. <hi>That there is neither ſacrifice nor vow,</hi> nor any oblation that is to be preferred before the obedience which God commands vnto children. But let vs proceed and try by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples borrowed from him, that is both God and man, whether it be true <hi>that a man which is deſirous to take the miniſtery, or to lead a mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtricall life, may renounce all kind of obedience, and that it is to no purpoſe for him to aſke his fathers conſent and iudgement in taking thoſe orders vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him or no?</hi> I pray thee whom did Chriſt call to be his Apoſtles? called he ſuch a one as thou art a yong boy? and tell me if they left their ſhips, their nets, and all their tackling to follow Chriſt, did they for all that leaue their parents? or if they left them did they leaue them without leaue? yea, which is more, did they that were husbands put away their wiues, or did they which were fathers, for that cauſe forſake their children? Certaine it is that
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:19591:50"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:19591:50"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:19591:51"/>
               <hi>Iames</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> were aboue 25. yeers old, when they departed from their father. But did they further to ſhew their more impudencie in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting, leaue Iudea and trauaile into <hi>Italie, Lorraine,</hi> or <hi>Spaine?</hi> or elſe becauſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues were Chriſtians, could they not endure to looke vpon their fathers? or was his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, ſpeech, or conuerſation, irkſome vnto them? Had they done ſo, they ſhould haue done otherwiſe than their Lord and Maſter had done before, who (as I ſaid) neuer went from <hi>Mary</hi> and <hi>Ioſeph.</hi> But that I may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate vnto thee, that they went not out of their country, or fathers houſes, vntill ſuch time as after Chriſts paſſion, they were to goe into the whole world, and that albeit after their calling, they accompanied Chriſt, yet neuertheles they were conuerſant at home, &amp; dwelt with their parents; It is written that Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus came to the houſe of <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Andrew,</hi> where when he ſaw their mother in law ſicke of an ague, hee cured her, and forthwith ſhe miniſtred to him and to his diſciples. Therfore to follow Chriſt was not to forſake ones friends, his parents, his wife, his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, or his houſehold, yea (which is more) <hi>Iames</hi> and <hi>Iohn,</hi> albeit they were growen in yeeres, would not haue followed Chriſt, if <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedeus</hi> their father had not conſented there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:19591:51"/>For ſeeing they were together, with their father, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Chriſt</hi> bad them follow him, it cannot be but that either <hi>Zebedeus</hi> did ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe his conſent in words, or imply it by holding his peace. But tell mee whether thou thinkeſt all vocations be of one kind, as well they that proceede expreſlie from Gods immediate will, as they whereunto the Church calleth vs? God knoweth directlie and changeth the hearts of men, therefore he is not deceiued. But men in their elections doe onlie coniecture and gheſſe, wherefore they oftentimes exceedinglie erre? for to be a man and ſubiect to error be termes conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible: as to be God and not to be ſubiect to error. what then? why we had need vſe all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence and be verie warie, in theſe vocations ſo that no ſolemnitie be paſſed ouer eſpecially the conſent &amp; good leaue of our parents. If I ſhould alleadge that place vnto thee, where Chriſt ſaid vnto his Apoſtles. <hi>Suffer little ones to come vnto me,</hi> thou wouldſt ſay, that there he ſpeaketh of ſuch as are yong in age. And in very deed you ſhall find in the Goſpell <hi>that theſe little ones were brought vnto Chriſt, and that they came not of their owne accord vnto him,</hi> therefore he ſaid not, <hi>Come vnto me, but ſuffer them to come,</hi> and againe <hi>forbid them not,</hi> to teach that the <hi>calling of little ones,</hi> as well as
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:19591:52"/>their Baptiſme did depend both, vpon their fathers tutors and curators ſuit and promiſe made for them. But whereas it was ſaid ouer and aboue, <hi>forbid them not,</hi> that was not ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to their parents but to the diſciples, that found fault with ſuch as brought them vnto Chriſt: and this without doubt is ſpoken of ſuch as are in their minoritie. But that which was before alleadged, makes no diſtinction at all of anie age. It is written to all in generall tearmes, <hi>Honour your parents,</hi> I know when the ſonne is once come to fiue and twenty, that then his fathers approbation, yea his diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation, and which is more, his very ſilence, (ſuch as was that of <hi>Zebedeus</hi>) goeth for his conſent. But yet that, ſuch as it is, is verie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite. Neither canſt thou depart from thy father or mother if they be vnwilling. What ſaid I? from thy parents? I ſay thou canſt not goe from thy brethren or thy kindred (for S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeakes generallie of the whole fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie) but thou muſt perforce ſinne againſt God and be guiltie of a cruell and faithleſſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. But I ſuppoſe there is a text alleadged thee to the contrarie, that when one of Chriſts diſciples deſired him, that he would permit him to goe and burie his father, before that he followed him, Ieſus replied vnto him, <hi>Follow me and ſuffer the dead to burie their dead,</hi>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:19591:52"/>whereupon they diſpute thus: Buriall is a very religious and holie dutie, eſpeciallie if it be done to a mans father. But Chriſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe willeth vs rather to attend him, than the buriall of our parents. Againe, lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men are accounted as dead men, for they which are ſo hampered and entangled in the pleaſures of this world, that they cannot ſwim out of them, may iuſtly be eſteemed for drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and dead men. Hence ſaith S. <hi>Paul, The widdow that liueth in pleaſure, is dead while ſhe liueth.</hi> 1. Timoth. 5.6. The cleargie men on the contrarie may properlie be ſaid to liue: For they are the part and portion of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God, therefore well may he be ſaid to abſtaine from the dead, who hath left his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and his mother to follow Chriſt (that is as they make it) to be a Ieſuit. Verie acutelie collected, Sir, but we haue our anſwer in a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe for you. Firſt it followeth not, that whatſoeuer was pronounced of Chriſt muſt forthwith neceſſarilie be applied to the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, and all ſuch at haue betaken themſelues to a regular courſe of life. Indeed all his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine was deliuered ouer vnto them, but not all power, ſaith <hi>Tertullian,</hi> in his book of <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitie.</hi> And verilie it is one thing, to embrace Chriſt and another thing to follow, ſo manie orders of monks as be now adaies; yea though
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:19591:53"/>there were ſmall ods between them and thoſe of whom <hi>Dorotheus</hi> ſpake of old. Secondlie, when the father of that diſciple was once dead, that exact reuerence which perhaps he pretended to Chriſt, ceaſed, and was no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to be performed. For it was certaine that he was then no longer a ſonne. Laſtlie, the Lord commanded not that the burial ſhould be whollie omitted, but that it ſhould be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured to be done by ſome other, and who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſouer that was, he was ſaid to celebrate his fathers funerall, in regard that we commonly call all thoſe, which are departed out of this life before vs, <hi>our fathers or forefathers.</hi> The charge and coſt of funeralls is a publique buſineſſe, ſaith <hi>Papinian</hi> the ſanctuarie of the law, whence alſo <hi>Iuſtinian</hi> in his 43. and 59. <hi>Nouell</hi> manifeſtlie ſheweth, that in <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople</hi> the charge and expences of funeralls was wont to be defraied out of the publique treaſurie. Why therefore ſhould this celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hinder the diſciple fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> following Chriſt, ſince that it might be done as well by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as by himſelfe. But yet ther is great diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence whether children deſtitute their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents in malice or pure ſimplicity. This ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition will ſerue thee againſt all theſe ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments wherewith they haue beguiled thee. If thy parents be dead, that is if they be Iewes.
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:19591:53"/>if Idolaters, if Pagans, if Infidels, &amp; if the ſon contrariwiſe be a chriſtian, if a Catholique, and the father would burie this his ſonne with him, that is, command him to commit ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie, <hi>leaue this father and follow mee</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>let the dead burie this dead.</hi> That theſe words ought ſo to be taken, and vnderſtood, is cleare bothout of <hi>S. Ambroſe,</hi> when he ſaith, <hi>The ſonne is not diſſwaded from his duty towards his fathers, but a beleeuer is ſeuered from the fellowſhip of an vnbeleeuer.</hi> And alſo out of <hi>S. Auſtin</hi> as well in that one booke of <hi>obſeruations on S. Mathew,</hi> as in his firſt booke to <hi>Marcellian concerning the Baptiſme of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</hi> Canſt thou therefore perſwade any man that the Ieſuits onlie liue the beſt kind of life, and that we miſerable chriſtians, becauſe we are of the laitie muſt be reputed for dead and buried. S. <hi>Hierome</hi> writing vnto <hi>Furia</hi> think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth far otherwiſe: whoſoeuer beleeueth in Chriſt (ſaith hee) liueth. And <hi>Tertullian</hi> in his booke, <hi>de carne Christi,</hi> doth not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ranke <hi>Marcion</hi> among thoſe that were dead, becauſe he was not a Monke or an Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, but becauſe whilſt he was an heretique, he was not truly and properly a good chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an. But we fathers, poore men though we be, euen we are beleeuers we are called the ſonnes of God, his friends, his brethren, and coheires
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:19591:54"/>with him, and wee alſo are made partakers through him of the holy Ghoſt. As many as haue a true faith, and lead an vpright life, yea although they worke not miracles, nor caſt out diuells, yet they are holie, ſaith <hi>S. Hierome</hi> in his 59. <hi>Homilie.</hi> But if you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the ſame, yea, if thou boaſt of greater things than theſe, why this alſo is our benefit, this alſo is our aduantage. For if you aske any of vs Chriſtians of what religion we are, euerie of vs being taught by you, can make you this anſwer: of the ſame religion, whereof our fathers and anceſtors were. There was no oath more inuiolable, than that which wee ſware by our <hi>fathers faith,</hi> ſaith <hi>Philo,</hi> who bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed this ſentence of an ancient Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher: therefore why thou ſhouldſt ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credinglie deſpiſe vs, now there is no reaſon: or if thou wilt needs contemne vs, doe it then, when we can expect nothing from thy hands but our buriall. You ſhall haue in this caſe if not the meaning, yet the words of Chriſt to his Diſciples, when our Sauiour Chriſt ſaid vnto him follow me, he well knevv that his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was novv dead, ſaith the ſame <hi>S. Ambroſe</hi> in this verie place. But I beleeue the text in <hi>S. Matthewes</hi> Goſpell hath moſt ſeduced thee. <hi>He that loueth father or mother more than mee, is not worthy of me:</hi> And againe in <hi>S. Luke,</hi> if
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:19591:54"/>
               <hi>any man commeth vnto me and hateth not his father and his mother, his wife and his children, his brethren and his ſiſters, yea and his owne ſoule, he cannot be my diſciple.</hi> Theſe and ſuch like places ſeem to yeeld thee great and forceable arguments for thy defence: but ſince thoſe reaſons and authorities, which we haue alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy brought to the contrarie, be as pregnant and forceable to all intents, it had been your courſe to infer, that ſurelie theſe latter places do require ſome farther expoſition and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, leaſt God ſhould ſeem to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, or to contradict himſelfe. For, I pray you, tell me, what manner of doctrine is this, or what kind of religion may this be called, which teacheth, that a man <hi>of neceſſity muſt hate his father, and his mother, his wife, and his children, his brethren and his ſiſters, yea his owne deare ſoule alſo that will be Chriſts diſciple,</hi> if we ſhould ſticke vnto the words and not ſtand vnto the meaning? for if he that ſhould hate his father, muſt therefore be a good diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, doubtleſſe he that ſhould well beate him, were worthy to be a patriarch, and hee that ſhould kill him, might exceedinglie well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue to be a Pope. See how many abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and miſchiefes, would ariſe from theſe words, not ill conceiued, but il vnderſtood. So <hi>S. Chryſoſtome</hi> in his 36. homily, vpon S. <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thews</hi>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:19591:55"/>Goſpell, he did not abſolutelie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand thee, to make inuectiue ſpeeches, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thy familiar friends and acquaintance, for that were an action ſauouring of indiſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and might procure harme. But look how much any other deſires to haue thee loue him more than me, hate him, ſaith he, ſo much the more. I confeſſe then that we ought rather to loue God than our parents: and that is the leſſon which <hi>Salomon</hi> teacheth vs, <hi>begin your loue with me,</hi> as <hi>Origen</hi> witneſſeth. Which is alſo ſpoken by S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> on S. <hi>Luke,</hi> if men ought to performe dutie to their parents, how much more then ought they to render their moſt bounden dutie, to the creator and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of their parents, in yeelding him alwaies thanks, that gaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> parents. But I am much miſtaken if the conſequence hold, <hi>ergo,</hi> it is more bleſſed, to become a <hi>Franciſcan</hi> Frier, or a Ieſuit, than either to loue or reuerence thy father. For chriſtian religion is grounded eſpeciallie vpon faith, but doth not depend, vpon this or that particular order of religion. Nay I may further tell you may a generall Councell haue been ſummoned, that neuer confirmed or approued theſe orders. And if (put caſe) it be a degree of more perfection to be a Cleargie man than a lay man, I thinke it muſt not be inferred, <hi>ergo,</hi> a ſonne need not
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:19591:55"/>refraine anie ſtubborne vndutifull or vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly behauiour to his parents, if he intend to be a Prieſt rather than a lay man. God hath no where (that I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> find) laid any ſuch preciſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, on either of vs both to be Prieſts, his eſpeciall charge to thee wards, is that thou ſhouldſt doe me honor, by all meanes. Haſt thou then wilfullie done me this open wrong? thy ſinne is of ſo hainous a nature, that Gods curſe &amp; mans is vpon thee for it. For I tel thee ſonne it is a matter of meer indifferency to be one of the Ieſuits companie. A man may be a good chriſtian, and walke in the way of Chriſt, which is the path to euerlaſting life, and yet neuer turne Ieſuit for the matter. And therefore it ill became thee to put by an act of abſolute neceſſitie, for a proiect of thine owne priuate fancie, &amp; voluntarie concept, as <hi>S. Thomas</hi> verie wiſelie informeth thee. I pray thee tell me, if there were two waies to follow Chriſt in, and the one were ſo faire and plaine, that thou mightſt loue me, and thy ſauiour Chriſt alſo, the other ſo ſtonie and craggie that vnleſſe thou didſt perfectly hate me, it were impoſſible for thee to loue him, which of theſe waies wouldſt thou rather chuſe? but (O ſonne) S. <hi>Matthew</hi> and S. <hi>Luke</hi> are ſo cleer in this point, that there is not ſo much as the leaſt letter which may caſt thee into any
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:19591:56"/>ſuch labyrinth, or intricate maze. Read theſe Euangeliſts and read them from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the end, thou ſhalt find it deliuered, that if queſtion be of vndergoing martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome for Chriſt (which they call <hi>to carrie the croſſe and follow him</hi>) and theſe two ſhould be in tearmes of oppoſition, <hi>To denie God before men, or to honor and loue ones father,</hi> it is farre better to hate father, yea to hate himſelfe and his owne foule, than once to diſtruſt the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of his ſweet Sauior Chriſt. So then if I ſhould haue perſwaded thee to abiure the Chriſtian baptiſme, wherunto I firſt brought thee, and might well enough haue beene thy Biſhop in it, had I aduiſed thee to caſt away that moſt pretious pearle, which <hi>S. Iohn</hi> the Apoſtle gaue him that told him where hee might find the woluiſh God, that had yeere by yeere had 12. young children offered vp vnto him for ſacrifice, had I requeſted thee to renege Chriſtianitie, to entertaine Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metiſme, Atheiſme, or hereſie (I may not haue thee tell me now with <hi>Saluianus,</hi> that ſuch a time may happen, wherein ſome thing that is not God ought to be preferred before God) then mightſt thou by vertue of this ſcripture, in theſe caſes haue lawfully refuſed to do me ſuch duty, and reuerence, as apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth to a father: and <hi>Saturus,</hi> or the worthy
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:19591:56"/>Lady <hi>Victoria,</hi> would haue been good pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedents for thy imitation (of whom <hi>Victor</hi> the Biſhop reporteth in his firſt booke <hi>De perſecutione Vandalica,</hi> that they had rather be held from their children, parted from their husbands, depriued of all their world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wealth, than by any ſeducements whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, become Arrians. In ſuch a caſe it would haue been good for thee, to haue been with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out father or mother like <hi>Melchiſedech,</hi> who was therefore ſaid to be without both, becauſe he was a deuout holy man, though his parents were wicked, and cruell <hi>Canaanites.</hi> Heathen people loue their natiue country exceedingly, and none can haue any part in their loue but their parents. Now we (ſaith <hi>Pontius, S. Cyprians</hi> Deacon) we deteſt and abhor our very pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, when once they goe about to perſwade vs for anie thing againſt our God. But ſith we are both good chriſtians and Catholiks, who ſhould preuaile more with thee than my ſelfe, that haue done more for thee than all the world beſides? if any father might be iuſtlie deſpiſed of his childe, abuſed and wronged by him, choaked with that text in <hi>Leuiticus (I am ignorant, I know you not)</hi> certainlie it were ſuch a father, as ſhold dedicate his childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſtrange Gods, or aduow them to the worſhip of the molten Calfe, according to that of
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:19591:57"/>
               <hi>Moſes,</hi> (let thy hand be vpon them and powr foorth their blood which would ſeduce thee from the truth) in which place notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, maybe obſerued as alſo out of the 32. of <hi>Exodus;</hi> that although <hi>Moſes</hi> in this caſe, allowes of parricide, yet he exemplifieth it in the wife, in the ſonne, in the brother, in the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, in the kinſman and friend, he makes no mention at all of the father. So ſacred, vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and inuiolable is that name of a father, nothing may lawfullie be attempted againſt a father. Read the Epiſtle of <hi>Moſes, Maximus, Nicoſtratus, Rufinus,</hi> and other Confeſſors (it is the 77) to <hi>Cyprian,</hi> thou ſhalt find theſe words vnderſtood in this ſence; peruſe like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe <hi>Chriſoſtome</hi> in his 65. homilie vpon <hi>S. Matthew,</hi> where he expounds them. Theſe words (ſaith he) to my vnderſtanding, cloſelie do betoken perſecutions. For many ſonnes haue been drawn to wicked courſes by their parents, manie husbands by their wiues, which whenſoeuer they attempt, let them neither be reſpected for wiues, nor parents. And the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor which wrote on the ſame Euangeliſt in his 27 homilie. It is not to be beleeued (ſaith he) that God which commanded thee to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor thy father and mother, would bid thee forſake father and mother: if therefore thou haſt an vnbeleeuing father, continue thy
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:19591:57"/>obedience to him for in ſo doing, thou ſhalt receiue the reward of thy dutie, and contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe he ſhall find the condemnation of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelitie. And therefore our Sauior ſaid not he that loueth his father is not worthy of me, but he that loueth his father or mother, more than me, is not worthy of me. For as to loue our parents after God it is dutie, ſo to honor them more than God, is plaine impietie. If therefore (he repeats it againe) thou haſt an vnbelieuing father, ſtill obey him, but if hee would haue thee ſwallowed into the gulfe of infidelitie, loue God more than thy father, for he is the father not of the ſoule, but of thy bodie onlie. Howſoeuer yet, he doth not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire that the ſonne vpon any ſuch occaſion, ſhould deſert him by his bodily preſence, but by diſſenting from him in point of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. Marke how theſe words of the olde law, <hi>theſe men, ſaith the Lord, haue kept my commaundementes, which haue ſaide vnto fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and mother we know you not</hi>) are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded by <hi>Philoſtratus</hi> ſometimes Biſhop of <hi>Brixia,</hi> and S. <hi>Auſtins</hi> ancient in his booke of hereſies. You are not to vnderſtand hereby, to condemne your father, for begetting you, but to condemne the groſſe impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etie of your father that would miſlead you. And this was the opinion of <hi>Salonius</hi> Biſhop
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:19591:58"/>of <hi>Vienna,</hi> writing vpon <hi>Eccleſiaſtes.</hi> For the profeſſion of our faith in Chriſt, wee muſt contemne, yea and hate, father and mother, and all our kindred, when they be anie ſtops or impediments vnto vs, in the way of the Lord: as vve read that the holy Martyrs, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie times did: whence it is that S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> in his ſermons, ſaith, theſe words, ſeeme to encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage men to martyrdome. Finallie, Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus himſelfe being readie to giue vp the ghoſt (to ſpeake in the words of <hi>Arnold</hi> the Abbot) that he might ſuperlatiuelie commend this noble and great article of the ſecond table, <hi>Honour thy father and thy mother,</hi> and that by al the bonds and leagues of pietie, doth giue &amp; bequeath it to his mother the bleſſed virgin, <hi>(woman behold thy ſonne)</hi> and to his beſt belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued diſciple <hi>S. Iohn, (behold thy mother).</hi> And that S. <hi>Iohn</hi> was likewiſe of his maſters mind, <hi>Prochirus</hi> relateth Chap. 21. for hauing bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized <hi>Chryſippa</hi> in the Iland <hi>Pathmos,</hi> and ſhe would thereupon in all ſpeed leaue hir vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing husband, <hi>S. Iohn</hi> told her, no, that is by no meanes to be permitted, for God hath not ſent me to ſeparate man &amp; wife, I haue no ſuch commiſſion, &amp; therfore returne in peace to your owne houſe. For if it were lawfull, that a woman might ſeparate her ſelfe from her husband, yet were it not expedient (ſaith
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:19591:58"/>
               <hi>Auſten</hi> in his book <hi>De Adulterinis coniugijs</hi>) to <hi>Pollentius.</hi> Now if it ſhould be ſaid, that in theſe daies there be no martyrdomes, and therfore the former expoſition wil not now hold: then Gregorie the great in his 37. homily <hi>De Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſis Euangelij lectionibus,</hi> will giue this inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation, that the place is to bemeant of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence, and carnall affections. For then ſaith he, we truelie hate our owne ſoule, when wee repoſe not our ſelues on carnall deſires, when we ſubdue our inordinate appetite, and ſtriue againſt our delicious pleaſures. Yea but the Ieſuites buzze into thy eares, that twere better for thee to ſpurne and trample thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnder thy feet than to be without a cowle. Well, then I would faine know for my better learning, whether <hi>S. Iohn Chryſostom</hi> attained to the true ſence of theſe words, of S. <hi>Mathew</hi> and S. <hi>Luke,</hi> (now wee are come to be tride by God &amp; the Church) vvhen in his firſt book <hi>de Sacerdotio,</hi> he reports of himſelfe (and ſo doth <hi>Leo</hi> the Emperour report of him in a certaine Panegyricke oration) that hauing finiſhed the courſe of his ſtudies in the Vniuerſity of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens hee returned to Antioch, and there through the often admonitions of one <hi>Baſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> (for it was not <hi>Baſil</hi> the great, if wee may take <hi>Simeon Metaphraſtes</hi> his worde.) had a great longing to haue beene a monke, vvho
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:19591:59"/>hindred him from his courſe of deuotion, for hee vvas pittifullie perplexed a long vvhile? It was no conceit of nonage, hee vvas then 25. yeares olde, and was a pleader in the Court: tvvas no reſpect of reuerence to his father (for hee was departed out of the vvorlde:) twas not that his reſolution was ſomwhat ſtag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gered by the remembrance of his olde friends and fellows, for he more regarded <hi>Baſile</hi> then them all? how then, where was the impedime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t? it was obſeruance to his poore mother: for when ſhe ſet vpon me with this ſpeach, O ſon I was a freſh young beautifull widdow, when I refuſed the profers of a ſecond mariage, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to enable my ſelfe to doe thee the more good, and then (alas poor childe) when thou waſt a ſmall infant, all my care was, that thou mighteſt haue plentifull meanes for thy edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and preferment; And now in liew of all theſe my kindneſſes, in ſtead of al thoſe tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ks and comforts which ſo many benefits might challenge from thee, canſt thou finde in thy heart to forſake me now? to contemn and diſdaine me now? make mee twice a widdow? and waken my time of mourning which vvas novv laide aſleepe? why tell me (good ſonne) didſt thou euer lacke any thing that I could helpe thee to? did I euer vvrong thee in al my life? If thou wilt needes enter into a monaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:19591:59"/>vvhy firſt ſee me honeſtlie buried in my graue? Hearke: doſt thou not hear the voice of the Lord crying aloud [ſonne honour thy mother <hi>Authuſam.</hi>] Surely he performes faire obedience to Gods commandements, that by ſuch demeanour grieues his mother: O ſonne hadſt thou done for mee all that poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly a ſonne can doe for his mother, yet haſt thou payd me nothing for my manifold ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, for my throbs in childbed, which for thy deere ſake I ſo patiently endured, for my paines in bearing thee, for the ſuſtenance which I gaue thee, when I ſtroaked my breſts into thy lippes, with the true affection of a moſt naturall mother! What haue I for my hunger and faſting which I ſuſtained for thee, when I refrained to eat any thing that might hurt thee, and drinke anie thing that might marre my milke. If I kept faſt, it was for thee, if I did eate, it was for thee, If I refuſed any meat, it was for thee, if I accepted of any meat it was for thee, and many a night I haue wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched for thee, and manie a bitter teare haue I ſhed for thee, and doeſt thou now vtterlie for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake me? I could hould out no longer (ſaith he) but forthvvith yeelded, as being ſtrongly ouercome with a reuerent reſpect to ſo good a mother. And thereupon he makes his excuſe to <hi>Baſilius,</hi> and in deſpite of al theſe arguments
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:19591:60"/>(which haue bene forceably bent and diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged againſt thee) choſe rather to continue with his mother, than to abide in a monaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. He himſelfe writing afterwards to <hi>Baſilius,</hi> vſeth theſe words: I confeſſe I haue broken my promiſe, for vvhen I left Athens, &amp; ſuch familiar acquaintance as I had in that vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, my purpoſe vvas to haue addicted my ſelfe vvholly to your companie, and vvith you to haue ſpent my daies in contemplation. But I haue broken my worde and that not vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on anie wilfull diſpoſition (I would haue you ſo to vnderſtand mee) but, for that one law hath more preuailed with me than another, I meane that law which requires dutifull obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence vnto parents, more than the ſociable Law of friendſhip and good fellowſhip. Now parallell thy ſelfe with S. <hi>Chryſoſtome.</hi> When thou waſt yet in thy nonage, all thy contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing was, how to be a Ieſuite; fatherles, I am ſure thou waſt not, except thou wilt ſay thou wert fatherleſſe in this ſence, that thou hadſt a Father, but ſuch a one as thou didſt not care for: nor motherleſſe, for, that thou hadſt a moſt kinde and louing gentlewoman to thy mother. How was it then? that neither thy fathers authoritie, nor thy mothers tender loue and affection might ought preuaile with thee in not attempting anie thing
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:19591:60"/>without their approbation and aduice. Thou haſt ſhunned their preſence, wandred vp and downe the worlde like a vagabond, and for three whole yeeres together concealed thy ſelfe, after ſuch a manner of inſolent indigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and arrogancie, that in all that long time, thou haſt neither vouchſafed to write me one letter, nor ſend me ſo much as one word how I might know to find thee out, either in France, Lorryne, or Spaine. Perhaps, you ſtood in ſome feare that your Mother <hi>Hortenſia</hi> ſhould affront you with ſuch an encounter as this. Why ſon, if God ſhould haue called away thy Father (which I hope neuer to ſee) what ſtay ſhould I haue found in the worlde after him? Thy brethren, alas poore ſoules they be too young. And what hope could I haue had from them, that haue thee for a patterne of diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience? No doubt God is much bound vnto you for your good ſeruice done vnto him, that in a iealous compariſon thereof, cannot endure any commerce or correſpondency with your parents? no not ſo much as for the returne of a few letters? If this you haue done vpon ſome nice conceit, that they reſpect you too too neere, becauſe you are of their bloud, and alliance, yet remember withall they bee good Chriſtian folke, not pagans, and that this tender affection of theirs proceeds rather
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:19591:61"/>from a feare of thy well doing, than from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny doubt which they can poſſibly make of the articles of their Chriſtian faith and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. It was not without good cauſe (I perceiue now) that good <hi>Veturia</hi> refuſed vtterly to be employed in embaſſage to <hi>Martius Cariola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> hir ſonne. For what ſaith ſhe, ſhall I get at his hands? what ſhall all my little nephewes get, when he that hath liued in baniſhment for 4. yeares together, in all that while neuer ſent me ſo much as one letter? hath quite forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten his kindred, as well as his natiue coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, which (might I ſpeake like a mother) moſt vncurteouſly and vndeſeruedly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned him. Shee notwithanding all this, embarkt her ſelfe in the meſſage, and forced him to come in, by no other ſtratagem of war than the name of a mother. What thinkeſt thou? art thou more religious than S. <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome,</hi> more hard harted than was <hi>Coriolanus?</hi> yet he came to meete his mother halfe way, thou flieſt from thine, and eſcheweſt her very preſence. What? feareſt thou to write vnto me? in Gods name write, write without date of day or year. Indeed if S. <hi>Baſil</hi> be your coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance for this irreligious deuotion, the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation were the leſſe, and the fault more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſable on you part, I muſt needs grant.</p>
            <p>But (I feare me) that we haue little aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taged
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:19591:61"/>our cauſe all this while by quoting of ſo many ancient Fathers, except it be, the filling vp of a long empty catalogue with names. Our beſt way therefore in my iudgement to deale with thee, will be with ſome records and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedents of antiquity. And whereas S. <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome</hi> hath written ſome bookes, againſt ſuch as diſcommend the monaſticall life, &amp; hath giuen counſell to parents to take ſome care that their children bee trained vp in ſuch ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, rather then to make them ſwordmen or of the long robe, his intent is therby in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring that kinde of life before any other, to aduize men rather to beſtow their children in a courſe of religion, than a ſecular employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; but not to make them in any ſort diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient to their friends, and in deſpite of them to abandon cities, and inhabite vaſt moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainous deſerts, nay hee wills them after ſome time ſpent, after they haue bene well ſeaſoned in Chriſtianity, to repayre home againe to their parents. Which makes mee to thinke that the Monkes of that world, were not ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers for life in their monaſtery, as now they vſe to be, but at curteſie to return home when they liſt. Againe reade the ſame S. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> in his bookes <hi>de prouidentia,</hi> there you ſhall obſerue how hee ſpends himſelfe in comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Stagyrius</hi> the Monke, who was therefore
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:19591:62"/>vexed with a deuill, becauſe that contrary to the aduice of his Father, he had caſt himſelfe into a cloyſter, and whom for that cauſe, he terms an <hi>intruding Frier.</hi> But <hi>Stagyrius</hi> was the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ripe yeares and his father had not expreſly forbid him that calling, onely hee counſelled him otherwiſe. S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> himſelfe and S. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi> in his firſt booke, <hi>De Virginibus,</hi> towards the end, proues that parents ſhould not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a daughter from conſecrating her ſelfe to theſeruice of the Church, but yet withall ſo, that a Father may (if his pleaſure bee) pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptorily to forbid it. And doth not Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> in his 109 and 110. epiſtle to <hi>Ecdicia</hi> plainely ſay, that ſhee had made a deede of gift of her ſonne in her life time, whereby to kill him, in that his father was not firſt made acquainted therewith, what courſe of life vpon more maturitie and diſcretion hee after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards might follow, to bee either a Monke a Prieſt, or a married man: therefore till hee came to ſuch an age, his fathers voice and conſent was abſolutelie neceſſarie thereunto: but the concluſion of all is, that the ſon borne in lawfull and holie Wedlocke is more to be in ſubiection to the Father than to the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And therefore he cannot be denied him whereſoeuer he be, when once hee is lawfullie demanded. The ſame Father in his 233. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:19591:62"/>to <hi>Benenatus,</hi> doth not he write of a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine girle, that as the report went, would faine haue beene a Nunne, how hee conſulted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the matter with <hi>Felix</hi> her Aunts Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, and that otherwiſe he neither could nor would haue giuen way vnto it. What would his opinion haue beene (thinke you) of hir mother, whoſe direction and vvill in beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of hir daughter, was euer to bee preferred before all others? Without doubt if the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers intereſt be ſo much, the fathers is a great deale more, and ſo great as he would not haue much demurred, vvhether the ſonne were vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der yeares or aboue, for ſuch a queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on would neuer haue beene propoſed. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I appeale to thy conſcience (good Father <hi>Saluianus</hi>) waſt thou a ſtranger to this newe Church diſcipline, when thou tookeſt ſuch extraordinary paines to <hi>Hepatius</hi> and <hi>Quie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta,</hi> that they would pleaſe to excuſe that acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their daughter <hi>Palladia,</hi> for that ſhee was conuerted from Paganiſme to Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye, without their priuity? do I ſay her action? nay to excuſe thine owne, that after the birth of thy daughter <hi>Auſpiciola,</hi> refrainedſt the companie of thine owne wife, the better to giue thy ſelfe to faſting and praier, hauing no warrant ſo to doe from thy father in laws per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion. When they betrothed <hi>Palladia</hi> to
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:19591:63"/>thee, they gaue her to a Chriſtian husband, and thereby ſufficiently expreſt their conſent that ſhe likewiſe for hir behalf ſhould become a Chriſtian. Yea and certaine it is, that a little after this bleſſed match, thy wiues parents that ſo dearely affected their daughter, became Chriſtians alſo. Howſoeuer then they might haue taken it ill at thy hands, that vndertoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt this without their ſpeciall leaue, (for what hope could they conceiue of any grand-child to be borne vnder that marriage, where the man and wife liued a part?) what reproache was it vnto them, that in a matter of ſuch weighty importance they ſhould not be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie ſo much as to be lookt after? If they for ſuch an inſignious contempt done vnto them ſhould haue ſaid vnto thee, Sirra, packe out of our ſight, and write letters vpon letters as long as thou liſt, and it bee ſeauen yeares together thou ſhalt receiue not one line from vs in way of anſwer, (and yet I muſt haue tolde you that <hi>Palladia</hi> now after the enter-marriage, belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged not to hir Father but to hir husbands diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition) couldſt thou in defence of thy ſelfe haue ſaid, that it was a point of feruent zeale to Godwards, firſt to hate and ſet at naught thy Father? Oh, but reade his epiſtles, and reade them ouer, thou wilt tell me another tale: there is nothing but bitter teares, pitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:19591:63"/>ſuites: and begging pardons, although ſaith he, for my part, I do not well know how, or wherin I haue offended them. Now vppon theſe premiſes, ſee how I could conclude a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee: I haue writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> many letters to thee, but neuer receiued any one for anſwere backe again. Thou art not yet come to yeers of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, thou haſt entred into a vow, (I wil not ſay of chaſtitie but of ſingle life,) and neuer told me of it. Poore ſoule, how couldeſt thou make any vow at that yeares? thou canſt not defend thy ſelfe and ſay, why but Father, I had your conſent, though you did not openly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe it. For thou knoweſt vvell enough that I did mainely withſtand it: in a worde whereas thou haſt reuolted to the Ieſuites companie, tis not paganiſme that thou haſt forſaken: but the holy fellowſhip and Communion of thy Chriſtian brethren. Why then doſt thou not vpon thy bare knees aske me forgiuenes, thou haſt more reaſon ſo to doe, ſonne, than euer <hi>Saluianus</hi> had: for hee in humility acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged his offence, but thou canſt not be brought to confeſſe thine. Now I pray thee, ſonne, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>think thy ſelfe how greeuouſly this holy man would haue bene affrighted with the remorſe of his diſobedience, if hee had offered ſuch wrong, I will not ſay to Idolatrous parents, ſuch as they vvere, but to beleeuing, whereas
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:19591:64"/>he takes on ſo much, for being the occaſion of their heauineſſe, which were yet infidells, and not his parents by birth, but by affinitie only, and thought himſelfe no good Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, for not honoring them, as Gods co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement would haue enioined to honour his naturall parents, that is, without diſtinction of being good or bad, Iew or Gentile, faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full or vnbeleeuer.</p>
            <p>Doubtleſſe hee tooke this leſſon out of <hi>Ariſtaeus,</hi> where King <hi>Ptolomie</hi> asking one of the 72. interpreters, how he might be kind and thankfull to his parents, receiued this anſwere, that the next way was, neuer to grieue or moleſt them. Or elſe he had read the deſcription of the laſt iudgement in the Poet where they are ranked among the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ghoſts by <hi>Sibyila,</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>That do forſake their aged Sires, and care not to reward</l>
                  <l>Their parents which did foſter them, or ſpitefullie refuſe</l>
                  <l>To doe them ſeruice at their need, or them with ſoornes abuſe.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Certain it is, that Biſhop <hi>Fauſtus</hi> in his firſt booke <hi>De libero arbitrio,</hi> and the twelfth chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, interpreting thoſe words in the Goſpell, <hi>Let vs nowfeaſt and bee merry, for this my ſonne was dead and is aliue, loſt and now is found,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds the loſſe to be his departure from his father: he was not loſt in perſon (ſaith he) but
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:19591:64"/>he that forſooke his father, and by ſuch his contempt was no better than a dead man, by a dutifull deſire that he had to come home <hi>to his father,</hi> was againe reuiued, and reſtored to life. For as it was a ſinne in him, to trauaile in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a far countrie, out of his kind fathers pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, ſo was it a point of his good nature and dutie, reſolutelie to change his courſe, and to returne with teares to his fathers mercifull embracements.</p>
            <p>And now I take it to be high time, to ceaſe to inſtance any farther by example, and dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctly paſſe ouer to the decrees and Canons of the Church, leaſt happilie it be replied, that all which is hitherto alleadged, is but for par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular ends, and not ſufficient to proue the generall aſſertion. For albeit, I muſt ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſlie confeſſe, an Idolatrous father may be deſtituted and forſaken by his ſonne, if hee ſhould offer vpon violence to compel him to Paganiſme (as <hi>Theodoret</hi> hath it it his third booke and fourteene and 22. Chapters, and <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> in his ſecond booke, againſt ſuch as diſcommend the retired and ſolitarie life) yet if there be no compulſion vſed, I can ſhew you generall and prouinciall Councels both, which haue ordained, that neither the father may forſake the ſonne, nor the ſonne the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, nor the wife her husband, nor the ſeruant
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:19591:65"/>his maſter, for this cauſe only, that they differ in religion. Sir it is not your Friars cowle, nor Monks habit, nor anie order of knighthood, that ye can enter into, ſhall euer be able to raz or blot out, that faſt tie and obligation, which in this caſe, God and men haue inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeablie ſealed and deliuered the one to the other It is a faſhion well becomming Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barians and heretiques (ſo ſaith Biſhop <hi>Victor</hi> in his firſt booke <hi>De perſecutione Vandalica</hi>) to ſeparate husbands from their wiues, or chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren from their parents. And when <hi>Valentini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> the Emperor like a moſt glorious Prince, had authoriſed the profeſſion of Chriſtian re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and the citie of <hi>Carthage,</hi> whence by reaſon of <hi>Arrianiſme</hi> it was for a ſeaſon exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, the firſt worke that the Biſhop did, was, that al mariages ſhould hold though the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties were of different religion, and parents ſhould haue their children againe, that the Arrians had forceably taken from them.</p>
            <p>So then to begin our relation with the ſtory of a ſlaue. If he would fall off from his maſter becauſe he was a Gentile or a Iew, might not the fauour of libertie, but eſpeciallie of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, plead his excuſe? the Canons, which bee tearmed the Canons of the Apoſtles, flatlie ſay no. <hi>If ſeruants bee promoted to holie orders without their maſters conſent, ipſo facto, their
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:19591:65"/>maſters may challenge them backe againe for ſlaues,</hi> (it is to be found in the 81. Chapter, But if any perſon of ſeruile condition be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie the degree of holy orders (as was <hi>One ſimus</hi> and the maſter yeeld therunto) after they be enfranchiſed and made free men, it may bee done. The Councell of Gangrene which was held An. 324 and ſomewhat after the <hi>Nicene,</hi> forbids it likewiſe, ſaying: Let him be accurſed whoſoeuer he be that ſhall ſeduce another mans ſeruant to be vndutifull to his maſter vnder colour or occaſion of his religion, and doth not rather teach him to ſerue him with an honeſt heart and all due obſeruance, that ſo he may be a free man of Chriſt, (as <hi>Ignatius</hi> ſupplies it) let him be accurſed. Certaine it is, that this is to be ment of the ſlaues of hethen, and the religion there mentioned is to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended of the Chriſtian. But in the Councell held at <hi>Orleance</hi> vnder King <hi>Childebert,</hi> there is a great deale more: for ouer and beſides that it diſauowes the voluntary obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a ſlaue to the ſeruice of the Church, without his maſters knowledge, it laies a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty vpon the Biſhop that ſo admits him: to wit, that in ſix months after, he is not to ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrate. <hi>Iuſtinian</hi> in his 123. nouell Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, apointed a certaine time, wherin the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter was to recouer his ſlaue from the Church,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:19591:66"/>but <hi>Leo</hi> the 9 made an act, that the challenge ſhould ſtill hold and be perpetuall. Yea but if you ſay the caſe is altered, in a Monk, for his eſtate being regular, is more to be priuiledged than a ſecular prieſt. <hi>Charle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maine</hi> (as it ſhould appeare by a certaine conſtitution of his) is of a contrarie opinion. Let no man, ſaith he, entice another mans ſlaue, to become a Prieſt or a Monk, without leaue and licenſe of his maſter (you may read the Act in the 20. and 27. Chapter. The primitiue Church obſerued as much, not that ſhe thought God was any way diſhonored by the miniſterie of a poore ſlaue, (for with God all men are alike) how then? <hi>Tertullian</hi> againſt the heretique <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> will giue you the reaſon. Saith he, what action is there more vniuſt, wrongfull, and wicked than ſo to demerit my ſeruant, with your kindnes, as that neuer afterwards he ſhal liue to doe me any more ſeruice? another man ſhall lay claime to him, and let me haue any ſuit in law, he ſhall produce him for a witnes againſt me, and that (which of all bad is the worſt) euen then, and at that time, whilſt he liues in my houſe with me, liues vpon my al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance, trembles and quakes vnder the ſtripes of my rod. A wiſe man ſhould bee as ſparing to do another mans wife, his ſlaue, free man, or any vnder his charge, any cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:19591:66"/>extraordinarie, as to procure them any harme. For a man cannot poſſiblie inueagle or allure anie of them, but withall of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie he muſt bereaue them particularlie of that loue and truth which in conſcience the wife ſhould beare to her husband, the ſlaue to his maſter, the freeman to his patron, and laſtlie the ſubject to his ſoueraigne. And no doubt by Gods grace, but he that liues in ſubiection to another mans rules, in that courſe of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, may be partaker of eternall bliſſe: whereas he that ſpurnes and murmurs in that he is called to be a ſeruant, ſhould I ſay, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorceth himſelfe from the religion &amp; faith of Chriſt, nay maliciouſlie reneges it, which conſiſts whollie in loue and obedience, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept there be ſom ſuch action inioined, which is directlie oppoſite to pietie. And ſo writes S. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> in his 35 homilie vpon thoſe words of S. <hi>Paul, Children obey your parents in all things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now concerning wiues (for that is our next paſſage) ye find it thus decreed, <hi>Let neither Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, Prieſt or Deacon, put away his wife, vnder colour of religion: if he doe, let him be excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, and if he ſo continue, let him be degraded.</hi> The ſame Canon is thus tranſcribed into <hi>Gratians</hi> decree, at the 28. diſtinction, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer ſhall teach that a Prieſt vpon pretence
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:19591:67"/>of religion, may refuſe his wife, let him be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed. And the Fathers aſſembled in the Councell of <hi>Gangrene</hi> publiſht this decree, that whoſoeuer ſhould put a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween a married or vnmarried Prieſt, as though his mariage diſabled him from ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtring the holy communion, and for that cauſe refuſeth to communicate with him, let him be accurſed. And a little after: Whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer ſhall condemne mariage, or thinke that a faithfull deuout woman, cohabiting with her husband, is therefore iudiciallie to bee indited, as if, forſooth, the married cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple could not poſſiblie enter into the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen, let him bee accurſed. What canſt thou ſay for thy ſelfe to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary? doſt thou not find by theſe lawes, that as well ſhe is to be reputed for an excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate perſon, which vpon pretence of liuing continent, liues a part from her husband, and refraines his bed, as they, which ſtand ſo high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vpon commendation of chaſtitie, (and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they would be tearmed abſtinent) do vilifie and diſgrace the holy eſtate of wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locke?</p>
            <p>Now concerning parents and children, their obligation, as well as their relation, is mutuall. Therefore the Synod ſaith thus much firſt of parents: Whoſoeuer ſhall for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:19591:67"/>his own children, &amp; ſhal not bring them vp, as it is the part of a father, and giue them not things neceſſary, but vnder pretence of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing continentlie, thinks they may be forlorn let him be accurſed. Son, thou neuer foundeſt me yet defectiue in any one point, that a kind father ſhould doe for his child, which if I had I muſt haue been extreamlie negligent, and ſo reputed in the iudgement of <hi>Ptolomie.</hi> I haue maintained, cheriſht, and taught thee: for Greek and Latin, I dare be bold to ſay, thou haſt been inſtructed, ſo far foorth, as was fitting for a yong gentleman, Thy good vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ckle <hi>Monſieur Iames Aerodius</hi> the preſident, and my ſelfe, haue made it our eager conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (as indeed we exceed both in our loue and affection, towards thee) that thou ſholdſt faile of nothing that might be any way deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed meet for any excellent purpoſe, that ſo fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the courſe whereunto thou waſt moſt inclined, we might in time accordingly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of thee, (which <hi>Nazianzene</hi> ſaith was the faſhion among the Athenians) or that thou mighteſt diſpoſe of thy ſelfe, in caſe we were dead before, and thou come to full age. And haue we this faire recompence for all our loue and kindneſſe to be forſaken by thee now, &amp; not thought good enough to be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vnto at thy departure. It is reported in <hi>S.
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:19591:68"/>Hieromes</hi> Epiſtles, that the holy matron <hi>Paula</hi> left both towne and children, excepting only her yong daughter <hi>Euſtochia,</hi> whom ſhe took in her companie with her to <hi>Bethleem,</hi> vpon a reſolution there to liue retired. But I muſt tell you, all theſe children (beſide <hi>Toxotius</hi>) were come to yeers, and he was not left vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouided neither, for the mother made him, and his ſiſter <hi>Rufina,</hi> that was mariageable, her ſole executors, and gaue them all that ſhe had, and appointed them guardians to ouerſee them. And the like ſtory you may read in <hi>Paulinus</hi> in his 10. Epiſtle to <hi>Seuerus,</hi> how he commends exceedinglie the holy woman <hi>Melania,</hi> that hauing buried her husband, and being the mother of one little boy, left him behind her, ſailde to Ieruſalem, and there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tooke her ſelfe to a life of more perfection. But ſhe left him (which likewiſe would be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued,) exceeding rich, ſhe left him kin, and allied to all the great men of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now that I may haue a ſaying to thee, come on ſir, ſtand neere, and hearken to the doome which ſhall be pronounced againſt thee, and bethinke thy ſelfe, who ſhall giue thee abſolution from the curſe of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Synod, whereunto without doubt thou art notoriouſlie liable. If any ſonne (ſaith the 16. Canon) ſhall forſake their parents, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciallie
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:19591:68"/>ſuch as are beleeuers, taking occaſion by pretence of religion, and ſhall not yeelde them more dutie and reuerence in that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, let them be accurſed. Now I pray thee, tell me trulie did they conceale this Councel from thee? I verilie beleeue they did. I cannot be perſwaded that thy iudgement is ſo erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous as to imagine that a ſonne may doe more againſt his father, than a ſlaue againſt his maſter: as to imagine that it were a grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous ſinne for a father (not to prouide for his children) and but a peccadilio in a ſonne to ſtand out vndutifull, deſpitefull, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptuous againſt his parents. See, the Councell makes noe diſtinction of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing parents or vnbeleeuing, of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens minority or their fulage. But peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, they vvill priuily whiſper, and tell thee that this Councel vvas but to hold for a time, not to continue. To this I anſwere, that the reuerend fathers of the Church, for a long time after, approued that Synode, as you may find it recorded in the fifth generall Councell of Conſtantinople, and ſo did <hi>Gratian</hi> alſo in his Decrees: for to what purpoſe elſe did hee incorporate it among them? Laſtlie, that an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſvvere might ſtand for good, if the Councell of Gangrene had intended their Canon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt deſertion of heathen parents onely: for
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:19591:69"/>vvhereas Gentiliſme vvas then in more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt and ſway than Chriſtianity, the greater care was to be taken for it, that they ſhould not loath our Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> religion too much (as poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly they would) and not vnlike, but at that time, the Church might directly inhibite the beleeuing man to forſake his vnbeleeuing wife, vnleſſe in point of violence forced to pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganiſme and Idolatry. But ſure it is, that the Councells meaning neuer was that Children ſhould forſake their parents, becauſe they were Chriſtians, for it ſaith in expreſſe words: [Let children reuerence their parents, if for no other ende, yet for this, becauſe they are Chriſtians], a reaſon (as I conceiue) that will euer holde for Chriſtians: for <hi>Vigoreus,</hi> a wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of our time, cites the ſame Synode to this very purpoſe. But it will not bee amiſſe in my opinion, to ſet downe the cauſe and occaſion of the ſummoning of this Synode. It was not becauſe Pagan parents did make it their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of grieuance, that their children did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon and forſake them, the cauſe was clean contrarie, which was, that they which were Chriſtians left them which were of their owne profeſſion, and religion, malapert and ſawcie ſonnes and treſpaſſe ſo againſt their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, as thou haſt lately done againſt mee: marry, the difference if any bee, is this, that
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:19591:69"/>they in former time, affected a true monaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call retired life, and thou according to the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion of the time, doſt affect a profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie conſiſting in an habit of apparell, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malitie of words: they crucified the worlde to the fleſh, and the fleſh to the vvorlde, but men of your coate ſaue halfe the labour; and cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the world onlie. From whence then comes ſuch a corruption in this diſcipline? I will tell you. About the time that ſome newe fangled fellowes ſprung vp in the Church, and termed themſelues Anchorites, Eremites or Monkes, there ſteps me vp one <hi>Euſtatius,</hi> who led by an inconſiderate zeale, began whereſoeuer hee came, to thunder out thoſe glorious magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent words written in the Goſpell, [that they were vnworthy of Chriſt, that loued Father or mother more than Chriſt,] and thereupon to inferre that all things in the world are to bee contemned and ſet at naught: as houſe, poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions, parents, children, brethren, yea (and to make ſhort worke,) all the vniuerſal world, the better to liue in ſome ſolitary hermitage, vnder ſome rule, and in ſome company ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and ſhut from all men. And why ſo thinke you? becauſe it was nothing worth to bee a Chriſtian, except you had bene alſo of the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of <hi>Euſtatius.</hi> But what was the iſſue of this Doctrine? Sir this, that the wife wold leaue her
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:19591:70"/>husband, and be his wife: the ſeruant his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and he his ſeruant: the parents their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and they their parents: that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians ſet light by marriage, and all duty elſe, which euery man owes vnto his countrie: that religion, which was wont to keepe all in good order, was now become ringleader to all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion and diſorder. Laſtly, that the Gentiles might well ſay (and <hi>Zozimus</hi> by name) <hi>The Chriſtians be barren &amp; unfruitfull in all affairs of dutie,</hi> which is a ſpeech that <hi>Tertullian</hi> in his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologeticus, holds <hi>to be the moſt diſgracefull &amp; ſcandalous that ouer yet was vttered againſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.</hi> But the ſectaries of <hi>Euſtatius</hi> reioynde, why but this deſertion is, becauſe wee would bee the freer for the ſeruice of God. But the Fathers aſſembled in Councell, condemne this faire occaſion, and prooued full &amp; whole, that it was an act far more Chriſtianlike and Religious, to worſhip and loue our parents, (for that is the commandement of God) than ſo to ſerue God, as thereby to deſpiſe the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, a thing which he vtterly forbids. For God and parents may well bee honoured to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, but no man liuing can truely worſhip God without he honor his parents alſo. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon this new founder <hi>Eustatius,</hi> ſhortly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter changed his copy, and came to be a Biſhop in the Church, and not a cloiſterer. And that
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:19591:70"/>this was the true occaſion of aſſembling that Councell the very letter of that Councell, as alſo <hi>Socrates, Sozomen, Iſidor</hi> and <hi>Gratian</hi> in his 16. and 30. <hi>Diſtinct.</hi> doe apparantly teſtifie. How now ſir? Will ſo many and ſo waighty authorities do no good with you? for (I thank you) you haue beene bold to ſet my authority at naught? or are you eftſoones perſwaded, that ſhould I affoord my conſent neuer ſo much, you could not yet bee a true and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Ieſuite? peraduenture you are yet ſome what grauelled in this doubt? ſo then let vs take ſome view of that which they alleadge vnto you out of S. <hi>Hierome,</hi> and withall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, whether there be any cloyſter Diuinity, or new found Goſpel lately ſprung vp among them, to repeale theſe auncient Canons and decrees of the Church, which you in your braue ruffe doe ſo lightly eſteeme of. It may not be denied, but that S. <hi>Hierome</hi> writing to <hi>Heliodorus</hi> in commendation of a ſolitary life, vſeth theſe words [ſhould thy little nephewe hang faſt claſping about thy neck: &amp; thy mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with her treſſes diſheueled about her ears renting &amp; tearing her garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, diſcouer thoſe paps which gaue thee ſucke: ſhould thy father that begate thee lie downe before thee in the way: paſſe ouer thy father, and trample him vnder thy feete, ſhed not a teare, but with an
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:19591:71"/>heroicall reſolution, flye towring vp in high ſpeed to the ſtandard of thy Sauiours croſſe. Sauage cruelty in ſuch a caſe is your onely pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Doubtleſſe, heere is a right noble ſentence and well becomming the high ſpirit of ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent a Father in the Church: but before I cleare the point, &amp; ſhew in what meaning this was ſpoken, wherein S. <hi>Hierome</hi> (as it ſhould ſeeme by this) makes ſuch cheape reputation of parents authority, and in ſo dooing diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours the chaſtity of all naturall kindnes: I would faine ſee that paſſage in him, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning parents obedience, (it is in his Epiſtle <hi>de vitando ſuſpecto contubernio</hi>) reconciled to this. There you ſhall reade him thus, Father and Mother, ſaith he, are names of dutie, wordes of reſpect, bonds of nature, and vnder God, the ſecond truce and league of our loue. It is none of your commendation to ſay you loue them not, it is a notorious ſinne in you, if you hate them. Our Lord and Sauior Ieſus Chriſt was ſubiect to his parents. He reuerenced that mother to whom hee was father, loued that nurce; whom he foſtered, and forgot not that wombe where hee was conceiued, nor thoſe armes that ſo oft bore him. You will perhaps replie and ſay, but heere lies the exception, when a ſonne liuing vnder the gouernment of his Father is once reſolutely determined to
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:19591:71"/>goe into a monaſterie, why then hee may bee bolde to forbeare all ſhew of dutie, and paſſe neither for good nature nor good manners. Then crueltie in that caſe may be interpreted mercie; incluilitie, good conditions; contempt obedience. But thinke not (good ſon) though S. <hi>Hierome</hi> vſed ſuch a faire colourable ſpeech to <hi>Heliodorus</hi> that if hee ſhould haue dealt in earneſt with him, he would haue aduiſed him, to ben ſo behaued, as his words doe implye. God forbid that S. <hi>Hierome</hi> ſhould euer be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for principall or acceſſory in parricide: that for the ſame verie cauſe that <hi>Aeneas</hi> was ſurnamed the <hi>pious</hi> (as <hi>Virgil</hi> in all places ſtiles him)
<q>
                  <l>Amids the ſcorching flames, and thouſand ſhot of darts</l>
                  <l>I reſcued mine aged Syre, and made theſe ſhoulders bowe</l>
                  <l>To garde him from the enemies troope.</l>
               </q> For an action directly contrarie, a Chriſtian man ſhould goe about to merit, the ſame ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>name &amp; appellation: or that S. <hi>Hierome</hi> by any meanes, ſhould rather propoſe wicked <hi>Tullia</hi> for an inſtance of pietie, that roade in her coach ouer her fathers coarſe, than deuout <hi>Aeneas,</hi> for an imitation to <hi>Heliodorus.</hi> Yea though hee might purchaſe thereby all the kingdomes and ſeignories of the world, or all the vaſt territories of hell, where ghoſtes Lorde it, as <hi>Painims</hi> ſuppoſe: or laſtly, that
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:19591:72"/>who ſo profeſt himſelfe a Monke in ſuch a ſcornefull faſhion to his parents, ſhould bee better thought of than <hi>Cleobis</hi> and <hi>Piton,</hi> that drewe their aged mother in a litter, (to a place where ſhe was to ſacrifice) in ſtead of a payre of co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tch-horſes. Or thoſe brethren, which for they reſcued their impotent parents, from the rage of a tempeſtuos fire, the people of Catanna, in a reuerence of their deuotion, called by no other name than the <hi>godlie-chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</hi> Certainely it is ſo far from S. <hi>Hieromes</hi> meaning to haue his words peruerted &amp; drawn to the maintenance of ſuch a barbarous cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city and impity, as that when hee ſpake this to <hi>Heliodorus,</hi> neither his Father or mother were then liuing: ſo that the inference is impoſſible that had his Father &amp; mother forbad him to haue beene an Eremite in the wildernes of Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria, he would haue gone ouer them, and ſtam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped them vnder his feete. What then may S. <hi>Hieromes</hi> meaning be? why this: After <hi>Helio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorus</hi> had long time beene a ſouldier in the wars, and dealt much in negotiating of ſtate matters, growing into ſome years, and hauing no iſſue, (as we tolde you before) he bad fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well to the world, and in S. <hi>Hieromes</hi> compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny which was his puyſne, vowed a ſolitary and retyred life, and to that end they both entred into a monaſtery, liued there long time toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:19591:72"/>at laſt <hi>Heli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dorus</hi> had a great longing to ſee how his onely ſiſter, and hir young ſonne did: and there (lo) did he alter his former re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, for there he betakes himſelfe to the Church, and in ſtead of being a Monke, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes a Cleargy man. This was the time without all peraduenture, when S. <hi>Hierome</hi> wrought theſe matters in commendation of the monaſticall life, beeing for yeares but a ſtripling, and almoſt a very boy, (as he ſpeaks of himſelfe in another place,) and comming freſh from the vniuerſity, then he vſeth theſe flouriſhing ſpeeches vnto him, alluding from his ſecular to the heauenly warfare, interlacing withall ſuch ſtrong motiues, and perſwaſions as friends vſe often to their friends, all to this purpoſe in effect, that wheras we are comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be <hi>Eunuches</hi> for Chriſts ſake, to put the verie eies out of our head if they offend, to leaue and forſake all that we haue in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent worlde, as if the caſe were deſperate for a rich man euer to come to heauen, (a point whereof S. <hi>Auſten</hi> diſcourſes excellently in his 89. epiſtle to <hi>Hilarius</hi>) not to be carefull for to morrow, to turne thy left cheeke to him that ſmites thee on the right, and many moe ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the like nature, which were they lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally vnderſtood and not ſpiritually, without queſtion, would fill the Church full with he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:19591:73"/>and yet concerning worldlie vvealth doth not <hi>S. Auſten</hi> in an Epiſtle to <hi>Bonifacius</hi> tell vs, a valiant Chriſtian minded man ſhould not be puft vp if he haue it, nor be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected if he looſe it? vvas not <hi>Leontius</hi> a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Laodicea,</hi> condemned of the Church for diſmembring himſelfe? vvhereupon <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſius</hi> a Biſhop of <hi>Nice</hi> in his 73. and 79 que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion ſaith, vvhat is meant by this Goſpell, <hi>(if thy right eie offend thee, or thy right hand, cut it off from thee)</hi> Chriſt meant it not of our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dilie parts and members, (God forbid) but of our friends, and kinsfolke, for hee ſlanders Gods workmanſhip, that diſmembers him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe? And euen <hi>S. Hierome</hi> himſelfe, hath he not vvritten ſo manie things in that ſtrain of vehemencie for commendation of virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie and ſingle life, that he ſeems in a manner to diſallow and condemne all mariage? yet queſtionles he neuer meant it. For were it ſo that he ſpake as he thought, and perſwaded <hi>Heliodorus</hi> rather to make his way ouer his fathers body, than to forſake that bliſſefull eſtate (which as it ſeems in your conceipt) the cloiſter affoords, why then would he prefer Prieſthood before it? indeed he confeſſeth that <hi>Heliodorus</hi> anſwer, may ſerue any other mans turne elſe, but cannot ſerue his owne, who hauing profeſt in preciſe tearmes, the
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:19591:73"/>actiue life, might not without blame, renou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce his former profeſſion, and betake himſelfe to an order of higher perfection, as namely Prieſthood. Indead he deſcribes the good and happie eſtate of them that liue in mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, and likewiſe how perilous and ſubiect to all manner of temptations, their condition is, that liue at large in the world and ſaith he was a glad man, to ſee him come vp ſo high, but very fearefull to thinke of his fall. So that he blames not <hi>Heliodorus,</hi> for leauing his cloiſter, nor his entrings into Prieſthood, nay he perſwades him not directly, to forſake the one, and returne to the other. But becauſe firſt he reuolted from being a ſouldier, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Monke, and afterwards grew wearie of his cowle, abjuring the profeſſion which he vndertook in <hi>S. Ieromes</hi> company, his endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour is now by theſe forceable reaſons, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther rhetorique ſchemes and colours, to draw him backe againe into his monaſterie. And as for theſe words of the Goſpell <hi>(he that lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth father or mother more than me)</hi> I pray marke whether <hi>Heliodorus</hi> anſwered <hi>S. Hierom</hi> well, that they were to be vnderſtood in caſe of martyrdome, or whether <hi>S. Hieromes</hi> reply to this anſwer, be ſufficient. But be it as it may be, that no man ſhould ſtand to too ſtiffelie vpon the authoritie of that ſpeech, which is
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:19591:74"/>not altogether ſo true, as neat and elegant, obſeruing more his words, than his meaning, for an vpſhopt of all, when he came to riper yeeres, he recants that opinion, in an epiſtle written to <hi>Nepotian,</hi> who by this time alſo, was both in yeers and diſcretion grown to be a man. And as concerning ſuch arguments, as he had propoſed to <hi>Heliodorus,</hi> he ſaith he did it as a yong man, after the faſhion of the ſchooles, when the fire of his ſtudy and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in Rhetorique was not clean beat out of him for verily at that time, a man might free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enter into a monaſterie, and when him liſt leaue him. And then the queſtion was idle, whether a man might follow this courſe of life, without his parents liking, becauſe then there was no ſuch obligation by vowes as now a daies there is, and had a man miſliked of his profeſſion, his puniſhment was none other but the imputation of lightneſſe and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtancie, which is euident out of <hi>S. Auſtins</hi> epiſtle to his friend <hi>Boniface.</hi> The profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of being a Monke in thoſe daies was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but the meditation, and exerciſe of the ancient, free, and trulie chriſtian manner of liuing. And therefore in this pretence, they might with much more honeſtie looſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues from their kindered, and alliance. So then let no man father it vpon <hi>S. Hierome,</hi>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:19591:74"/>which makes nothing for his purpoſe. Indeed he went about to ſolicite ſome of his fellows, to enter into this kind of life with him, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie one liked it not, and among others <hi>Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machius</hi> that was his chiefeſt friend, had leaſt fancie vnto it. For his deſire was rather to liue married than to be tied to ſuch ſtrict rules of religion. Onlie <hi>Bonoſius</hi> followed him, and profeſt himſelfe a Monke, not paſſing for mother, brother, or ſiſters, yet ſtill reſpecting his father. Nay euen S. <hi>Hierome</hi> himſelfe, after he had been an Hermite for ſome time, retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned backe againe to <hi>Rome.</hi> S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> indeed in his 76. Epiſtle, is not throughlie reſolued in this point, whether a Monke forſaking his cel, might afterwards be in holy orders. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore bethinke now with thy ſelfe, and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it well, whether that aſſertion of S. <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>romes</hi> can be thy iuſt excuſe, I ſay whether it can be any iuſt excuſe, for thee that art not yet fiue and twentie yeers of age, that haſt a father and mother yet liuing, that neuer madeſt any vow to the Ieſuits before hand, that art not hereupon either to renege Paganiſme, or to ſecure thy ſelfe from perſecution, or to wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der into vaſt and vncouth wilderneſſes, and there to continue, but to be entertained into as delicate and pleaſant places and cities, as the worlds yeeld any, that haſt an abbie for
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:19591:75"/>thy priſon, and a good town for thy paradiſe. But make of S. <hi>Hieromes</hi> ſpeech what can be made, make him of what age thou wilt, when he wrote this Epiſtle, if notwithſtanding all this, the name of ſuch a great workma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie with you, why may you not for your ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction herein parralell <hi>Heliodorus</hi> example with him? why not the example of <hi>Letus</hi> (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeciallie if that be S. <hi>Auſtius</hi> epiſtle which is written vnto him:) who hauing vowed a reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious life, and that not in his minoritie but at mans eſtate, vpon the ſole diſcontent and griefe which he conceiued afterwards, becauſe he had neglected the dutie to his mother, in not making her acquainted with this vow, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned fairelie home againe to his countrie, which before in the hot zeale he bare to a religious life, he had abandoned. Why may you not oppoſe <hi>S. Iohn Chryſoſtomes</hi> example. theſe men were neuer for all this, either the leſſe holie, or worſe Chriſtians, moſt certaine it is there is nothing can be a bar to a godlie life. You may not plead pretence that you are maried, that you are a father of children, that you are a ſouldier, a merchant, an artificer, a ſeruant, a rich man, a begger, (for ſo ſpeakes <hi>S. Chryſoſtome</hi> in a certaine mariage ſermon.) I tell you one that dwells in the Citie, may com very neer to a Monks deuotion, &amp; a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:19591:75"/>man, that liues at home, may ſay his pray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ers, and faſt, and be penitent for his ſinnes, as the ſame Father alſo affirmes in another place. Now that you may not thwart me, and ſay, that ſuch precedents were proper onlie for the primitiue Church, and that the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon ſtood then betwixt gentiliſme and Chriſtianity, betwixt a religious life in a cloi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and an vpright godlie life abroad in the world, when this controuerſie was treated of. I will produce you that verie age wherein S. <hi>Bernard</hi> liued, and laſtlie to leaue you with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all ſcruple of doubt, I will anſwer an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection, which is made out of the Emperor <hi>Iuſtinians</hi> conſtitution, which in ſome mens conceipt, is verie ſtrong for the libertie of children, in dedicating themſelues to the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of the Church, without their parents leaue, to the intent, that hauing throughlie conſidered what can bee alleadged of both ſides, thou thy ſelfe mayſt be iudge, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, whether this fact of thine which thou haſt thus committed againſt me, be to be termed a fact of honeſt behauiour, or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trariwiſe altogether of vnreſpectiue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanour. Here then the queſtion conſiſts ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerallie betweene Catholiques, nay in a far more narrow compaſſe, than Catholiques, it conſiſts between monkes: that holie Abbot
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:19591:76"/>had a nephew whoſe name was <hi>Robert,</hi> his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther purpoſed to make him a Monke of the order of <hi>Cluniacenſes,</hi> but he dying before his ſonne was tendred, <hi>Robert</hi> profeſt himſelf a <hi>Ciſterian</hi> Monke, and S. <hi>Bernard</hi> himſelfe adopted him thereunto. Soone after this, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Monkes of the order of <hi>Cluniacenſes,</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced the poore youth, and drew him from that Abbie to their owne. Heare then began the brige between the two regulars. S. <hi>Bernard</hi> was the firſt man that accuſed this their fact, and ſaid it was done by meer ſeducement and enueagling of the youth, in that they had vſed fraude, flatterie, and craftie conueiance, to effect this their purpoſe. For they that ſhould ſeduce his nephew, firſt attempted it by a nouice of their order, after that by a Monke that was better able, laſtlie by one of their greateſt Priors, amongſt them. Then hee laid to their charge, forceable intruſion, in that they had hurt the porters of the Cel, and ſo reſcued yong <hi>Robert</hi> out of his cloiſter, as if they would haue broken a Gaile. With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out acquainting either the ſuperior of the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der withall, or the Abbot, or his vncle S. <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard,</hi> now I pray thee tel me whether thy caſe and this be all one, firſt, becauſe one that was penitentiarie and Confeſſor there, buzd this into thine eare, and after him, another that
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:19591:76"/>was maſter of the chamber, came and told thee that there was no eſtate of men ſo bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, as the Regular was, and laſtlie the prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall of the order came, &amp; ſaid, that among al the regular, there was none comparable with your ſociety, as beeing called after the name of Ieſus: but marke what S. <hi>Bernard</hi> alleages, and that will ſufficientlie refute and condemn your ſo highly magnified vocation and inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration: there was no ſuite (ſaith hee made for his admiſſion by his parents, which the rule expreſſely enioyneth.) as though hee ſhould haue ſaid, albeit his Father when he was aliue did much wiſh to haue his ſonne of the order of Cluniacenſis, but being preuented by death neuer liued to ſee his deſire fulfilled, and the common rule expreſly requires, that he that will enter into a monaſterie, muſt bee offered vnto it firſt, by his parents, in the view and preſence of ſome witneſſes (for that is alſo in the rule) this wants in his profeſſion, to your order of Cluniacenſis: but theſe prouiſions, were not neceſſarie or requiſite, for his admiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to the Ciſtertians, becauſe then hee was paſt his nonage, and was at his owne choyce and beſtowing. Why then (exclaymes the good Abbot) why then haue you robd me of my nephew? why haue you bereft mee of my ioy? Why haue yee taken away the fruite of
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:19591:77"/>my ſpirit, and the one halfe of my poor ſoule? might he not haue beene ſaued with me, if he had continued with me? O nephew ſaith hee, the vizard of holines hath beguiled thee, the pretence of religion hath ſeduced thee, the authority of the Ancients hath vndone thee. Now ſurely if the good Abbot inueigh ſo bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly againſt theſe monkes, that thereupon he calls them rauening wolues, what might bee fit for me to do againſt theſe Ieſuits that haue robd me in my life time of my ſon, in ſuch an vnworthy faſhion? and when I challenge him, they deny him trecherouſly? peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture they tooke ſome compaſſion of thee, as the monks did of young <hi>Robert.</hi> peraduenture thou hadſt beene in ſtate of damnation, if thou hadſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained with thy Chriſtian Catholique pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, thy Vncles and Aunts, Brothers and Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters. But if the bare changing of one mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery for another, was of ſuch feareful ſequele, that the poore ſoule was in danger of beeing damned for it (for ſo thinkes S. <hi>Bernard</hi>) what will betide thee, that treadeſt vnder thy feete and in ſuch a preſumptuous inſolent manner, ſpurneſt at, not God almighties commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments alone, but alſo the decrees and canons of our reuerend prelates and paſtors? &amp; why forſooth? not to chaunge thy religion but thy habite, not the Church, but thy ranke and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:19591:77"/>in the Church. Pray let me tell you what <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>igorous</hi> once wrote in a ſermon of his, which he made of S. <hi>Martin,</hi> it is written to vs French men, you ſhall neuer find him vary in opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the auncient and moſt ſanctified Church gouernement: his words be theſe. S. <hi>Martin</hi> was a nouice in the Chriſtian religion, and not admitted into the congregation by the Sacrament of Baptiſme, and albeit hee dwelt with his parents which were gentiles, yet did he perform all good offices vnto them as became a Chriſtian: (for the Law of God doth not acquit that obligation, wherein a ſon is bound to his Father, or a ſeruant to his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. And ſurely the Church neuer taught <hi>Martin</hi> to be a rebell againſt his parents, but rather in all things to yeelde them due obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and reſpect, ſo God were not offended.) Whereupon by reaſon of ſuch reuerent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity vnto his parents commaund hee got this graunt from them, that conſidering for what vocation hee was moſt fit and addreſſed vnto that they would bee pleaſed to beſtow him in, for queſtionleſſe the ſonne is not left to any ſuch libertie, as either to marrie or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take himſelfe to anie ſort of liuing, without his Fathers approbation, I ſay vnto anie ſort of life, heeres no limitation [except he will be a monke]. And now that wee paſſe not ouer
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:19591:78"/>
               <hi>Iuſtinian</hi> the Emperor, grant him to bee of the opinion, that for a ſonne to vow a monaſtical life without his Fathers conſent, was neither a ſinne of ingratitude, nor any cauſe able in law to diſinherit him. Doth it therfore follow that becauſe it is no ſuch hainous offence as parricide or inceſt, therefore it is no offence? or it deſerues not diſinheriting, therefore muſt it paſſe without all correction, or if it be no ſinne is it therefore no fault? Why I tell you, a ſonne might not marrie without his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers leaue, put caſe he had married, there was no law could extend ſo far as to diſinherit him, vnleſſe his wife were ſome leaud and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous perſon: will your inference hereupon be, that therefore he offended not his father in marrying againſt his vvill, this is a noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <hi>nonſequitur.</hi> And novv ſir, I tell you for your learning, let <hi>Iuſtinian</hi> ſpeake or thinke as pleaſeth him, all the Emperours before him made this caſe a matter of diſinheriting: aske you me what warrant I haue for it? marry ſir this, becauſe he profeſſeth in this one point, to correct the auncient Ciuill Law, and this I tell you withall, that take all thoſe Emperors together, eſpecially thoſe that were Chriſtian Emperours, and I truſt their ioint authorities ſhall ſway more, than <hi>Iustinians</hi> alone: who in all likelihood might haue as good leaue, to
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:19591:78"/>erre therein, as he did miſtake in the matter of diuorce, &amp; in participating with the hereſie of <hi>Eutiches.</hi> But certaine it is that in the ende of that conſtitution, <hi>[which is an act for bondmen comming to Chriſtianity,]</hi> wheras <hi>Iuſtinian</hi> takes away the penalty of diſinheriting, it is to bee vnderſtood of ſuch children of the Gentiles, as entring into holy orders, or monaſticall profeſſion, were therfore emancipated in caſe they were ſonnes, or <hi>ipſo facto</hi> enfranchiſed, if they were bond-men. For had the act beene generall, comprizing all, or more ſpeciall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending onelie to the children of Chriſtians, it is not to bee preſumed, but that hee would haue vſed ſome diſtinction, concerning their age, that thus betook themſelues either to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie orders, or monaſticall profeſſion; and haue ſaid, before fourteen yeares be compleat theres a nullity if a man profeſſe: after four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene, there is none, the vow holds, and there is no danger of beeing diſinherited for the matter. So then <hi>Iuſtinians</hi> conſtitution <hi>(in the titles of Biſhops and Cleargy men)</hi> is in this ſence to bee vnderſtood, that whereas the cauſe of our Chriſtian religion is to all intents much more fauourable, than Pagan Idolatry, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Pagans children, liued they vnder their parents verge and iuriſdiction, or liued they without it, both the one and the other might
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:19591:79"/>vowe and profeſſe religion, without paine or perill of being diſinherited, (the forme wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is deſcribed by <hi>Theodoret</hi> in his two and twentieth chapter:) and ſo might the bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of infidels be enfranchiſed, and in lieu of ſuch manumiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the church to yeeld no ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome backe againe vnto their former maſters as it was enacted before <hi>Iustinians</hi> time, (the like prouiſion is made alſo by <hi>Gregory</hi> the firſt in his ſecond booke, and 78. epiſtle; <hi>if a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian mayden would become a Conuert in anie houſe of religion, againſt her maisters leaue</hi>) whereupon the cloſe of the conſtitution fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes in this maner, <hi>and thus much hath our Imperiall maiesty beene pleaſed to ordaine and decree in contemplation of Gods cauſe and the enlargement of Chriſtian Religion.</hi> And if it bee laſtly replyed, yea but <hi>Iuſtinian</hi> made the ſame Law euen for Chriſtians alſo in 123. nouell conſtitution, and one of the laſt Paragraphs there: Probable it is, and in all likelihood to intended, that the caſe in moſt mens opinions would haue beene hardly thought of, for one to be diſinherited becauſe he was a monke, for in ſo being, hee ſtill notwithſtanding continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Laye,</hi> and entered not into holy orders, He ſucceeded his father by inheritance, his goods eſcheated not to the Abbey, he kept himſelfe ſtill maſter of his owne, (as it is euident out of
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:19591:79"/>the 239. epiſtle of S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> to <hi>Alipius</hi> (and as I ſaid before) it reſted in their own free choice whether they would ſtil continue in their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſterie, or forſake it. But when once vowes of pouertie and ſingle life, came to bee in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, it had beene verie idle, for the parents to haue diſinherited them, that <hi>ipſo facto</hi> by their entrance into the monaſterie diſinheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted themſelues, there was then no farther controuerſie to bee made of the matter, but whether the profeſſion would hold good a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Fathers conſent. Doth all this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe you ſir, and ſticke you yet ſo cloſe to <hi>Iuſtinian?</hi> To encounter him, I oppoſe the ſixt generall Councell of Conſtantinople, I op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that great Canon of the Church in both which the heauie ſentence of excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which the Councell of Gangrene pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth againſt all ſuch kinde of offenders, is againe renewed &amp; confirmed. But in a word to this forraigne Emperour, (whoſe lawes haue no authoritie to binde vs) I oppoſe the moſt excellent and flouriſhing Princes of our own natiue countrie, the decrees &amp; conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of our French Church, the moſt commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and receiued opinions of al men, and the book caſes as they were debated and determined in the court of Parliament. <hi>Charles</hi> the great, with the aduice and conſent of his Lords ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:19591:80"/>and temporall enacted ſundrie lawes about Church matters (my Author for that which I deliuer is <hi>Anſegiſtus</hi>) amongſt the reſt, theſe be ſome in the fift booke, and 95. Chapter.</p>
            <p>Now concerning boies and yong maidens it is flatlie forbidden that either the one ſhould be clipped, or the other veiled, without leaue of their parents. And whoſoeuer ſhall at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt ought againſt this act, ſhall be liable to that fine and amercement which is men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in ſome of the branches of our tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall lawes, and in deed the fine in that Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique law is vnder the title of them which ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kill or clip <hi>yong boies or maiden children.</hi> Where it would be principallie noted, that in the intent of the law, it is abſolutelie all one, to kill our children and to match them to a monaſterie againſt their parents liking. For I pray tell me, is it not a kind of murder ſo to tirannize ouer them, that now they muſt become aliens to their owne parents, no kin to their kinsfolke? muſt die inteſtate, leaue no iſſue, keep no companie, muſt neuer ſee them ſo long as life laſteth, as though they were dead men, and out of mind? I euer before this thought that the Fabian law had onlie taken order with theſe purloining companions and man-ſtealers. But now I find that this great
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:19591:80"/>Emperor hath brought the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> within compaſſe of the <hi>Cornelian</hi> law, and made them murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers. So then to ſumme vp all in a word, what manner of reproofe is this, what a ſtrange kind of challenge, that ſuch holie and bleſſed men forſooth our Sauiour Chriſt ſhould not onlie deem hypocrites, the Church accurſed miſcreants, the law manſtealers, <hi>S. Bernard</hi> wolues, but the Emperor ſhould brand them alſo for murderers? Looke to it in time Sirra, and looke to it, that ſuch and the like enorme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous crimes doe not turne you and your mates one day out of this countrie and all the kings dominions, for ſome ſuch kind of ſpirituall murder, as hereafter you are verie like to haue a hand in. And now let vs take a ſhort view, of that which remaines whether there be any ſuch ſtatute at this time in force, as was that of <hi>Charles</hi> the great. <hi>Charles</hi> the ninth a Prince of famous memorie in a Parliament holden at <hi>Orleance,</hi> the 19. article, makes this order, that no parents, gardians, or kinſmen, man or woman, ſhould ſuffer either their children or their wards to enter into any monaſticall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, vnleſſe the one firſt, were going into fiue and twentie, the other into twentie. And if anie were profeſſed before ſuch times, the parties ſo profeſſed might neuertheleſſe haue power and intereſt to make and declare their
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:19591:81"/>laſt wills and Teſtaments (euer with this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſo) that they bequeathed nothing therein to their monaſterie, anie former lavve or cuſtome to the contrarie notwithſtanding. This conſtitution is of larger extent, than the Councell of <hi>Mentz</hi> in their 16. and 20. que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, the third and ſeuenth Chapters. For in caſe any man before ſuch age ſhould haue ſhaued his crowne, the intendment of the law is, that it vvas done in fraude and couin alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and to ſatisfie the monkes hungrie couetous humour. Furthermore it is ſo ſhort of permitting children before that age, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into religion vvithout parents leaue and liking, that it expreſly forbiddeth parents, gardians, or kinſmen, to giue any ſuch leaue. Now if reports and book caſes can doe any good with you, ſee here is the iudgement of a parliament aſſembled both of Lay and Eccleſiaſticall perſons as it was punctuallie giuen in thy verie caſe, by name (a caſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture, which the Ieſuits of purpoſe haue concealed from thee) and it is this, <hi>that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as Petrus Aerodius Iuſtice of the Pleas of the Crowne hath put in a bill of complaint againſt his yong ſonne Renate by the Ieſuits fraudulentlie ſeduced and purloined from him, and whereas the Rector and Preſident of Clerement Colledge haue beene cited and brought perſonallie into the
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:19591:81"/>Court about the matter, it is therefore ordered and thought good by the Court at the motion of Faius the Kings Atturney general, that Aerodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us ſhall haue a commiſſion granted vnto him to enquire and make ſearch after his ſtolne ſonne,</hi> (for had they not ſtood vpon the negatiue in pleading not guilty, the decree would haue been that they muſt haue laine faſt by it till they had rendred thee openlie in Court) <hi>in the meane while the Court doth ſtraightlie forbid that ought be done to the preiudice of this their order, and that the Ieſuits entertaine him not into their ſocietie as they will anſwer to the contrarie, and that no excuſe of ignorance may be herein pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by the brethren of that company, they charge and require with all that they of Cleremont Colledge certiſie ſo much vnto their ſeuerall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies whereſouer. Giuen at the Parliament the</hi> 20. <hi>of May.</hi> 1586. Happily you ſhall alſo in time reade, what the ſtates of <hi>France</hi> aſſembled at Blois haue humblie beſought his maieſtie now our king, <hi>Henry</hi> the third in this verie buſineſſe, and what he will conclude thereupon after his brother the king decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. I am ſure in the <hi>Interim</hi> his pleaſure was <hi>that the Pope ſhould bee certified thus much, that whereas all good men were much offended heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, his holineſſe would ſet to his helping hand, that it might be reformed and redreſſed.</hi> Now ſir
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:19591:82"/>what can you anſwere to all theſe reaſons? all theſe lawes and precedents? If for this offence of thine, or rather thy ſeducers offence (to whome indeede it is more proper) I haue bin grieued, am I grieued (thinkeſt thou) without cauſe? or is it naturall affection, fleſh &amp; bloud that makes me beyond meaſure paſſionate? or is it my groſſe ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that knowes not in the matter of religion what appertaines to pietie, honeſty, or any duty elſe of great importance. I truſt you are informed and throughly reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by this time, that bee the religious life good and commendable in it ſelfe, or newter and indifferent, it ill beſeemed you, (ſonne) in making choyce of either ſo contemptuouſly to haue neglected me. For were it indifferent theres a neceſſitie would haue forced you to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, but had it bene good and commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable, it would neuer haue proued the worſe for my approbation. Indeede if none could bee ſound now a daies, that would offer their children to the Churches ſeruice, and if it were abſolutelie neceſſarie that young men ſhould miniſter in the Church, in Gods name then let religion bee priuiledged to robbe and ſteale our children from vs (as thou waſt from me) it skills not much by force or policie: but whereas there is ſuch a number of Churches and Abbeyes, can any man ſay, that there is
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:19591:82"/>not plenty enough to ſupply ſuch places but if (and ſpeake what may bee ſpoken for the contrarie) the vow which children make, bee good &amp; iuſtifiable, without the parents leaue, yet, me ſeemes ſomewhat ſhould bee left vnto their diſpoſition, wherein they ſhould beare ſome ſtroake, as peraduenture; to make choice of one Abbey before an other, for their children to be profeſt in; and if there be no remedy but that parents muſt beſoſleight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly put by, when the queſtion ſtands betwixt them and religion, yet me thinkes twere well, that ſome few reliques ſhould ſtill remaine of that ancient dutie &amp; reuerence, which God &amp; nature preſcribed for parents. But the caſe is farre otherwiſe now, for it comes ſo ſhort to the buſineſſe in hand, that parents in any lawe, ſhould bee relinquiſht and deſtituted of their children, that euen they which haue written in an high ſtile for commendation of the ſolitarie life (as moſt monkes haue done) confeſſe that children may bee diſmiſſed out of their cloyſter, and diſclaime their vow, to bee attendant on their parents. And that this vow is of a greater obligation, and much more ancient for continuance, then any other vow whatſoeuer, it may be prooued out of S. <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory Nazianzene,</hi> for he being ſent for to come home from his monaſtery by his Father, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:19591:83"/>he was now growne olde, and not able to follow ſuites in law, which came thicke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him by reaſon of a publique charge where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in hee bare office, and hauing loſt alſo his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſonne <hi>Caeſarius,</hi> forſooke his Couent, made ſpeed to returne to his Father <hi>Gregorie,</hi> and his mother <hi>Nonna,</hi> which then to their farther griefe, had buried their daughter <hi>Gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonia:</hi> the ſame appeares in like manner out of <hi>Heliodor</hi> of whom wee ſpake before, who left to be an Eremite, and left <hi>S. Hieromes</hi> compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, to aſſiſt and helpe, not his Father, but his ſiſter and nephew. S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> holds the ſame opinion or whoſoeuer be the Authour <hi>ad fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres in Eremo;</hi> and will haue no man enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to returne backe againe to his monaſtery, except his Father bee dead firſt. S. <hi>Hierome</hi> in an Epiſtle to <hi>Fabiola,</hi> ſpeakes of this kinde of deſertion, where hee ſaith, how many monkes haue beene cauſe of deſtroying their owne ſoules, in compaſſionating the eſtate of their Fathers and Mothers? in which wordes hee doth not ſimply condemne ſuch deſertion, ſo it be without frawde, to do true ſeruice to their parents, but his meaning is, that many monks pretending ſuch manner of excuſes, doe ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by hazard the vtter vndoing of their owne ſoules. Wherefore put caſe I had beene con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and willing to haue made thee a Ieſuite,
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:19591:83"/>couldſt thou yet find in thy heart, now at this time eſpeciallie, to leaue mee, and liue apart from me? couldeſt thou holde it for a religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous courſe, to lurke in a Cell, (nay a Gayle for that is <hi>Baccharius</hi> word for a monaſterie) where thou mighteſt ſleepe in a whole skinne at pleaſure, and vnderſtand of our ciuil broils or rather lawleſſe open robberies, that ruine and lay waſt thy flouriſhing natiue coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trye? nay couldeſt thou forbeare, to repayre home with al ſpeed poſſible, to be helpfull, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendant and ſeruiceable vnto vs, to allay and mittigate the ſurpaſſing ſorrow, whereof eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie good mans hart is ſenſible in this our coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries combuſtion? But perhaps they detaine thee by violence; Well, bee it ſo, for I am more prone to think ſo, then to imagine thou art cleane paſt all ſence of humanitie, al good nature &amp; gentry, chieflie at this time &amp; ſeaſon, when Princes ioyn iſſue in armes, not for mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of religion, but for a ſoueraign monarchy? but laying aſide all prerogatiue of antiquity in our preſent queſtion (if you be ſo pleaſed) let vs argue the matter by reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a while: wheras it is ſo that you acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt marriage for a Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and for precedence in time, the firſt that euer was ordained in this world, how happens it, that you giue it no better entertainment a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you? doth it not neceſſarilie follow,
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:19591:84"/>that Church and common-wealth both muſt partake euident loſſe, when either it is ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanelie polluted, or not ſet by? when it is bereft of the fruit of mariage, which are chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, robd of thoſe ſweet loue pledges? when you vntie that knot, which is knit faſter, than any knot that fire and water, bed and boord, or plighting of troth, did euer tie? Why, who will take any paines to bring vp his children, if after all his care taken, and coſts beſtowed, when all is done, they muſt be another mans children, and not the fathers? If by direct au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie or indeed rather by a kind of Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meticall immanitie, they be hald and lugd away from their parents? if as ſoone as our wiues be brought to bed, and deliuered, the ſhaueling that firſt can ſeize vpon our child muſt haue him for his paines? he that robs a father of his child, a foſter father of his fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter ſonne, or a maſter of his man, in the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of <hi>Tertullian</hi> writing againſt <hi>Marcion,</hi> commits an act of impietie againſt God, ſins againſt the parent, wrongs the foſter father, and treſpaſſes againſt the maſter. To take away filiall obedience, and dutie to parents, is to grub vp nature by the root, to windſhake all that commerce and ſocietie, which is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween man &amp; man, euen from the very grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d plot, and foundation. Obedience ſaith <hi>S. Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian</hi>
               <pb n="157" facs="tcp:19591:84"/>in his booke of the abuſes of the world, is the mother of all gouernment, then fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well all gouernment when parents cannot be obeied. And becauſe paritie in honour and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate breeds quarrells and contention, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hath God made many formes of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, many of ſubiection. As husband and wife, father and ſonne, old and yong, bond and free, Prince and ſubiect, maſter and ſcholler, as S. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſpeaks in his Epiſtle to the Romanes, take away theſe ſubordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and there is no companie or ſocietie of men can poſſiblie continue. Nay the conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion cannot be gainſaid, doe but once proue diſobedient to parents, and preſentlie you fall downe headlong into Atheiſme, or hereſie, as it is deliuered with common conſent, by all ſorts of men, as well Chriſtians as heathen; and by name, by <hi>Plutarch</hi> in his booke <hi>de fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terna amicitia,</hi> and by the author of a late diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe. But it were better to hear the Authors in their owne words. There is no man ſaith <hi>Plutarch,</hi> who though he thinke otherwiſe in his conſcience, would not affirme and in words maintaine that the Gods ought to bee worſhipped in the firſt place, our parents next to them, and that in ſo large an extent, that nothing can be ſo acceptable to the Gods as when they ſee children repaying ſome v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurie
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:19591:85"/>for their parents bounty, whereas they be not able to pay the principal. Contrariwiſe that there is no argument ſo pregnant, to conuince them of Atheiſme, as by deſpiſing their parents, and treſpaſſing neuer ſo ſleight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt them. The other vtters himſelfe thus; What makes yong men now a daies ſo ſoone turne ſchiſmatiques? why ſaith he, they do not honor their parents, as they ought to do, as if he ſhould haue ſaid, it is no great wonder if they forſake the faith and religion of their forefathers, when they once take a taſte of contempt and diſobedience againſt their naturall parents. Good God, if ſuch diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyall behauiour might either be endured or commended, what? ought this to be a time for ſuch tolleration? to be a place? where there is ſcarce to be found any one, who by ſome meanes or other claimes not an immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, from doing his duty to God, or the king, or the Magiſtrate, or laſtly to his Elders? why but all theſe preheminences are to be found in a father, all theſe relations of duty in a ſon. Is it then honeſt and conuenient for mee, to ſhew any countenance to him that beſides his graceleſſe neglect: of mee, is ſo vngrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and irreuerent? In the latter daies (as S. <hi>Paul</hi> writeth to <hi>Timothie) there ſhall come perilous times, men ſhall be louers of themſelues,
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:19591:85"/>blaſphemers, diſobedient to fathers and mothers vngratefull, without naturall affection.</hi> Shouldſt thou now replie and ſay, why but good fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, after I am once profeſt into religion, I will honor you a great deale the more, I will eſteem of you much more highly than be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore? I tell thee againe, duty can neuer ſpring from diſobedience. Beſides all this, I would faine know what colour can be giuen, why thoſe grand ſchoole men, as <hi>Scotus, Durandus, Aquinas, Paludanus, Dominicus Soto,</hi> and many mo, ſhould enter into ſuch ſerious and deepe diſputes, whether the children of infidells might lawfullie be baptized againſt their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents will, <hi>Thomas</hi> abſolutelie holds that they may not, and ſaies that the Church neuer per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted ſuch a baptiſm, (not Pope <hi>Silueſter</hi> to <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the great, nor <hi>S. Ambroſe</hi> to <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odoſius</hi>) And yet to make no queſtion of main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining this doctrine, that our children may bind themſelues by a religious vow, though the father neuer ſo much proteſt againſt it. Doubtleſſe if the parents be chriſtians, the generall tenent is, that they may be forceably compelled, to initiate their children in the ſame religion: but if it be but a particular rule or couent of Regulars, then they hold they may not, for that is left to their owne diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. As for example, they ſay, that to be
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:19591:86"/>baptized in the faith of Chriſt it is ſufficient for any: but to be of Dominickes or S. <hi>Auſtins</hi> order, it is not neceſſary. But were a man Iew or Gentile, Saint <hi>Thomas</hi> peremptorily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, that either in caſe he bee of full age, hee ſhould be violently conſtrained, or being vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der yeares, his parents ſhould bee forced to yeeld their conſent to his baptiſme. And the Toletane Councell, whereof you ſhall finde Recorde in <hi>Gratians</hi> decrees, at the fiue and fortith diſtinction, in the chapter of the Iews. And <hi>Gregory</hi> the greate, writing to <hi>Virgilius</hi> and <hi>Theodorus,</hi> Biſhoppes of Fraunce, in his fiue and fortieth Epiſtle; If you liſt (ſaith he) you may ſpeake him fairelye, and aske him whether hee likes better, to liue in a cloyſter, then in the worlde at large. But I pray you tell mee, is it force or fayre dealing when ſuch a promiſe as this hath beene extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from him <hi>(as to ſay I will be a monke)</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to keep him a cloſe priſoner, or to lead and driue him vp and downe, to the intent he ſhall neuer light vpon his father or any one of his kinne, which might perchance diuert him from that reſolution, which was put vpon him before hee came to yeares, or in the prime of his youth when (as <hi>Cicero</hi> ſaith) counſell and diſcretion is at the weakeſt? What ſir, are you become an other <hi>Hercules Prodicus,</hi> that muſt
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:19591:86"/>forſooth by and by be wiſe, as ſoone as you are eighteene? what, is there no other courſe to be held, for the furniſhing of Churches and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſteries, but that children doe preſently ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iure their parents ſight and company, as if they were baniſhed perſons? the Church of God neuer allowed of this courſe, but in the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Iews, which was to this end, that hauing bene once voluntarily Chriſtned; they might not afterwards relapſe into their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents errors. And ſo it is in the Canon. But for one Chriſtian brother to ſuſpect or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt an other, in ſuch a caſe as this, of infide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity or Iudaiſme, what manner of ſtrange Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell were this? how can any man make this good, that whereas by the diſcipline of the Church, Prieſts may not bleſſe the married couple, if they be not giuen by their parents, a Biſhop of one Dioceſe may not giue orders to one of another Dioceſe, without the leaue of his Dioceſan: A Clarke that is a forrayner may not bee entertained to ſerue any where, without letters <hi>dimiſſoryes,</hi> or a certificat from him that made him: but our ſonnes and our daughters may make vowes, which ſhal be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited &amp; accepted of, though there beno giuing no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mending of them, no aprouing of them? yet the vovv muſt ſtil be obſerued. And now at length to conclude all this diſcourſe, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:19591:87"/>hath beene hitherto alleadged againſt thee, reckon thou of it at thy pleaſure, make as light account of my fatherly authority as thou wilt, or rather as they pleaſe to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand thee to make, with whom thou liueſt in ſo bleſſed and deifying an eſtate, yet ſuch as be well borne, not of baſe kinde, will bee of a different opinion from thee, and thinke it built vppon foure maine columnes. The principal piller which beares vp the fabrique, is the indignation of the liuing God, that eſteemes a wrong done to parents as done to himſelfe. How ill is the report of him that forſaketh his Father (ſaith the Preacher,) and accurſed of God that is bitter to his mother? The ſecond is the iudgement of baniſhment, which the Father pronounceth againſt him for his vndutifulneſſe. Depart from me, come no more in my ſight: for albeit, (as it ſhould appeare) thou haſt but a very meane conceipt of it, yet very certaine it is, that Gods ſeuerity is then greateſt, when a Father wil not vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to ſee his childe, a Prince not deigne to looke vpon his ſubiect, nor admit them vnto their preſence, which ought to be moſt glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom &amp; cheerfull to them. I ſaid Gods ſeueritie was then greateſt, for is it not ſo that euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting damnation of body and ſoule conſiſteth only in the depriuatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Gods bleſſed viſion,
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:19591:87"/>and Gods bleſſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the wages and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward that man, can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> for from God? And men vſe to be muſt ſeuere likewiſe in this kind. For <hi>Dauid</hi> puniſhed <hi>Abſalon</hi> ſo. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, after two yeeres ſpace continued in this diſgrace, oh (ſaith hee) if my Father bee yet mindfull of mine iniquity, good <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oab,</hi> be thou a ſuiter for mee rather that hee will kill mee? And did not <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lius Torquatus</hi> proceed in the ſelfe ſame manner againſt <hi>Iunius Syllarius</hi> of whome the Macedonians complained of for briberie and extortion. Becauſe thou haſt not (ſaith hee) demeaned thy ſelfe ſo in thy office, as thy woorthy Anceſtors haue done before thee, therfore I forbid thee from henceforth euer to approach vnto my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> ſurely hee was not able to endure the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, he ſlew himſelfe. The like is repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of <hi>Marcus Scaurus,</hi> that when his ſon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned diſhonourably out of the field, ſent him this meſſage, ſince I heare you are turned baſe coward, let me neuer ſee you more. The meſſage deliuered, he fel vpon his ſword with more valour and reſolution than euer before he had vſed againſt the enemy. And <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar,</hi> when one <hi>Tarrius</hi> his ſon was conuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted before him for the like offen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, gaue this iudgement, that hee was puniſhed with a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, whom the Father would not endure once
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:19591:88"/>to looke vpon. <hi>Plato</hi> yeelds an excellent rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, if there bee no ſhrines in the Temple ſo beautifull in the eie of the children to looke on as the portraiture of the Gods, no treaſure ſo pretious at home, as their aged and impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent parents, what worſe puniſhment can you deuiſe againſt them, than ſo to doom them, as to depriue them of their preſence, that be the patro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gods of their family, &amp; neuer to be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, to touch or to kiſſe them more. If ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment ſeeme only in this reſpect, a puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment intollerable, becauſe it depriues vs of beholding certaine faire buildings, and tomb ſtones, which we term monuments, what then may we thinke of ſuch a puniſhment as wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we ſhall be bard, of their ſweet companie that erected ſuch ſumptuous buildings for vs, nay erected vs? that would poſſeſſe no more then what they might leaue after their death to vs their children. Now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the King, <hi>Auguſtus Caeſars</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample is at hand to proue it, who vppon a reuenge to puniſh the Athenians choſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ariue at the Iland <hi>Aegina</hi> which was much out of his way, than (as he thought) to do them ſo much honor as to be ſeen at <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens.</hi> The like example haue we in <hi>Marcus Antonius</hi> the Philoſopher that trauailing by
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:19591:88"/>
               <hi>Antiochia</hi> would not be entreated to come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the City, becauſe they took part with <hi>Aui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius.</hi> Freſh alſo is the example of <hi>Charles</hi> the eight our French king, who comming with his army back from the expedition of <hi>Naples,</hi> and rendring his deuout thanks to God at S. <hi>Denis</hi> for the victory, would not ſo much as endure to come at <hi>Paris,</hi> becauſe they aided him not in his iourny for the wars. The third ſort of animaduerſion which pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, euer had, and euer ſhall haue, (as ſaith <hi>S. Ambroſe</hi> in that one book of his which he entitles <hi>de be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedictionibus patriarcharum,</hi>) is that bleſſing which they giue to their kind and dutifull children, and that curſe which they denounce againſt vnnaturall and diſobedient ones. The fathers bleſſing (as <hi>Elias</hi> the Cretia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpeaketh) is the wages of obedience, and therefore S. <hi>Gregory</hi> that had bin dutifull to his father, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires not that he would giue him his bleſſing, but that he would pay it him for his ſeruice. But be it that thou value it not at any ſuch high rate as <hi>Iacob,</hi> or <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> or <hi>Nazianzene,</hi> yet I would wiſh thee ſtand in feare of the curſe. Remember <hi>Noahs</hi> ſonnes, think on that which is written in <hi>Deuteronomy</hi> and is ſecond in order of the Comminations: <hi>Curſed is he that honoureth not his father and mother and</hi>
               <pb n="166" facs="tcp:19591:89"/>all the people ſhall ſay Amen. Meditate of that which is written in the third of <hi>Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticus,</hi> the bleſſing of the father eſtabliſheth the houſes of their children, but the curſe of the mother roots vp the foundatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: al which you ſhall find in <hi>Antiochus</hi> who was him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a Monk, in his 108. Homilie. Look vpon that in <hi>Homer</hi> his 2. Odiſſea, where <hi>Telema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus</hi> ſtands fearefull to caſt his mother out of doores, becauſe of her curſe. Call to thy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance that which is written by <hi>Plato,</hi> in the eleuenth book of his Lawes, how that all thoſe imprecations of <hi>Oedipus, Amynter,</hi> and <hi>Theſeus</hi> vttered againſt their children, were entertained and ratified in heauen, oh there is nothing in the word ſaith he ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious to a child, as the curſe of his father! Laſtly bethinke thou of that which is in <hi>Sui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> of <hi>Leo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tius</hi> a Biſhop of <hi>Tripoly,</hi> whoſe praier God almighty heard, and that was, that his ſonne might rather die, than that he ſhould ſee him liue a graceleſſe &amp; diſſolute life. The laſt remedy that parents may vſe in this caſe, is the helpe of the Iudge who vpon complaint made, ſeuerely cenſures or impriſons the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders, and giues ſuch iudgement againſt them, as the parents do require. For ſo <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> the Emperour anſwered one that made
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:19591:89"/>the like petition. All hard meaſure, and rigor would be vſed towards a ſaucie and malepart ſonne, though ſhould a ſtranger ſo offend, the offence I grant were not ſo hainous. And what is the reaſon? mary ſir, that children might not ſo much as conceiue, that there was any thing in the world more ſacred or inuiolable than their parents. It is ſtoried in the French Chronicles in the raigne of King <hi>Lewis,</hi> that <hi>Steuen Boley</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoſt of <hi>Paris,</hi> cauſed one to be hangd, for no other reaſon, but that his mother had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of him, that do what ſhe could do, he would neuer leaue filching and ſtealing. To conclude then, that may be ſpoken to you which <hi>Ierom</hi> hath in his book <hi>de honora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dis pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentibus,</hi> you that wil be fathers hereafter, you muſt honor your fathers, and loue your mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers with a tender affection, that your wiues after you be married may deſerue to be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers alſo. It remains therfore that if you haue a purpoſe to free thy ſelfe from theſe puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which as thou ſeeſt all lawes do inflict vpon a diſobedient ſon, and if this diſcourſe of mine, worke ſo well with thee that thou come to thy ſelfe again, if there be any good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in thee, bethinke thee of thy dutie in Gods name, preſentlie and out of hand thus
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:19591:90"/>doe, fulfill Chriſts parable in me, let vs make good chear my friends and be merrie, for this my ſon was dead and is aliue, loſt and now is found. The Church hath her armes alwaies open, to embrace the penitent ſoule (it is true) yet this mercifull diſpoſition they firſt lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from parents. Before thou canſt crie, I will heare thee, come then and we will bee friends, returne vnto me and all ſhall be well: and now will I vſe the like words to thee as <hi>S. Bernard</hi> did to his nephew: Againſt all due proceeding of law, I, that haue been wronged, doe yet withdrawne mine action, I haue bin offended and deſpiſed, yet ſue I vnto the ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, I haue been iniuriouſly dealt withall, yet I offer ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds vnto him that did me the wrong, and in few words, I ſeek vnto him that firſt ſhould haue beſought me. Or to vſe the ſpeech of <hi>Caeſarius,</hi> in his 30. homilie, he that is the iudge entreates to pardon the priſoner: but if they buz into thy head that when thou ſhalt once be fiue and twenty yeers old, then maiſt thou be at thy owne diſpoſition, and after that age who can challenge thee for thy diſobedience. I tell thee ſonne, and tel thee againe, though naturall duty, can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be dayde nor yeard, nor determined by age, or elderſhip, nay the more yeers the more
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:19591:90"/>duty, (whereupon <hi>Plato</hi> vſed more ſeueritie to one of thirty, then to one vnder fiue and twenty, for being vndutifull to his father, (I tell thee I ſay, hadſt thou been with me, and ſo continued to the terme of lawfull age, by that time, in likelihood I might haue yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſomwhat vnto thee, eſpecially if I had ſeen a ſuitable diſpoſition in thee for that kind of life, whereunto thou waſt addicted. But now the caſe is far otherwiſe, for as a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man child vnder the age of twelue being for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced and abuſed, by any man, and ſhe after the rape committed abide with the rauiſher, can not be ſaid all that while to be of yeers, and theres anullity in the mariage, if any ſuch be contracted between them, as it hath been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed in the Councel of <hi>Trent:</hi> ſo what age ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer thou comeſt to in that place, where thou art kept priſoner much againſt my will, think not that any ſuch aduantage acrues thereby, but may be void, and fruſtrate, to the intent either of law or religion, notwithſtanding all your preſcription. Would you haue a reaſon? why ſir, becauſe the Ieſuits ſeduced thee, and ſtill deteine thee, with an euill conſcience, and a ſca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dalous example. The excuſe wil not ſerue to ſay, the action was the holy ghoſts, for ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the holie Ghoſt hath no hand in a ſinful
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:19591:91"/>action. As ſtolne goods till they come home to the true owner, be ſtill felonious, ſo be the neuer ſo old, and continue with them neuer ſo long, thou ſhalt neuer be better then felons goods. Is there anie tells thee the contrarie? tell him againe, and ſay that <hi>Plato</hi> ſaid it, Sir you are much ſcanted in the faculties and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of your vnderſtanding: For there is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther God nor good man were he well in his wits, that would enueagle any mans child to be vndutifull to his parents.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:19591:91" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
